<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Most Recent Articles: Frontiers in Zoology</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com</link><description>Most Recent Articles: Frontiers in Zoology</description><item><title>Cloning and functional analysis of the molting gene CYP302A1 of Daphnia sinensis</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-023-00483-2</link><description>Molting is an important physiological process in the growth and development of arthropoda, which is mainly regulated by juvenile hormone and ecdysone. CYP302A1 is a key enzyme which plays a critical role in th...</description><category>Research</category><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-023-00483-2</guid><dc:creator>Huiying Qi, Huijuan Cao, Yajie Zhao, Yaqin Cao, Qide Jin, Yeping Wang, Kun Zhang and Daogui Deng</dc:creator><dc:date>2023-01-12T00:00:00Z</dc:date></item><item><title>Chromosome-level genome assembly of a high-altitude-adapted frog (Rana kukunoris) from the Tibetan plateau provides insight into amphibian genome evolution and adaptation</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00482-9</link><description>The high-altitude-adapted frog Rana kukunoris, occurring on the Tibetan plateau, is an excellent model to study life history evolution and adaptation to harsh high-altitude environments. However, genomic resource...</description><category>Research</category><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00482-9</guid><dc:creator>Wei Chen, Hongzhou Chen, Jiahong Liao, Min Tang, Haifen Qin, Zhenkun Zhao, Xueyan Liu, Yanfang Wu, Lichun Jiang, Lixia Zhang, Bohao Fang, Xueyun Feng, Baowei Zhang, Kerry Reid and Juha Merilä</dc:creator><dc:date>2023-01-06T00:00:00Z</dc:date></item><item><title>Antennal sensory structures of Phenacoccus solenopsis (Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae)</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00479-4</link><description>The cotton mealybug Phenacoccus solenopsis Tinsley (Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae) is one of the most devastating sap-sucking pests of cultivated plants. The success of P. solenopsis is attributable to its ecological...</description><category>Research</category><pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00479-4</guid><dc:creator>Nesreen M. Abd El-Ghany, Jing-Jiang Zhou and Youssef Dewer</dc:creator><dc:date>2022-12-15T00:00:00Z</dc:date></item><item><title>Social dynamics impact scolding behaviour in captive groups of common ravens (Corvus corax)</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00477-6</link><description>Predator avoidance can have immense impacts on fitness, yet individual variation in the expression of anti-predator behaviour remains largely unexplained. Existing research investigating learning of novel pred...</description><category>Research</category><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00477-6</guid><dc:creator>Christian R. Blum, W. Tecumseh Fitch and Thomas Bugnyar</dc:creator><dc:date>2022-12-12T00:00:00Z</dc:date></item><item><title>Competitive ability is a fast-evolving trait between house mouse populations (Mus musculus domesticus)</title><link>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00476-7</link><description>House mice are commensal animals with a nearly global distribution, structured into well differentiated local populations. Besides genetic differences between the populations, they have also diverged behaviora...</description><category>Research</category><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><guid>https://frontiersinzoology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12983-022-00476-7</guid><dc:creator>Miriam Linnenbrink</dc:creator><dc:date>2022-12-08T00:00:00Z</dc:date></item></channel></rss>