<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>TechCrunch</title>
	<atom:link href="https://techcrunch.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://techcrunch.com/</link>
	<description>Startup and Technology News</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 04:02:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/cropped-cropped-favicon-gradient.png?w=32</url>
	<title>TechCrunch</title>
	<link>https://techcrunch.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>So much fintech M&#038;A</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/so-much-fintech-ma/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/so-much-fintech-ma/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mary Ann Azevedo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 15:15:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Interchange]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[venture capital]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470315</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to The Interchange! If you received this in your inbox, thank you for signing up and your vote of confidence. If you’re reading this as a post on our site, sign up here so you can receive it directly in the future. Every week, I’ll take a look at the hottest fintech news of the previous week. [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/so-much-fintech-ma/">So much fintech M&#038;A</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/mary-ann-azevedo/">Mary Ann Azevedo</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary"><em>Welcome to <a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/the-interchange/">The Interchange</a>! If you received this in your inbox, thank you for signing up and your vote of confidence. If you’re reading this as a post on our site, sign up </em><a href="http://techcrunch.com/newsletters"><em>here</em></a><em> so you can receive it directly in the future. Every week, I’ll take a look at the hottest fintech news of the previous week. This will include everything from funding rounds to trends to an analysis of a particular space to hot takes on a particular company or phenomenon. There’s a lot of fintech news out there and it’s my job to stay on top of it — and make sense of it — so you can stay in the know. — </em><a href="https://twitter.com/bayareawriter" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Mary Ann</em></a></p>
<h2>Consolidation everywhere</h2>
<p>On Friday, January 13, investment giant <strong>BlackRock</strong> announced it was acquiring a minority stake in SMB 401(k) provider startup <strong>Human Interest</strong>. Terms of the deal weren’t disclosed, but it definitely caught my attention for a few reasons. For one, as one source told me, BlackRock’s investment is a show of faith in the SMB 401(k) market — one where the firm hasn’t historically played. That same source, who preferred not to be named, pointed out that “SECURE 2.0&#8217;s auto-enrollment provisions (among others), will make 401k plans more impactful at the lower end of the market, and Human Interest is well-positioned to execute.”</p>
<p>I’ve been writing about Human Interest since March 2020, covering each of its funding rounds since then (<a href="https://news.crunchbase.com/venture/human-interest-raises-40m-series-c-to-close-retirement-savings-gap-for-smbs/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/02/11/401k-provider-human-interest-doubles-valuation-with-55m-fundraise/">here</a> and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/08/04/human-interest-raises-200m-at-a-1b-valuation-plans-for-an-ipo/">here</a>), and following its impressive growth. It achieved unicorn status in August 2021 and at the time was eyeing an IPO. A lot has changed in the markets since then, so this feels like a good outcome for the startup, which was founded by Paul Sawaya and Roger Lee in 2015. Lee (a very nice guy, incidentally) moved on years ago, recently founding another startup, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/10/04/this-startup-wants-to-help-other-startups-figure-out-compensation/">Comprehensive.io</a> and launching layoff tracker <a href="https://layoffs.fyi/">Layoffs.FYI</a> soon after the COVID-19 pandemic hit.</p>
<p>The deal was just one of many M&amp;A deals in the fintech space that occurred last week. Here’s a rundown of some others:</p>
<ul>
<li>Remote payroll startup <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/deel/">Deel</a></strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/deel-enters-equity-management-space-with-acquisition-of-capbase/">acquired fintech <strong>Capbase</strong></a> for an undisclosed amount in a cash and stock deal, the companies shared with me exclusively. Last valued at $12 billion, Deel is one of the buzziest fintechs around, and its decision to pick up Capbase reflects its intent to enter the equity management space.</li>
<li>Investment giant <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/fidelity-snaps-up-fintech-shoobx-after-7-years-without-an-acquisition/"><strong>Fidelity</strong> acquired <strong>Shoobx</strong></a>, marking its first buy in 7 years (!). Jason Furtado and Stephan Richter founded Boston-based Shoobx in 2013, according to Crunchbase. The pair went on to raise a known $10 million in funding for the company. Fidelity said its purchase of Shoobx is a sign of its commitment to the private market “and will help to satisfy an increasing demand Fidelity sees from private companies to support them as they scale and grow.”</li>
<li><strong>Vouch,</strong> an insurtech focused on startups,<a href="https://www.lifeinsuranceinternational.com/news/insurtech-vouch-buys-level/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> acquired lending startup <strong>Level</strong></a> for an undisclosed amount. As reported by Life Insurance International: “Level has created a tech-driven underwriting process for early-stage fintech startups that is claimed to have brought new efficiency and speed to the debt-raising process. Vouch hopes to leverage Level’s expertise in developing underwriting technologies to underwrite and support complex insurance products. Level was founded by Vladimir Korshin, Asa Schachar and Molly Hogan in 2021.” In September 2021, I covered Vouch’s announcement of <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/09/10/vouch-business-insurance-provider-to-startups-raises-90m-and-is-now-valued-at-550m/">$90 million in new funding</a>. Both Vouch and Level are Y Combinator alums.</li>
<li><strong>American Express</strong> announced that it has entered into an agreement <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/amex-axp-acquire-nipendo-eye-185706016.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to acquire <strong>Nipendo</strong>,</a> a company that aims to automate and streamline business-to-business (B2B) payments processes for global businesses that has raised a known $12 million in funding. I talked with Dean Henry, EVP of global commercial services for Amex, and Colleen Taylor, president of merchant services, US at Amex, and they gave me some insight into the strategy behind the buy. For starters, Henry said the credit card giant has been on “a multiyear journey…to really grow and expand capabilities in B2B payments.” He added: “What we&#8217;ve really tried to evolve in the last few years is into a one-stop-shop for businesses to pay anybody anywhere, using any kind of payment rails that they want to use in order to facilitate the payments….What we&#8217;re trying to do with Nipendo is add to that capability set and provide more value to suppliers who are trying to send invoices, interact with buyers and transact with data around B2B payments.” Notably, Taylor told me that American Express concluded that it would take a big company like American Express “a long time to replicate what they&#8217;ve built.&#8221; And this line was the classic motivation for all incumbents buying fintechs: &#8220;Why not just bring it in to our platform and get it to customers as quickly as possible?”</li>
</ul>
<p>To bring some context around all this M&amp;A, I conducted an email interview with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jonahcranefintech/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jonah Crane</a>, partner at <strong>Klaros Group</strong>. Crane predicts we will continue to see a lot of fintech M&amp;A.</p>
<p>He told me: “The question I have is who will capitalize on this bear market to scoop up valuable technology or talent. In particular, I’m interested in whether banks can be opportunistic. Some of the large banks have already been active, and the others need to ask themselves whether they are serious about innovation and digital transformation. If they are, they can’t afford to miss this moment.”</p>
<p>Of course, he added, much will depend on the macro picture. “If we have a soft landing, and markets head back up, the true bargains may already have passed. And if we are in for a very hard landing, buyers are at risk of catching falling knives—especially in the credit sector,” Crane said. “Getting deals done in these markets is no sure thing. We’ve already seen a number of announced deals fail to close: UBS/Wealthfront, Bolt/Wyre, and now JPMC/Frank (more on that later). Ultimately, the big challenge will be whether buyers and sellers can cross the massive valuation chasm created by the bursting of the fintech bubble.”</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>No doubt the venture slowdown and practically dead IPO and SPAC markets have contributed to the surge in M&amp;A activity.</p>
<p>“VCs are telling their portfolio companies they should be prepared to shelter in place for 18 to 24 months, and many have laid off a lot of staff. But what’s the end game? What are you aiming to achieve that will allow you to raise at a reasonable valuation when markets are fully reopened?” Crane asks. “Those who don’t have a clear bridge to the other side of that chasm will be looking for buyers (if they’re smart).”</p>
<p>All I know is if we have more weeks like this one, you’re going to have one exhausted fintech journalist on your hands!</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2100919" style="width: 1210px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2100919" decoding="async" class="wp-image-2100919 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg" alt="a blank check and a pen" width="1200" height="720" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg?resize=150,90 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg?resize=300,180 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg?resize=768,461 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg?resize=680,408 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/01/GettyImages-843044658.jpg?resize=50,30 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2100919" class="wp-caption-text">check pen</p></div></p>
<h2>Weekly News</h2>
<p><strong><em>Layoffs</em></strong></p>
<p>Reports Jagmeet Singh: “<strong>Greenlight</strong>, a fintech startup offering debit cards to kids, has laid off 104 employees — or over 21% of its total headcount of 485 employees — to “better align with ongoing operating expenses” amid the economic slowdown. TechCrunch learned about the layoff that was announced to its employees earlier this week. The startup later confirmed the development over an email.” More <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/greenlight-fintech-layoff/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Digital mortgage platform <strong>Blend</strong> said last week its slashing its U.S. workforce by 28%, or 340 jobs, in its fourth layoff in less than a year. The company also said that president <a href="https://www.housingwire.com/podcast/tim-mayopoulos-on-leading-blend-after-leaving-fannie-mae/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tim Mayopoulos</a> will step down from his role in the first quarter and remain as a board member. Clearly, the rise in mortgage interest rates has taken its toll. More <a href="https://therealdeal.com/2023/01/11/mortgage-firm-blend-cuts-30-of-staff/">here</a>.</p>
<p>Publicly-traded online lending platform <strong>Lending Club</strong> is cutting 14% of its workforce, a move that will impact 225 employees, reports <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/lendingclub-to-lay-off-14-of-staff-as-higher-interest-rates-weigh-11673558656">MarketWatch</a>, &#8220;as higher interest rates discourage demand for loans, and the company forecast fourth-quarter revenue that was below expectations.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong><em>In other news</em></strong></p>
<p><strong>Public.com</strong>, an investing platform with more than 3 million members, announced last week that it has begun <a href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230111005253/en/Investing-Platform-Public-Introduces-Treasury-Accounts" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rolling out Treasury accounts</a> through a partnership with fintech startup <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/10/06/fintech-jiko-banks-40m-in-series-b-funding-for-scaleable-money-storage/"><strong>Jiko</strong></a>. According to the two companies, the accounts allow members to invest their cash in U.S. Treasury bills that “are automatically reinvested at maturity and can be sold at any time.” A spokesperson told me that Public’s Treasury accounts “offer members similar flexibility to a high-yield savings account, but are currently offering even higher yields.”</p>
<p>Equity management platform<strong> Carta</strong> had a rough week. As TC&#8217;s Connie Loizos reported on January 11: &#8220;The 11-year-old, San Francisco-based outfit whose core business is selling software to investors to track their portfolios, has <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/carta-previously-sued-for-gender-discrimination-is-now-suing-its-former-cto/">sued its former CTO</a>, Jerry Talton, who the company says was fired &#8216;for cause&#8217; almost three weeks ago, on Friday, December 23.&#8221; The case is a bit of a sordid one, considering that &#8220;toward the end of Carta’s long list of accusations against Talton, Carta says that Talton both sent and received &#8216;sexually explicit, offensive, discriminatory and harassing messages with at least nine women including during work hours and on Carta’s systems.'&#8221; For his part, Connie also wrote that Talton was put on administrative leave in October of last year after submitting a letter to Carta’s board of directors, flagging various “problems” with the company’s culture. Then, Natasha reported later that day that the company, which was last privately valued at $7.4 billion, had <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/carta-lays-off-10-as-cto-lawsuit-looms/">cut 10% of its staff</a>.</p>
<p><strong><i>It looks like incumbent banks and institutions are still struggling when it comes to offering tech-enabled financial services.</i></strong></p>
<p>For one, <strong>Goldman Sachs Group</strong> reported last Thursday that it lost $3.03 billion on its platform solutions business that houses transaction banking and credit card and financial technology businesses since 2020. Reuters <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/finance/goldman-sachs-reports-12-bln-loss-platform-solutions-unit-2023-01-13/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reports</a>: “The disclosure did not provide separate numbers for its direct-to-consumer business, Marcus, which was moved into its asset and wealth management arm. Marcus has also lost money and failed to introduce a checking account. Swati Bhatia, who led the group, <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/finance/goldman-sachs-consumer-banking-unit-head-steps-down-memo-2023-01-03/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">stepped down</a> earlier this month, according to an internal announcement seen by Reuters.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, <strong>Wells Fargo</strong> is taking a step back from mortgages. CNBC <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/01/10/wells-fargo-once-the-no-1-player-in-mortgages-is-stepping-back-from-the-housing-market.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported</a>: “Instead of its previous goal of reaching as many Americans as possible, the company will now focus on home loans for existing bank and wealth management customers and borrowers in minority communities.” Interestingly, in an interview with CNBC, CEO Charlie Scharf acknowledged that the bank “will need to adapt to evolving conditions” while remaining confident about its competitive advantage. Specifically, he said: “Given the quality of the five major businesses across the franchise, we think we’re positioned to compete against the very best out there and win, whether it’s banks, nonbanks or fintechs.” To me, it feels like the move to shrink back from the housing market might open up more opportunities for fintechs.</p>
<p>Lastly, as referenced above, Forbes<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexandralevine/2023/01/11/jp-morgan-fake-customers-frank-charlie-javice/?sh=4e7243a214d4" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> reported</a> on an absolutely crazy account of <strong>JPMorgan</strong> basically getting duped by the founders of a startup, <strong>Frank</strong>, that it acquired for $175 million. Here’s an excerpt from the Forbes piece detailing a lawsuit filed by the banking giant, which claims that founder and former CEO Charlie Javice “pitched JP Morgan in 2021 on the ‘lie’ that more than 4 million users had signed up to use Frank’s tools to apply for federal aid. When JP Morgan asked for proof during due diligence, Javice allegedly created an enormous roster of &#8216;fake customers&#8217; — a list of names, addresses, dates of birth, and other personal information for 4.265 million ‘students’ who did not actually exist.” In reality, according to the suit, Frank had fewer than 300,000 customer accounts at that time.” Oof. What happened to due diligence here???</p>
<p><strong><em>More news</em></strong></p>
<p>According to research from <strong>Utility Bidder</strong>, there are said to currently be over 700 active unicorn companies in the U.S., 132 of which are in the fintech industry. The firm’s<a href="https://www.utilitybidder.co.uk/compare-business-energy/the-fintech-billion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> new study</a> has revealed the global fintech companies achieving the $1 billion valuation mark the fastest. Proptech <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/09/14/softbanks-latest-proptech-bet-is-leading-pacasos-125m-series-c/"><strong>Pacaso</strong></a> tops the list, taking just under six months to achieve unicorn status. Other companies on the list include Magic Eden, Clara, Brex and Pipe. The firm also ranked the <a href="https://www.utilitybidder.co.uk/compare-business-energy/the-fintech-billion/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">most valuable fintech companies</a>. Leading the way is <strong>Stripe</strong>, which actually just got <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/stripe-internal-valuation-63-billion-409a/">another internal valuation cut</a> and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/11/03/stripe-cuts-14-of-its-workforce-ceo-says-they-overhired-for-the-world-were-in/">laid off over 1,100 workers</a> last November. Ironically, a number of other startups that made the top 10 also happened to conduct layoffs over the past few months, including Plaid, Brex and Chime. Wondering why Utility Bidder cares about fintech? I did, too. Here’s what a spokesperson told me: “Utility Bidder [is] a price comparison site for energy and utility rates, so they have a focus on business finances as well as energy as a whole.&#8221;</p>
<p>Identity decisioning platform and fintech unicorn<strong><a href="http://alloy.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Alloy</a></strong> recently released its annual <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/more-than-two-thirds-of-financial-institutions-lost-over-500k-to-fraud-in-2022-alloy-report-finds-301715626.html?tc=eml_cleartime" target="_blank" rel="noopener">State of Fraud Benchmark Report</a>. The report found that 70% of financial institutions surveyed lost over half a million to fraud last year and that 27% of respondents lost over $1 million to fraud in the last 12 months. Further, 37% of fintech companies and 31% of regional banks estimated losing between $1 and $10 million to fraud.</p>
<p>A <strong>Morgan Stanley</strong> spokesperson reached out to me last week after seeing our coverage of Fidelity’s acquisition of Shoobx to let me know that “Morgan Stanley at Work has invested a lot of time and resources” in its Private Markets business, “and continues to see it as an area of growth — especially as we recently just saw an astounding uptick in liquidity events during Q4 2022, which further supports the idea that private companies/startups need an effective software solution to handle these complex transactions.” The firm acquired Solium, a cap table management solution platform now called <a href="http://shareworks.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Shareworks</a>, in 2019.</p>
<p><strong>Oracle</strong> <strong>Retail</strong> announced last week its new <a href="https://www.oracle.com/news/announcement/new-oracle-payment-cloud-service-gives-retailers-greater-transparency-and-pricing-flexibility-2023-01-12/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Oracle Retail Payment Cloud Service</a>. Via email, a spokesperson told me: “This new service equips retailers with a fixed rate model and the ability to accept all major contactless payment options including credit/debit cards and mobile wallets — all without hidden fees, long-term contracts or minimum monthly requirements. These benefits enable increased flexibility, agility and greater transparency for retailers of all sizes and industries…”</p>
<p><strong>Mesh Payments</strong> has brought on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/daniel-ochoa-6185435a_excited-and-honored-to-share-that-i-have-activity-7016880258054328320-Ryxs?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Daniel Ochoa</a> as its first SVP of global sales. Based in Austin, Ochoa most recently served as VP of sales and customer success at TripActions. Mesh co-founder and CEO Oded Zehavi told TechCrunch via email that Ochoa was brought on “to leverage a surge in customer demand” as the company builds out “new services to meet the needs of larger companies who are more than ready to move off of legacy spend management solutions.” Sounds like Mesh, like competitor Brex last year, is going after more enterprise customers.</p>
<p>Speaking of <strong>Brex</strong>, here’s a fun <a href="https://twitter.com/samdblond/status/1612518983726424080?s=20&amp;t=LXhFAJtafxx-WuZepG5xTQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tweet thread</a> from former CRO and current Founders Fund partner Sam Blond about “the best outbound campaign” Brex ever ran.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_1887124" style="width: 2010px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1887124" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-1887124 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/GettyImages-640267784-e1673659604988.jpg" alt="GettyImages 640267784" width="2000" height="1435" /><p id="caption-attachment-1887124" class="wp-caption-text">Bank sign on glass wall of business center; Image credit: Getty</p></div></p>
<h2>Funding and M&amp;A</h2>
<p><b><i>Seen on TechCrunch</i></b></p>
<p><em><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/from-cloud-computing-to-proptech-digital-ocean-co-founders-raise-29m-for-welcome-homes/">From cloud computing to proptech: DigitalOcean co-founders raise $29M for Welcome Homes</a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/fintech-mayfair-emerges-from-stealth-to-offer-businesses-a-higher-yield-on-their-cash/">Backed by Tiger Global, Mayfair emerges from stealth to offer businesses a higher yield on their cash</a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/vista-equity-partners-to-acquire-insurance-software-company-duck-creek-for-2-6b/">Vista Equity Partners to acquire insurance software company Duck Creek for $2.6B</a></em></p>
<p><em><b>And elsewhere</b></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://fintech.global/2023/01/12/social-investing-startup-investsky-picks-up-3-4m-pre-seed/">Dubai-based social investing startup InvestSky picks up $3.4M pre-seed</a><b> </b></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/fractal-homes-london-property-tech-startup-raises-30m-in-funding-2023-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Proptech that offers fractional home ownership to wealthy individuals raises $30M in debt and equity</a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://seekingalpha.com/news/3923696-pagaya-technologies-announces-acquisition-of-darwin-homes" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Pagaya Technologies announces acquisition of Darwin Homes</a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://www.pymnts.com/acquisitions/2023/nuvei-1-billion-dollar-paya-purchase/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canadian fintech Nuvei will acquire Atlanta-based payments firm Paya for $1.3B</a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://www.pymnts.com/news/investment-tracker/2023/40seas-raises-111m-to-grow-cross-border-trade-financing-platform/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">40Seas secures $11M in equity, $100M in credit to grow cross-border trade financing platform </a></em></p>
<p><em><a href="https://www.butterpayments.com/blog/butter-series-a-blog-post" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Butter raises $22M led by Norwest Venture Partners to end accidental payment churn</a></em></p>
<p><em><strong>Other stories I wrote this week:</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/these-5-companies-bootstrapped-their-way-to-big-businesses-while-vcs-came-knocking/">These 5 companies bootstrapped their way to big businesses while VCs came knocking</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/ftx-sbf-launches-substack-i-didnt-steal-funds-and-i-certainly-didnt-stash-billions-away/">Sam Bankman-Fried launches Substack: ‘I didn’t steal funds, and I certainly didn’t stash billions away’</a></p>
<p>And, I recorded Equity Pod with my incredible co-hosts Natasha Mascarenhas and Rebecca Szkutak: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/frank-ly-the-kardashian-method-wont-work-for-sbf/?tpcc=tcplustwitter">Frank-ly, the Kardashian method won’t work for SBF</a></p>
<p>Whew. This was one of the busiest weeks we&#8217;ve seen in a while. Hope those of you in the U.S. have a good and restful long weekend, and if you&#8217;re outside of the U.S., I hope you have a good and restful weekend as well. Until next time, take good care. xoxoxo — Mary Ann</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/so-much-fintech-ma/">So much fintech M&#038;A</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/mary-ann-azevedo/">Mary Ann Azevedo</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/so-much-fintech-ma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Climate tech roundup: From solar to CES, this week had something for everyone</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/climate-tech-roundup-from-solar-to-ces-this-week-had-something-for-everyone/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/climate-tech-roundup-from-solar-to-ces-this-week-had-something-for-everyone/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Tim De Chant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 15:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Batteries]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CES 2023]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate tech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Solar Power]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470113</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Even without a milestone fusion announcement this week, plenty happened in the climate tech world that’s worth catching up on.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/climate-tech-roundup-from-solar-to-ces-this-week-had-something-for-everyone/">Climate tech roundup: From solar to CES, this week had something for everyone</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/tim-de-chant/">Tim De Chant</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Hello, climate tech readers! Even without a milestone fusion announcement this week, plenty happened in the climate tech world that’s worth catching up on. From massive solar investments to plant-based steaks and small, modular batteries to back up your home, there’s something for everyone. Let’s dive in.</p>
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/us-solar-manufacturing-gets-boost-with-2-5b-georgia-deal/">US solar manufacturing gets boost with $2.5B Georgia deal</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2468593" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2468593" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2468593" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg" alt="Solar panels cover parked cars at Qcells' Georgia plant." width="1024" height="682" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg 4000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=1536,1023 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=2048,1364 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1232671596.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2468593" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Elijah Nouvelage/Bloomberg / Getty Images</p></div></p>
<p>Last year was chock full of battery manufacturers and automakers announcing one gigafactory after another. If this week’s announcement is anything to go by, 2023 might be the year the U.S. solar industry ramps up in a serious way.</p>
<p>On Wednesday, Hanwha Qcells, a major Korean manufacturer, announced that it would spend $2.5 billion in Georgia to expand an existing factory and build an entirely new campus that would handle nearly everything in the solar panel supply chain, from silicon ingots to finished panels. The move was spurred by the Inflation Reduction Act, which offers investment and production tax credits that should help cover about half the cost of a finished panel, helping to erase some of China’s cost advantage.</p>
<p>This isn’t the first time the U.S. has attempted to bolster homegrown solar. But unlike a decade ago, when dozens of companies went bust because of slack demand, cheap Chinese panels and the Great Recession, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/us-solar-manufacturing-gets-boost-with-2-5b-georgia-deal/">this time might be different</a>.</p>
<hr />
<p style="text-align: center;"><i>Full TechCrunch+ articles are only available to members.<br />
<a href="https://techcrunch.com/subscribe/">Use discount code <strong>TCPLUSROUNDUP</strong></a> to save 20% off a one- or two-year subscription.</i></p>
<hr />
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/how-companies-at-ces-are-taking-on-climate-change-or-pretending-to/">How companies at CES are taking on climate change (or pretending to)</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2466121" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2466121" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2466121" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg" alt="A Caterpillar sign at CES 2023 reads, &quot;JOIN US AS WE BUILD A BETTER WORLD.&quot;" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg 4032w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=150,113 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=300,225 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=768,576 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=680,510 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=1536,1152 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=2048,1536 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=1200,900 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0196.jpeg?resize=50,38 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2466121" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Harri Weber for TechCrunch</p></div></p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>TechCrunch’s Harri Weber made the trek to CES this year, and she saw plenty of climate tech at the massive trade show, which has expanded well beyond VR headsets and home automation (though <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/why-the-matter-logo-was-everywhere-at-ces-2023/">that’s still there</a>, too.) From smart hoses and sprinklers to minimize water use to home energy systems, there was plenty to be optimistic about — though there was still some AstroTurf, too, both on the show floor and in what was being hawked in the booths.</p>
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/project-eaden-fiber-technology-plant-based-meat/">Project Eaden’s fiber technology poised to spin threads into whole cuts of ‘meat’</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2467699" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467699" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2467699" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg" alt="Project Eaden plant-based meat alternative" width="1024" height="576" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg 1872w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IMG_0118_2.jpg?resize=50,28 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467699" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits</strong>: Project Eaden</p></div></p>
<p>Plant-based meat has had a rough few months, with industry leaders getting hammered in the markets. But <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/08/plant-based-foods-investor-says-her-focus-is-more-on-teams-than-taste/">not everyone is bearish</a> on the sector. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/project-eaden-fiber-technology-plant-based-meat/">Project Eaden showed why</a> this week, adding €2.1 million in funding to an existing seed round.</p>
<p>The Berlin-based startup uses plant-based protein fibers to spin cuts of alternative meat that have a texture that’s much closer to the real thing. Project Eaden has just over €10 million in funding to refine its technology, and it’s planning on future rounds to build a production-scale plant.</p>
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/climate-benefits-of-killing-gas-stoves-arent-what-you-think-but-the-health-benefits-are/">Climate benefits of killing gas stoves aren’t what you think, but the health benefits are</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2467057" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467057" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2467057" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg" alt="Blue flames burn on a gas stove." width="1024" height="682" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg 3679w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-95836681.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467057" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Daniele Carotenuto Photography / Getty Images</p></div></p>
<p>It’s no secret that gas stoves are terrible for your health — asthma rates in households that have gas stoves are significantly higher than those without. They’re also <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/climate-benefits-of-killing-gas-stoves-arent-what-you-think-but-the-health-benefits-are/">not great for the climate</a>. Even though their emissions footprint is small, they let aging gas utilities keep their feet in the door, making it easier for homeowners to keep their fossil fuel systems running long after they should.</p>
<p>But why are we talking about gas stoves this week? U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission Rich Trumka Jr. made a comment about how they’re a “hidden hazard” and that “any option is on the table” if the industry couldn’t figure out how to clean up its act. Well, that brought the wolves out. Right-wing politicians latched onto Trumka’s statement, hoping to create a new flashpoint in the ongoing culture wars. That might backfire, though, as <a href="https://twitter.com/JustinHGillis/status/1613573981025476608" target="_blank" rel="noopener">gas-owning, induction-curious consumers</a> start looking into the matter themselves.</p>
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/john-deere-will-let-farmers-repair-their-own-equipment/">John Deere will let farmers repair their own equipment</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2467540" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467540" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2467540" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg" alt="John Deere earth mover with large front bucket" width="1024" height="683" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg 5616w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/r4e037390_rrd_02.jpeg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467540" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> John Deere</p></div></p>
<p>The right-to-repair movement got a shot in the arm this week when <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/john-deere-will-let-farmers-repair-their-own-equipment/">John Deere signed a memorandum of understanding</a> with the American Farm Bureau Federation that would grant access to tools and repair information needed by farmers and other operators to fix the company’s increasingly complex equipment without going through the manufacturer.</p>
<p>For farmers and independent repair shops, it’s not a perfect deal, however, because Deere said it would still withhold “trade secrets, proprietary or confidential information.” But given that Deere has long pushed back against right-to-repair requests, this is likely welcome news for farmers, operators and independent shops. And it’ll likely help keep well-functioning equipment in the fields longer.</p>
<h2><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/07/batteries-batteries-everywhere/">A big CES 2023 trend: All battery power, everywhere, all the time</a></h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2466507" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2466507" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2466507" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="576" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg 2000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/20230105-IMG_2455.jpg?resize=50,28 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2466507" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> <a href="https://yoshinopower.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Yoshino <span class="screen-reader-text">(opens in a new window)</span></a></p></div></p>
<p>It’s happening: Batteries are taking over. I’ve long anticipated that the <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/05/05/batteries-have-become-vc-and-pes-most-electric-investment-opportunity/">sheer amount</a> of R&amp;D and manufacturing capacity wrought by the shift to electric vehicles would spill over to transform myriad <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/05/10/battery-startups-are-working-to-disrupt-more-than-just-cars-and-trucks/">other sectors</a>. If this year’s CES is anything to go by, we’ve reached an inflection point.</p>
<p>TechCrunch’s Haje Jan Kamps was <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/07/batteries-batteries-everywhere/">bowled over by the number and diversity</a> of battery-based home power solutions at the show this year. Many were stackable. One could be wheeled around your house like a 100-pound wagon. Another carried like a milk crate. And yet another ties into a whole-home system that includes a solar inverter, smart circuit panel, EV chargers and more. If you don’t have a battery in your home yet, you might in the next five years if this CES was anything to go by.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/climate-tech-roundup-from-solar-to-ces-this-week-had-something-for-everyone/">Climate tech roundup: From solar to CES, this week had something for everyone</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/tim-de-chant/">Tim De Chant</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/climate-tech-roundup-from-solar-to-ces-this-week-had-something-for-everyone/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Environmental health and safety software is now a hot commodity</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/environmental-health-and-safety-software-is-now-a-hot-commodity/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/environmental-health-and-safety-software-is-now-a-hot-commodity/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kyle Wiggers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 14:00:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Enterprise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EC Enterprise]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[funding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[SaaS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Software]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[venture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469369</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Environmental health and safety (EHS) software is having a moment. One report predicts that it'll be worth $2.7 billion by 2027.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/environmental-health-and-safety-software-is-now-a-hot-commodity/">Environmental health and safety software is now a hot commodity</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/">Kyle Wiggers</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Historically, environmental health and safety software hasn&#8217;t been a massive market — at least compared to others in the software-as-a-service segment — and it&#8217;s admittedly not the most enthralling startup category. But that&#8217;s changing, according to a new survey released by research firm Verdantix.</p>
<p>EHS software acts as a data management system for capturing and analyzing information related to occupational health and safety, waste management and sustainability. Companies use EHS software to track emissions and investigate workplace incidents, for example, as well as conduct health and safety training and grant entry to restricted spaces.</p>
<p>Verdantix&#8217;s Green Quadrant: EHS Software 2023 <a href="https://www.verdantix.com/report/green-quadrant-ehs-software-2023" target="_blank" rel="noopener">survey</a> shows that the EHS software market had more than 50 transactions in the past two years and predicts that it&#8217;ll grow from $1.6 billion in 2022 to around $2.7 billion by 2027. Verdantix predicts it&#8217;ll buck the global economic downturn, furthermore, due to differentiators like the use of AI and automation.</p>
<p>&#8220;Over the past two years, the market landscape for EHS software has undergone a paradigm shift, as EHS providers have expanded their product offerings to meet the ravenous appetite for robust environmental management solutions brought on by the ESG megatrend,&#8221; Verdantix industry analyst Chris Sayers said in a statement. &#8220;As EHS functions seek to interlink with other business operations, providers are turning to emerging technologies as a point of differentiation and redefining the functional possibilities of EHS software.&#8221;</p>
<p>Per the Verdantix report, since ETF Partners <a href="https://www.environmentalleader.com/2016/07/ehs-software-leader-enablon-completes-275-million-sale-to-wolters-kluwer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">invested</a> around €10 million (roughly $11 million) in EHS vendor Enablon in 2011, private equity firms and strategic investors like Wolters Kluwer and Fortive have spent more than $4 billion to buy into the EHS software market. The absence of the world’s largest enterprise software vendors — including IBM, Microsoft, Oracle, Salesforce and SAP — has left a lot of oxygen in the market for midsize businesses to grow.</p>
<p><div class="extra-crunch-offer-container"></div><p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/environmental-health-and-safety-software-is-now-a-hot-commodity/">Environmental health and safety software is now a hot commodity</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/">Kyle Wiggers</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/15/environmental-health-and-safety-software-is-now-a-hot-commodity/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CircleCI says hackers stole encryption keys and customers&#8217; secrets</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/circleci-hackers-stole-customer-source-code/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/circleci-hackers-stole-customer-source-code/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Zack Whittaker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 22:27:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Security]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cybersecurity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[data breach]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[devops]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stolen passwords]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470486</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>CircleCi, a software company whose products are popular with developers and software engineers, confirmed that some customers&#8217; data was stolen in a data breach last month. The company said in a detailed blog post on Friday that it identified the intruder&#8217;s initial point of access as an employee&#8217;s laptop that was compromised with malware, allowing [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/circleci-hackers-stole-customer-source-code/">CircleCI says hackers stole encryption keys and customers&#8217; secrets</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/zack-whittaker/">Zack Whittaker</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">CircleCi, a software company whose products are popular with developers and software engineers, confirmed that some customers&#8217; data was stolen in a <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/05/circleci-breach/">data breach</a> last month.</p>
<p>The company <a href="https://circleci.com/blog/jan-4-2023-incident-report">said in a detailed blog post</a> on Friday that it identified the intruder&#8217;s initial point of access as an employee&#8217;s laptop that was compromised with malware, allowing the theft of session tokens used to keep the employee logged in to certain applications, even though their access was protected with two-factor authentication.</p>
<p>The company took the blame for the compromise, calling it a &#8220;systems failure,&#8221; adding that its antivirus software failed to detect the token-stealing malware on the employee&#8217;s laptop.</p>
<p>Session tokens allow a user to stay logged in without having to keep re-entering their password or re-authorizing using two-factor authentication each time. But a stolen session token allows an intruder to gain the same access as the account holder without needing their password or two-factor code. As such, it can be difficult to differentiate between a session token of the account owner, or a hacker who stole the token.</p>
<p>CircleCi said the theft of the session token allowed the cybercriminals to impersonate the employee and gain access to some of the company&#8217;s production systems, which store customer data.</p>
<p>&#8220;Because the targeted employee had privileges to generate production access tokens as part of the employee’s regular duties, the unauthorized third party was able to access and exfiltrate data from a subset of databases and stores, including customer environment variables, tokens, and keys,&#8221; said Rob Zuber, the company&#8217;s chief technology officer. Zuber said the intruders had access from December 16 through January 4.</p>
<p>Zuber said that while customer data was encrypted, the cybercriminals also obtained the encryption keys able to decrypt customer data. &#8220;We encourage customers who have yet to take action to do so in order to prevent unauthorized access to third-party systems and stores,&#8221; Zuber added.</p>
<p>Several customers have already informed CircleCi of unauthorized access to their systems, Zuber said.</p>
<p>The post-mortem comes days after the company <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/05/circleci-breach/">warned customers to rotate &#8220;any and all secrets&#8221;</a> stored in its platform, fearing that hackers had stolen its customers&#8217; code and other sensitive secrets used for access to other applications and services.</p>
<p>Zuber said that CircleCi employees who retain access to production systems &#8220;have added additional step-up authentication steps and controls,&#8221; which should prevent a repeat-incident, likely by way of <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/12/25/cybersecurity-101-guide-two-factor/">using hardware security keys</a>.</p>
<p>The initial point of access — the token-stealing on an employee&#8217;s laptop — bears some resemblance to how the password manager giant LastPass was hacked, which also involved an intruder targeting an employee&#8217;s device, though it&#8217;s not known if the two incidents are linked. LastPass confirmed in December that its <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/22/lastpass-customer-password-vaults-stolen/">customers&#8217; encrypted password vaults</a> were stolen in an earlier breach. LastPass said the intruders had initially compromised <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/14/parsing-lastpass-august-data-breach-notice/">an employee&#8217;s device and account access</a>, allowing them to break into LastPass&#8217; internal developer environment.</p>
<p><em>Updated headline to better reflect the customer data that was taken.</em></p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/circleci-hackers-stole-customer-source-code/">CircleCI says hackers stole encryption keys and customers&#8217; secrets</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/zack-whittaker/">Zack Whittaker</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/circleci-hackers-stole-customer-source-code/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ChatGPT goes pro, layoffs at Alphabet, and Dungeons &#038; Dragons flirts with restrictive new licensing</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/chatgpt-goes-pro-layoffs-at-alphabet-and-dungeons-dragons-flirts-with-restrictive-new-licensing/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/chatgpt-goes-pro-layoffs-at-alphabet-and-dungeons-dragons-flirts-with-restrictive-new-licensing/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kyle Wiggers]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 21:15:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Social]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ChatGPT]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[dungeons & dragons]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Microsoft 365]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[OpenAI]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vall-e]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Week in Review]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469932</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome, welcome, folks, to Week in Review, TechCrunch&#8217;s regular column that recaps the last week in news. If you&#8217;d like it in your inbox every Saturday, sign up here. Hope you&#8217;re sitting comfortably with a warm beverage on this wintery Saturday afternoon. Expecting Greg&#8217;s byline? Not to worry &#8212; he&#8217;s still enjoying parental leave, as [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/chatgpt-goes-pro-layoffs-at-alphabet-and-dungeons-dragons-flirts-with-restrictive-new-licensing/">ChatGPT goes pro, layoffs at Alphabet, and Dungeons &#038; Dragons flirts with restrictive new licensing</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/">Kyle Wiggers</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Welcome, welcome, folks, to Week in Review, TechCrunch&#8217;s regular column that recaps the last week in news. If you&#8217;d like it in your inbox every Saturday, sign up <a href="https://techcrunch.com/newsletters">here</a>. Hope you&#8217;re sitting comfortably with a warm beverage on this wintery Saturday afternoon. Expecting Greg&#8217;s byline? Not to worry &#8212; he&#8217;s still enjoying parental leave, as I mentioned in the January 7 edition. All&#8217;s well.</p>
<p>Before we get into it, I&#8217;d be remiss if I didn&#8217;t note, once again, that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/events/tc-early-stage-2023/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TC Early Stage</a> in Boston is on the horizon. With tickets starting at $99, it&#8217;ll be a worthwhile stop along the Eastern conference circuit, packed with expert-led workshops, case studies and deep dives with technical founders. Some members of the TechCrunch editorial staff will be in attendance &#8212; don&#8217;t be a stranger if you spot us on the show floor.</p>
<h2>most read</h2>
<p><strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/openai-begins-piloting-chatgpt-professional-a-premium-version-of-its-viral-chatbot/">ChatGPT goes pro:</a> </strong>OpenAI this week signaled it’ll soon begin charging for <a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/chatgpt/">ChatGPT</a>, its viral AI-powered chatbot that can write essays, emails, poems and even computer code. A &#8220;pro&#8221; version of the tool called ChatGPT Professional will throw in no unavailability windows, no throttling and an unlimited number of messages with ChatGPT &#8212; &#8220;at least 2x the regular daily limit.&#8221; Pricing remains up in the air.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/microsoft-365-basic-launches-with-100-gb-of-storage-outlook-and-more-for-1-99-per-month/"><strong>Microsoft 365 goes Basic:</strong></a> Microsoft will introduce a lower-cost tier of Microsoft 365, its family of productivity software and cloud-based document editing services, starting on January 30, the company announced Wednesday. Called Microsoft 365 Basic and priced at $1.99 per month or $19.99 per year, the plan will initially include 100 GB of storage, Outlook email and access to support experts for help with Microsoft 365 and Windows 11.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/news-aggregator-smartnews-lays-off-40-of-non-japan-staff-with-further-reductions-planned-in-japan/"><strong>Layoffs hit a news aggregator:</strong></a> SmartNews, the Tokyo-based news aggregation website and app, let go of 40% of its U.S. and China workforce, or around 120 people, my colleagues <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahintampa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/kirstenkorosec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kirsten</a> report. The company was impacted by the same macroeconomic factors that have led to a number of tech industry layoffs in recent months, in addition to complications that arose from Apple’s implementation of <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/04/26/apples-app-tracking-transparency-feature-has-arrived-heres-what-you-need-to-know/">App Tracking Transparency</a>, or ATT.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/alphabet-robotics-division-intrinsic-hit-with-layoffs/"><strong>Robotics, too: </strong></a><a href="https://twitter.com/bheater" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brian</a> reports that this week, Alphabet joined the growing list of tech giants making staff cuts amid ongoing economic struggles. The company&#8217;s robot software firm, Intrinsic, laid off 40 employees, a move that comes less than a year after Intrinsic acquired both Vicarious and Open Robotics &#8212; the latter having been announced less than a month ago.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/dungeons-and-dragons-ogl-wizards-of-the-coast/"><strong>Licensed fun:</strong></a> Dungeons &amp; Dragons content creators are fighting to protect their livelihoods, <a href="https://twitter.com/asilbwrites" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amanda</a> writes in a sobering deep dive. Wizards of the Coast (WotC), the Hasbro-owned publisher of the game, plans to update the game&#8217;s license for the first time in over 22 years, releasing a new licensing system that would require any D&amp;D content creator who makes over $750,000 in revenue to pay a 25% royalty to the company on every dollar above that threshold. In <a href="https://gizmodo.com/dungeons-dragons-ogl-announcement-wizards-of-the-coast-1849981365">a sliver of good news</a>, WotC has delayed the rollout of the licensing scheme, following a widespread backlash.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/e-ink-color-tech-epaper-magazines/">Colors, but E Ink:</a> </strong>One of the cooler gizmos to emerge from the 2023 Consumer Electronics Show is E Ink&#8217;s color displays, <a href="https://twitter.com/harrisonweber" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Harri</a> writes. They can spit out 50,000 colors at 300 DPI &#8212; way, way up from the last-gen model&#8217;s max of 4,000 colors. E Ink says it aims to use them to build a magazine reading experience that’s good enough to win over even the most demanding publishers.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/keychron-gets-it-right-with-its-q10-alice-style-keyboard/">Keys for days:</a> </strong>My colleague (and boss!) <a href="https://twitter.com/fredericl" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Frederic</a> reviewed the Keychron Q10 this week, a keyboard akin to <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/07/27/keychrons-new-q8-ergonomic-alice-style-mechanical-keyboard/">Keychron’s other &#8212; but smaller &#8212; Alice-style board</a>. He approved of the gasket mount and silicon gaskets, which provide a bit of flex while reducing ping and other noise. As for the Alice layout (the keys aren&#8217;t in a straight line, but the left and right half are slightly angled), it was easy to get used to, he said &#8212; and he appreciated that the five macro buttons under the knob could be mapped to anything you’d like. Read the <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/keychron-gets-it-right-with-its-q10-alice-style-keyboard/">full review</a> for more.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/from-cloud-computing-to-proptech-digital-ocean-co-founders-raise-29m-for-welcome-homes/"><strong>Welcome home, Welcome Homes:</strong></a> In a profile, <a href="https://twitter.com/bayareawriter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mary Ann</a> peels back the curtains on Welcome Homes, a proptech startup launched by the co-founders of cloud service provider DigitalOcean. The New York City–based firm &#8212; which recently raised $29 million &#8212; offers people a way to design and build new homes online, similar to other venture-backed companies (e.g., Atmos, Homebound) attempting to address the housing shortage.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/vall-es-quickie-voice-deepfakes-should-worry-you-if-you-werent-worried-already/"><strong>I hear deepfaked voices: </strong></a>Microsoft&#8217;s new VALL-E AI model can replicate a voice using just three seconds of audio from the target speaker. But as my colleague Devin writes, it&#8217;s not necessarily cause for alarm &#8212; or rather, cause for more alarm than was already warranted by voice-duplicating tech. Voice replication has been a subject of intense research for years, and the results have been good enough to power plenty of startups, like WellSaid, Papercup and Respeecher. VALL-E is simply the latest illustration of its potential &#8212; and dangers.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/medium-embraces-twitter-alternative-mastodon-with-launch-of-its-own-community/"><strong>Medium joins Mastodon: </strong></a>Online publishing startup Medium, originally created by Twitter co-founder Evan Williams, is embracing the open source social platform Mastodon. <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahintampa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah</a> reports that Medium has created its own instance &#8212; <a href="http://me.dm/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">me.dm</a> &#8212; to support authors and their publications with reliable infrastructure, moderation and a short domain name to make it easier for authors to share their usernames, among other things.</p>
<h2>audio roundup</h2>
<p>As always, TechCrunch had a winning lineup of audio content this week for your listening pleasure &#8212; although I <em>might</em> be a little biased. On startup-focused <a href="https://pod.link/found/episode/441fa82456cae0d3c97e743179d64b9d" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Found</a>, TechCrunch startup battlefield editor Neesha Tambe spoke with Sheeba Dawood, the co-founder of clean energy tech provider Minerva Lithium, about the struggles she’s faced as a woman of color trying to innovate in the mineral manufacturing industry and what’s next for the company. TC&#8217;s dedicated crypto show, <a href="https://pod.link/1616008890" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Chain Reaction</a>, featured an interview with Polygon Labs, one of the biggest market shakers and layer-2 blockchains in the crypto space that’s building on top of the Ethereum ecosystem. Meanwhile, over at <a href="https://pod.link/1215439780">Equity</a>, Natasha, Mary Ann, and Becca chatted about incoming deals from Inflow, Deel and Fidelity; layoffs and lawsuits at Carta; Microsoft&#8217;s much-rumored investment in ChatGPT and OpenAI; and SBF&#8217;s Substack debut.</p>
<h2>TechCrunch+</h2>
<p>Here&#8217;s your regular reminder to subscribe to TC+ if you haven&#8217;t yet. It&#8217;s where TC takes exhaustive, exclusive looks at trends, industries and emerging technologies. Here&#8217;s some of the most popular content on TC+ this week:</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/crypto-in-for-a-choppy-year-of-slow-capital-deployment-investors-say/"><strong>Crypto rollercoaster:</strong></a> While some crypto-focused venture capitalists are bullish for 2023, others see it as a hazardous time, <a href="https://twitter.com/jacqmelinek" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jacquelyn</a> reports. Internal sentiment among VCs is a &#8220;wait and see&#8221; game, according to one source quoted in the piece; competition in the market is likely to heat up as investors write fewer checks and become more selective.</p>
<p><strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/some-investors-are-cautiously-implementing-chatgpt-in-their-workflows/">ChatGPT, meet VC:</a> </strong>Some investors are (cautiously) incorporating ChatGPT into their workflows, as it turns out. ChatGPT being a specifically text-based support tool, automation could be making its way to rejection letters, market maps or even bits of due diligence, TC found &#8212; all in order to stay afloat in a changing venture landscape. <a href="https://twitter.com/nmasc_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Natasha M</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/christinemhall" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christine</a>, and<a href="https://twitter.com/kyle_l_wiggers" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> I</a> have more.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/how-we-pivoted-our-deep-tech-startup-to-become-a-saas-company/"><b>Pivot when ready:</b></a> Pivots aren&#8217;t necessarily bad news. Brian Casey writes about how he pivoted his deep tech startup to become a software-as-a-service company &#8212; albeit not without major challenges. In his words: &#8220;Pivoting from hardware to SaaS was the right move for our electric motor design startup, but the process wasn’t precisely linear.&#8221;</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/chatgpt-goes-pro-layoffs-at-alphabet-and-dungeons-dragons-flirts-with-restrictive-new-licensing/">ChatGPT goes pro, layoffs at Alphabet, and Dungeons &#038; Dragons flirts with restrictive new licensing</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/">Kyle Wiggers</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/chatgpt-goes-pro-layoffs-at-alphabet-and-dungeons-dragons-flirts-with-restrictive-new-licensing/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>YouTube plans to modify profanity rules that prompted creator backlash</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/youtube-plans-to-modify-profanity-rules-that-prompted-creator-backlash/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/youtube-plans-to-modify-profanity-rules-that-prompted-creator-backlash/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Taylor Hatmaker]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 20:02:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Social]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Creators]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[YouTube]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470345</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>YouTube&#8217;s gaming community pushed back against the company this week after some creators saw their old videos demonetized out of the blue. The culprit is a new policy that the company introduced back in November in order to make certain kinds of content more advertiser friendly. That change, made to YouTubes&#8217;s advertiser-friendly content guidelines, overhauled [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/youtube-plans-to-modify-profanity-rules-that-prompted-creator-backlash/">YouTube plans to modify profanity rules that prompted creator backlash</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/taylor-hatmaker/">Taylor Hatmaker</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">YouTube&#8217;s gaming community <a href="https://kotaku.com/youtube-violence-profanity-policy-rtgame-moist-critical-1849971177">pushed back</a> against the company this week after some creators saw their old videos demonetized out of the blue.</p>
<p>The culprit is a new policy that the company <a href="https://support.google.com/youtube/answer/9725604?hl=en&amp;ref_topic=9153642">introduced back in November</a> in order to make certain kinds of content more advertiser friendly. That change, made to YouTubes&#8217;s advertiser-friendly content guidelines, overhauled the platform&#8217;s approach to profanity and violence.</p>
<p>The good news is that while we don&#8217;t quite know what the company will do yet, YouTube is apparently listening to creators&#8217; concerns.</p>
<p>&#8220;In recent weeks we’ve heard from many creators regarding this update,&#8221; YouTube spokesperson Michael Aciman told TechCrunch. &#8220;That feedback is important to us and we are in the process of making some adjustments to this policy to address their concerns. We will follow up shortly with our creator community as soon as we have more to share.&#8221;</p>
<p>In November, YouTube expanded its definition of violence beyond real-world depictions, including in-game violent content &#8220;directed at a real named person or acts that are manufactured to create shocking experiences (such as brutal mass killing).&#8221; The company said that gore in &#8220;standard game play&#8221; was fine, but only after the first 8 seconds of a video. The whole section left plenty of room for interpretation, for better or worse.</p>
<p>The changes to its profanity policy were more drastic. YouTube announced that it would no longer count &#8220;hell&#8221; and &#8220;damn&#8221; as profane words, but all other profanity would be lumped together instead of differentiated based on severity (e.g. words like &#8220;shit&#8221; and &#8220;fuck&#8221; would now be treated the same way). Further, &#8220;profanity used in the title, thumbnails, or in the video&#8217;s first 7 seconds or used consistently throughout the video may not receive ad revenue,&#8221; according to the new policy.</p>
<p>If the swearing kicks in after the first 8 seconds of a video, it&#8217;s still eligible, but some of the changes stood to affect a massive swath of videos —many of which were made well before the changes were announced. Creators started noticing the new policies in effect around the end of December, watching some videos be slapped with new restrictions that limit their reach and ad eligibility.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>YouTube creator Daniel Condren, who runs RTGame, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DRsVDZvmaAE">explored the impact of the policy change</a> on his own channel in a video that racked up more than a million views this week. Condren has been grappling with the enforcement changes in recent weeks after seeing roughly a dozen videos demonetized and his request for appeals rejected.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="550" data-dnt="true">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">I am so sorry to have to keep tweeting this &#8211; but overnight, 6 more of my videos have now become limited suddenly, including my Best of 2020. No notification from YouTube at all on any of these. This is genuinely awful <a href="https://twitter.com/TeamYouTube?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@TeamYouTube</a> <a href="https://t.co/UHfSJA1FCt">pic.twitter.com/UHfSJA1FCt</a></p>
<p>&mdash; RTGame Daniel (@RTGameCrowd) <a href="https://twitter.com/RTGameCrowd/status/1608385443245989889?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">December 29, 2022</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>
<p>&#8220;I genuinely feel like my entire livelihood is at risk if this continues,&#8221; Condren wrote on Twitter. &#8220;I&#8217;m so upset this is even happening and that there seems to be nothing I can do to resolve it.&#8221;</p>
<p>YouTube didn&#8217;t respond to our follow-up questions about how it plans to tweak the policy, but we&#8217;re certainly curious if the platform will roll back enforcement for old, previously published videos that creators might rely on for income.</p>
<p>In the face of emerging regulation targeting social media&#8217;s relationship with underage users, the company is clearly trying to make its massive trove of videos more age-appropriate (and advertiser friendly). But retrofitting age restrictions and new monetization rules onto a platform like YouTube is a delicate balance — and in this case the changes had a swift, sweeping impact that gave creators little time to adapt.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/youtube-plans-to-modify-profanity-rules-that-prompted-creator-backlash/">YouTube plans to modify profanity rules that prompted creator backlash</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/taylor-hatmaker/">Taylor Hatmaker</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/youtube-plans-to-modify-profanity-rules-that-prompted-creator-backlash/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>This Week in Apps: ChatGPT app scammers, Instagram revamp and a consumer spending slowdown</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/this-week-in-apps-chatgpt-app-scammers-instagram-revamp-and-a-consumer-spending-slowdown/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/this-week-in-apps-chatgpt-app-scammers-instagram-revamp-and-a-consumer-spending-slowdown/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sarah Perez]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 19:15:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[app developers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[app stores]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[app-store]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Apple]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Google]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Google Play]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mobile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[This Week In Apps]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469889</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to This Week in Apps, the weekly TechCrunch series that recaps the latest in mobile OS news, mobile applications and the overall app economy. The app economy in 2023 hit a few snags, as consumer spending last year dropped for the first time by 2% to $167 billion, according to the latest &#8220;State [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/this-week-in-apps-chatgpt-app-scammers-instagram-revamp-and-a-consumer-spending-slowdown/">This Week in Apps: ChatGPT app scammers, Instagram revamp and a consumer spending slowdown</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/sarah-perez/">Sarah Perez</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Welcome back to This Week in Apps, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/this-week-in-apps/">the weekly TechCrunch series</a> that recaps the latest in mobile OS news, mobile applications and the overall app economy.</p>
<p>The app economy in 2023 hit a few snags, as consumer spending last year <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/the-app-economy-slowed-for-the-first-time-in-2022-with-consumer-spend-down-2-to-167-billion/">dropped for the first time</a> by 2% to $167 billion, according to the latest &#8220;State of Mobile&#8221; report by data.ai (previously App Annie). However, downloads are continuing to grow, up 11% year-over-year in 2022 to reach 255 billion. Consumers are also spending more time using mobile apps than ever before. On Android devices alone, hours spent in 2022 grew 9%, reaching 4.1 trillion.</p>
<p>This Week in Apps offers a way to keep up with this fast-moving industry in one place with the latest from the world of apps, including news, updates, startup fundings, mergers and acquisitions, and much more.</p>
<p><em><strong>Do you want This Week in Apps in your inbox every Saturday? Sign up here: <a href="http://techcrunch.com/newsletters">techcrunch.com/newsletters</a></strong></em></p>
<h1>Top Stories</h1>
<h3>State of Mobile 2023 arrives, consumer spending slows</h3>
<p>Data.ai&#8217;s anticipated review of the app ecosystem, &#8220;<a href="http://stateofmobile2023.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">State of Mobile 2023</a>,&#8221; <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/the-app-economy-slowed-for-the-first-time-in-2022-with-consumer-spend-down-2-to-167-billion/">arrived this week</a>, finding that consumer spending on apps has been hit by the same macroeconomic forces impacting the broader economy. That led to a first-time drop in consumer spending after years of record growth. However, there are some bright spots in the report&#8217;s findings. For starters, it seems that non-game apps are more resilient than games in a down economy. Though consumer spend on mobile games dropped 5% to $110 billion, spending on non-game apps increased 6% to $58 billion &#8212; driven by streaming subscriptions, dating apps and short-form video apps.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2467734" style="width: 2032px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467734" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2467734 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png" alt="" width="2022" height="1698" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png 2022w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=150,126 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=300,252 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=768,645 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=680,571 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=1536,1290 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=1200,1008 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Consumer-Spend-SOM-2023.png?resize=50,42 50w" sizes="(max-width: 2022px) 100vw, 2022px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467734" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p>The data also indicated that despite the tightening of wallets, consumer engagement on mobile continues to grow. Across top mobile markets, consumers were spending 5 hours, 2 minutes per day in 2022 using their apps, up 9% from 2020. That&#8217;s remarkable, given that 2020 was the onset of the COVID pandemic, which tied everyone to their phone and rapidly changed consumer behavior. However, there is a caveat to this news: Much of mobile users&#8217; time is monopolized by three app categories, which accounted for half the time spent on mobile: Social Media/Communication (19.5% of total time); Entertainment/Short Video (17% of total time); and Entertainment/Video Sharing (12.7% of total time).</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><div id="attachment_2467737" style="width: 2032px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467737" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2467737 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png" alt="" width="2022" height="1698" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png 2022w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=150,126 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=300,252 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=768,645 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=680,571 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=1536,1290 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=1200,1008 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-13-Macro-Top-20-Global-App-Subgenres-in-2022-by-Time-Spent-SOM-2023.png?resize=50,42 50w" sizes="(max-width: 2022px) 100vw, 2022px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467737" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p>In addition, while mobile ad spend growth will also slow alongside the economy, it will not decline. Data.ai is forecasting that mobile ad spend in 2023 will hit $262 billion, up from $336 billion this year as short video apps drive growth. TikTok, for example, became the second-ever non-game app to top $6 billion in all-time consumer spending, the report noted.</p>
<p>The first category — Social Media/Communication — includes WeChat, WhatsApp, Facebook, Messenger, Telegram, LINE and Discord, while the Entertainment and Short Video category is where you’ll find TikTok as well as Kwai, Vido Video, Baidu Haokan and Snack Video. The last category of Entertainment and Video Sharing includes long-form video like YouTube, YouTube Kids and bilibili.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2469893" style="width: 1004px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2469893" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2469893 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg" alt="" width="994" height="990" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg 994w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=150,150 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=300,300 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=768,765 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=680,677 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=32,32 32w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=50,50 50w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=64,64 64w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=96,96 96w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.24.47-AM.jpg?resize=128,128 128w" sizes="(max-width: 994px) 100vw, 994px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2469893" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p>One finding that jumped out at me is that TikTok this year lost its No. 1 position on the Top Charts by Downloads to Instagram, the Meta-owned social app that has been desperately trying to clone TikTok&#8217;s feature set with Reels. Data.ai&#8217;s report indicated that Meta had a bit of a comeback this year, with Instagram bumping TikTok on downloads, though TikTok remained No. 1 by consumer spending. However, in terms of real-world use, TikTok is much further down the charts.</p>
<p>In 2022, the top four non-game apps by monthly active users were all owned by Facebook. In order, they were Facebook, WhatsApp Messenger, Instagram, then Facebook Messenger. TikTok was No. 5. Amazon, which was No. 5 last year, slipped to No. 7 while Telegram moved up to No. 6 from No. 7 in 2021. Twitter, Spotify and Netflix rounded out the charts.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2467738" style="width: 2936px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467738" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2467738 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png" alt="" width="2926" height="1512" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png 2926w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=150,78 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=300,155 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=768,397 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=680,351 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=1536,794 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=2048,1058 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=1200,620 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Slide-83-Macro-Top-Apps-by-Market-SOM-2023.png?resize=50,26 50w" sizes="(max-width: 2926px) 100vw, 2926px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467738" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p>The report delves into other interesting trends related to specific categories of apps (some of which we may get into later), but one particular area of interest to us involved the detailed habits of Gen Z consumers. Unlike the top apps used by older generations, which tend to be more utilitarian and practical (think Amazon, eBay, Walmart, The Weather Channel, Waze, Ring, PayPal and others), Gen Z is still devoted to video apps, user-generated content and mindfulness apps, data.ai said. (<em>Ah, youth!)</em> They also have a preference for Meta&#8217;s Instagram over Facebook, TikTok, Snapchat, Netflix and Spotify.</p>
<p>Another trend driven by younger users was the rise of BeReal, a more authentic photo-sharing app that prompts users once a day to take candid photos of themselves and what they&#8217;re doing. Data.ai found that <strong>no other social app</strong> added more new users in the U.S. over the past five years than the 5.3 million users BeReal gained in August 2022. But the firm suggested BeReal may struggle to grow engagement since the app only asks people to use it for brief periods. However, in speaking with those close to the company, we understand BeReal is purposefully trying to build a non-addictive social app &#8212; it just doesn&#8217;t know how to monetize that sort of creation.</p>
<p>Another app category driven by Gen Z trends is friend-finding, which includes apps like Yubo, Hoop, Bumble (for its BFF feature), Live Talk and others.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2469928" style="width: 1860px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2469928" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2469928 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg" alt="" width="1850" height="1058" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg 1850w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=150,86 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=300,172 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=768,439 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=680,389 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=1536,878 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=1200,686 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.11.05-AM.jpg?resize=50,29 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1850px) 100vw, 1850px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2469928" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p>Meanwhile, in terms of gaming, the Gen Z demographic showed a preference for party, simulation and shooters, and counted Roblox as their No. 1 app. If there&#8217;s any wonder why Meta is spending billions trying to develop a virtual gaming landscape with Horizon Worlds, just look at Roblox&#8217;s growth and traction among the younger demographic. &#8220;Creative Sandbox&#8221; games like Roblox as well as Minecraft saw a global increase in time spent last year, up 25% from 2021 to 2022.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2469898" style="width: 872px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2469898" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2469898 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg" alt="" width="862" height="644" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg 862w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg?resize=150,112 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg?resize=300,224 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg?resize=768,574 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg?resize=680,508 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.33.24-AM.jpg?resize=50,37 50w" sizes="(max-width: 862px) 100vw, 862px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2469898" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits, above and below:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-2469899 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg" alt="" width="886" height="612" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg 886w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg?resize=150,104 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg?resize=300,207 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg?resize=768,530 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg?resize=680,470 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-9.34.48-AM.jpg?resize=50,35 50w" sizes="(max-width: 886px) 100vw, 886px" /></p>
<p><strong>A few other interesting highlights:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>The most-searched iOS App Store keywords in the U.S. for entertainment apps were, in order: netflix, disney+, hulu, HBO max, paramount, paramount+, amazon prime, peacock tv, prime video and tubi. Maybe Netflix will be okay after all.</li>
<li>Genshin Impact reached $3 billion in in-app purchases in Q2 2022.</li>
<li>Game publishers in China drove a third of consumer game spending.</li>
<li>Crypto apps&#8217; downloads fell in 2022, even as other fintechs grew.</li>
<li>Average MAUs among the top five neobanks in the U.S. climbed from 1.4 million in 2020 to 2.2 million in 2022. Chime is the market leader in both active users and user engagement.</li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_2469935" style="width: 1134px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2469935" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2469935 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg" alt="" width="1124" height="1028" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg 1124w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg?resize=150,137 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg?resize=300,274 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg?resize=768,702 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg?resize=680,622 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-13-at-10.26.21-AM.jpg?resize=50,46 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1124px) 100vw, 1124px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2469935" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> data.ai</p></div></p>
<ul>
<li>Consumers spent nearly 110 billion hours in shopping apps in 2022, up 9% globally. Cost-conscious shoppers drove growth.</li>
<li>Total time spent in social apps climbed 17% year-over-year to over 2 trillion hours on Android phones in 2022. The U.S. accounted for more than one-fourth of social app consumer spending.</li>
<li>Sports betting app downloads hit 4.3 million at the start of the 2022-2023 NFL season, up 8% year-over-year from 2021.</li>
<li>Language learning apps saw 31% year-over-year growth as travel returned post-pandemic.</li>
<li>Consumer spend in dating apps grew 12% year-over-year in 2022, and 91% year-over-year compared to pre-pandemic spend.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Apple let scammy &#8220;ChatGPT&#8221; apps flood the App Store</h3>
<p>What, no I mean, <em>what</em> is going on with App Review? For years, Apple has been caught off guard at times, allowing violative apps to slip through its review process to be published on the App Store until users or the media called out the mistake.</p>
<p>But in the case of the <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/app-store-and-play-store-are-flooded-with-dubious-chatgpt-apps/">scam &#8220;ChatGPT&#8221; apps that flooded the App Store</a> over the past couple of weeks, one has to wonder if Apple is even paying attention at all. ChatGPT&#8217;s maker OpenAI doesn&#8217;t offer a public API, so that should have been a red flag to reviewers about any app claiming a ChatGPT or OpenAI connection in its name or description, then charging money for access. One app, called “ChatGPT Chat GPT AI With GPT-3,” even managed to reach the Top Charts in the productivity category in multiple countries as a result of consumer demand for ChatGPT and Apple&#8217;s inattention. (The app was removed shortly after reporters, including ourselves, reached out to Apple for comment. Apple never answered our emails.)</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="550" data-dnt="true">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">The iOS App Store is full of folks putting ChatGPT into a paid wrapper with ambiguous language that would let you believe you’re paying for ChatGPT <a href="https://t.co/3w0rK14E5I">pic.twitter.com/3w0rK14E5I</a></p>
<p>&mdash; Austen Allred (@Austen) <a href="https://twitter.com/Austen/status/1611864110244990976?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 7, 2023</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>
<p>Google Play had the same problem, but frankly, consumers expect more from Apple&#8217;s App Store. In fact, Apple&#8217;s argument against antitrust concerns, like its ban on sideloading and third-party app stores, has to do with the safety and security of its users. Apple says only it should be trusted to keep consumers safe. But surely that means Apple should also be protecting consumers from scam apps and subscription scams. But it is not.</p>
<p>And while no system is perfect, it seems like the apps that are at the top of the App Store&#8217;s charts &#8212; or those that quickly moved up the charts for unknown reasons &#8212; should go under an additional review by Apple, just to make sure they&#8217;re playing by the rules. Developers have long argued that Apple should be cracking down on apps with high-priced subscriptions or those that are charging users for basic utilities or otherwise free features &#8212; in other words, the apps that are profiting from scamming users. If it did so, a subscription-based app that appeared to be charging for access to a free service with a non-public API wouldn&#8217;t have made the cut.</p>
<p>These things aren&#8217;t hard to spot either &#8212; third-party app intelligence services can parse customer reviews for negative sentiments and keywords, so surely Apple could implement a system of its own, if it wanted to. In the case of the scammy ChatGPT apps, customer reviews called the apps fake and non-functional, warning others not to get scammed. Where was Apple on this issue? Until the media coverage, it was quietly collecting its cut of the scammers&#8217; subscription revenues.</p>
<p>In other App Store news, activist investors have pressured Apple for more insight into app removals, the FT reported, but their interest lies in wanting a better understanding of when Apple acquiesces to foreign governments’ requests. The company will begin including additional information in its Transparency Report about whether removals are related to local laws and how many apps were pulled in each country.</p>
<h3><strong>Goodbye, Instagram Shop. Move over, Reels. </strong></h3>
<p><div id="attachment_2466980" style="width: 1930px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2466980" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2466980 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png" alt="" width="1920" height="1280" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png 1920w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/IG-Nav-2023-.png?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2466980" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Instagram</p></div></p>
<p>Instagram <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/instagram-is-removing-the-shop-tab-moving-reels-from-the-center-spot-in-design-overhaul-next-month/">announced</a> this week it will simplify its in-app navigation after years of confusing changes designed to push various products like Instagram Shop and Reels. The company said, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/instagram/541982071188223" target="_blank" rel="noopener">starting in February</a>, it will return the Compose button (the plus sign “+”) to the front and center of the navigation bar at the bottom of the app and it will remove the Shop tab entirely.</p>
<p>As a result, the Reels button will now move over to the right of Compose, losing its prime spot.</p>
<p>The<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/11/12/instagram-redesign-puts-reels-and-shop-tabs-on-the-home-screen/"> earlier changes</a> that had pushed Reels over Compose had been fairly controversial as Instagram users felt as if the company was forcing them to use the app’s new products at the expense of the overall user experience. Instagram defended the changes in prior years as a way to introduce users to its new products. But in more recent months, there’s been increased backlash over how far Instagram has deviated from its original mission. Even the Kardashians criticized the app for &#8220;trying to be TikTok.&#8221;</p>
<p>Instagram said shopping on Instagram will continue to be supported despite the removal of the tab. <em>We&#8217;ll see.</em></p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="S67a1oUoHz"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/instagram-is-removing-the-shop-tab-moving-reels-from-the-center-spot-in-design-overhaul-next-month/">Instagram is removing the Shop tab, moving Reels from the center spot in design overhaul next month</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Instagram is removing the Shop tab, moving Reels from the center spot in design overhaul next month&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/instagram-is-removing-the-shop-tab-moving-reels-from-the-center-spot-in-design-overhaul-next-month/embed/#?secret=XzuuzIPi8j#?secret=S67a1oUoHz" data-secret="S67a1oUoHz" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<h1>Weekly News</h1>
<h3>Android Updates</h3>
<ul>
<li>Google is working to fix a <strong>Google Play issue</strong> impacting <strong>missing app changelogs</strong>, according to an <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/google-play-store-app-changelogs-coming-back/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android Police</a> report.</li>
<li>The latest stable release of the official IDE for building Android applications,<strong> Android Studio Electric Eel</strong> (2022.1.1), <a href="https://youtu.be/bVt14IBv4NA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">arrived</a>. The release includes updates and new features that cover design, build &amp; dependencies, emulators &amp; devices, and IntelliJ, Google <a href="http://android-developers.googleblog.com/2023/01/android-studio-electric-eel.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said</a>.</li>
<li>Google <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/googles-extension-sdk-aims-to-bring-latest-features-to-older-android-versions/">released the <strong>Extension SDK to developers</strong></a>, bringing features like the Android 13 Photo Picker API and AdServices APIs to Android 11 and up.</li>
</ul>
<div class="embed breakout embed--video embed--youtube"><iframe title="What&#039;s new in Android Studio - Electric Eel" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bVt14IBv4NA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<h3>Apple News</h3>
<ul>
<li>Second <strong>developer betas</strong> for iOS 16.3, iPadOS 16.3, watchOS 9.3, macOS Ventura 13.2 and tvOS 16.3 have arrived. One notable change impacts the <strong>new Emergency SOS feature</strong>. The &#8220;Call with Hold&#8221; option is renamed to &#8220;Call with Hold and Release,&#8221; as now the call to emergency services won&#8217;t go through until users let go of the buttons they press down to start the SOS call. <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/01/10/ios-16-3-call-with-hold-emergency-sos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">More here</a>. The change may be an attempt to address issues over mistakenly triggered calls.</li>
<li>Seems like Apple pushed Flickr to update its <strong>SafeSearch filtering.</strong> The company <a href="https://blog.flickr.net/en/2023/01/12/flickr-release-notes-december-2022/">said</a> it updated the feature so it <strong>won&#8217;t return results for &#8220;bad words&#8221;</strong> when it&#8217;s enabled in order &#8220;to act in compliance with Apple’s policies.&#8221;</li>
<li>Bloomberg&#8217;s Mark Gurman <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2023-01-08/when-will-apple-launch-the-reality-pro-mixed-reality-headset-apple-2023-devices-lcnfzkc7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported</a> that <strong>iOS 17 is <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/apples-ios-17-may-have-fewer-major-changes-than-initially-planned/">going to be a smaller release</a></strong> with fewer changes as Apple focuses on its mixed-reality headset.</li>
<li><strong>Apple Maps</strong> now lets <strong>businesses update their listings</strong> and tout promotions<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/apple-maps-business-listings-are-about-to-get-more-detailed-with-launch-of-apple-business-connect/"> via a new <strong>Apple Business Connect</strong> portal</a>. No plans yet for any sort of Maps ads offering, however.</li>
<li>In a year-end review, Apple <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/app-store-developers-have-earned-320-billion-to-date-says-apple/">announced</a> it has now paid out a record<strong> $320 billion to app developers since 2008</strong> — a number that reflects the revenue apps have generated, minus Apple’s commission. The company now has <strong>more than 900 million paid subscriptions across Apple services,</strong> with subscriptions on the App Store driving a “significant” part of that figure, it said.</li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_2467604" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2467604" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2467604" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?w=680" alt="" width="680" height="469" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg 1306w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=150,103 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=300,207 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=768,529 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=680,469 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=1200,827 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Apple-celebrates-entertainment-infographic-01.jpg?resize=50,34 50w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2467604" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Apple</p></div></p>
<h3>Gaming</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Google and Nvidia <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-01-12/google-nvidia-express-concerns-to-ftc-about-microsoft-s-activision-deal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shared concerns with the FTC</a> </strong>as to how <strong>Microsoft&#8217;s Activision Blizzard deal</strong> would give it an unfair advantage in cloud, subscription and <strong>mobile gaming.</strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://cloud.jiogames.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">JioGames</a></strong>, part of Reliance Industries’ telecom platform Jio, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/india-ambani-jio-partners-with-gamestream-in-cloud-gaming-push/">announced</a> a <strong>10-year strategic partnership with France&#8217;s Gamestream.</strong> The latter will assist JioGames in bringing cloud gaming to &#8220;1.4 billion&#8221; Indians by helping scale the <strong>JioGamesCloud</strong> platform. JioGames&#8217; titles can be played on Android, web (PC, Mac and iPhone), and Jio&#8217;s set-top boxes.</li>
<li><strong>Roblox</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/roblox-may-arrive-on-meta-quest-later-this-year/">could be</a> coming to a new platform: <strong>Meta Quest.</strong> Sources told <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/9/23546945/roblox-is-coming-to-meta-quest" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Verge</a> that Roblox will be expanding its VR footprint &#8212; it already works on Rift and HTC&#8217;s Vive &#8212; by releasing to Meta&#8217;s Quest, which doesn&#8217;t require a PC to play.</li>
<li><strong>Stardew Valley&#8217;s big update,</strong> patch 1.5, finally <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/stardew-valley-apps-ios-android-patch-1-5/">reached iOS and Android users</a>.</strong> The update, which arrived on consoles in 2021, includes a number of new features and changes, including a new beach farm layout, new NPCs and enemies, ostriches (!!) and a new location called Ginger Island.</li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_2466991" style="width: 1930px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2466991" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2466991 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png" alt="Stardew Valley screenshot" width="1920" height="1080" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png 1920w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/stardew.png?resize=50,28 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2466991" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Stardew Valley</p></div></p>
<h3>Twitter Drama</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Twitter&#8217;s API</strong> began experiencing issues that are<strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/third-party-twitter-apps-tweetbot-twitterrific-echofon-down/"> impacting third-party Twitter apps</a> like Tweetbot, Echofon and Twitterrific</strong>. The app makers confirmed the problems have been causing log-in issues for users and their apps no longer work.</li>
<li>Online publishing platform <strong>Medium</strong>, originally created by Twitter co-founder Evan Williams,<strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/medium-embraces-twitter-alternative-mastodon-with-launch-of-its-own-community/">announced</a> that it’s embracing the open source Mastodon</strong> platform by creating its own instance to support its authors and their publications. Access to the instance will be offered through a Medium membership, which means in a way, it&#8217;s the first paid instance to come to Mastodon.</li>
<li><strong>Twitter&#8217;s Blue subscription,</strong> which is the new way to be verified and get your checkmark &#8212; <em>degrading the value of checks in the process!</em> &#8212; <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/twitter-launches-its-blue-subscription-service-in-japan/">rolled out to Japan.</a></strong> Users can subscribe for ¥980 (around $7.40) per month on the web and ¥1,380 ($10.42) per month on iOS, a bit lower than U.S. prices of $8 per month on the web and $11 per month on iOS.</li>
<li><strong>Twitter</strong> made the <strong>algorithmic timeline</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/twitter-makes-algorithmic-timeline-default-on-ios/">the default</a> and <strong>renamed it the &#8220;For You&#8221; feed.</strong><em> (Eye roll)</em>. You can now swipe between the For You feed and a chronological timeline, as well as lists.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Entertainment</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>TikTok</strong> is <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/tiktok-launches-a-talent-manager-portal-so-managers-can-negotiate-brand-deals-for-clients/">alpha testing a <strong>Talent Manager Portal</strong></a> with select talent agencies. The service would allow <strong>creators&#8217; agents and reps</strong> to oversee, execute and analyze <strong>brand deals</strong> their clients are being offered.</li>
<li><strong>Apple Music and the Apple TV apps</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/apple-tv-apple-music-apps-windows-microsoft-store/">quietly launched on the <strong>Microsoft Store</strong></a> &#8212; a few months after Microsoft said the apps would be coming to Windows 11.</li>
<li><strong>YouTube</strong> will <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/youtube-new-partner-program-terms-shorts-revenue-sharing-february-1/">begin sharing ad revenue</a> with Shorts creators</strong> on February 1, and will update its YPP terms to reflect this.<em> (Take that, TikTok!)</em></li>
</ul>
<h3>Etc.</h3>
<ul>
<li>Failed discount movie tickets service <strong>MoviePass</strong> is trying for a comeback with<strong><a href="https://appleinsider.com/articles/23/01/13/moviepass-returns-backed-by-cryptocurrency-firm?utm_medium=rss" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> funding from crypto backers</a></strong>, Animoca Brands. <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f612.png" alt="😒" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></li>
<li><strong>Google</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/google-is-finally-rolling-out-emoji-reactions-for-meet-video-calls/">added</a> <strong>emoji reactions</strong> to <strong>Meet</strong> video calls, starting on iOS and web, with Android to follow. The feature was announced last year.</li>
<li><em>Not so super</em>. Tata Group’s super app <strong>Tata Neu</strong> is <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-01-10/tata-reviews-super-app-strategy-as-sales-may-miss-target-by-50?sref=gni836kR" target="_blank" rel="noopener">expected to meet <strong>only half its sales target</strong></a> in its first year &#8212; $4 billion versus an $8 billion target. The app had been modeled on successful apps like Alipay and WeChat.</li>
<li><strong>Tinder and other Match dating apps</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/tinder-hinge-match-group-online-scam-alerts/">will introduce tips</a> on how to <strong>avoid romance scams</strong>. <em>Someone watched &#8220;The Tinder Swindler,&#8221; apparently!</em></li>
</ul>
<h1>Government &amp; Policy</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>TikTok’s CEO, Shou Zi Chew, met with senior European Union lawmakers</strong> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/tiktok-eu-meeting/">to answer a number of questions</a> including privacy, data protection, DSA compliance, child safety, Russian disinformation and the transparency of paid political content. The inquiry follows what&#8217;s expected to be increased regulatory scrutiny of the app, including possible oversight by the European Commission.</li>
<li><strong>After <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/instagram-fined-e405m-for-violating-kids-privacy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">being fined $400 million</a> by Ireland’s Data Protection Commission</strong> over how Instagram handled minors&#8217; accounts and data, <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/instagram-and-facebook-introduce-more-limits-on-targeting-teens-with-ads/">Meta announced it would remove</a> the ability for advertisers to target teen users by gender.</strong> The company will also <strong>end personalized ad targeting to users under 18 based on in-app activity,</strong> like who they follow on Instagram and what Facebook pages they like.</li>
<li><strong>New Jersey and Ohio have <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/new-jersey-and-ohio-are-the-latest-states-to-ban-tiktok-on-government-devices/">now joined 20 other U.S. states</a> in banning TikTok on government-owned devices</strong> over security concerns.</li>
<li><strong>The U.S. Supreme Court <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/whatsapp-green-light-lawsuit-nso-group-supreme-court/">declined to block a lawsuit</a> filed by WhatsApp that challenged the alleged mass phone hacking by Israeli spyware maker NSO Group.</strong> The spyware maker had argued the suit should be dropped because it was acting on behalf of a foreign government, but the Supreme Court rejected this claim.</li>
</ul>
<h1>Funding</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>A Twitter rival called ‘T2’</strong> <strong>raised its first outside funding,</strong> <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/twitter-rival-t2-raises-its-first-outside-funding-1-1m-from-a-group-of-high-profile-angels/">with $1.1 million</a></strong> from a group of high-profile angels including Bradley Horowitz, Rich Miner and the former CEO of Wikipedia, Katherine Maher. T2 founder Gabor Cselle has sold startups to Twitter and Google previously.</li>
<li><strong>Payments technology platform Butter Payments raised <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kenrickcai/2023/01/11/butter-payments-raises-22-million-accidental-churn/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$21.5 million in Series A funding</a></strong> led by Norwest at a ~$100 million valuation. The company leverages AI to help end accidental churn.</li>
<li><strong>Kakao Entertainment, which publishes apps for popular animated shows and novels, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-01-12/saudi-wealth-fund-joins-930-million-pre-ipo-bet-on-anime-giant?sref=gni836kR" target="_blank" rel="noopener">raised $930 million</a></strong> from Saudi Arabia&#8217;s PIF and Singapore&#8217;s GIC.</li>
<li><strong>A company developing a cognitive behavioral therapy platform for ADHD, Inflow, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/inflow-a-platform-for-managing-adhd-through-cbt-raises-11m/">raised $11 million in Series A funding</a>.</strong> Inflow&#8217;s self-help app offers daily exercises and challenges focused on habit development, mindfulness techniques, community support and more.</li>
<li><strong>Social crypto wallet app The Easy Company <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/the-easy-company-raised-14-2m-to-build-an-easy-to-use-crypto-wallet/">raised $14.2 million in seed funding</a>.</strong> The iOS and Android app offers an Instagram-like experience for showcasing NFTs.</li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_2470093" style="width: 1400px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470093" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2470093 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp" alt="" width="1390" height="946" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp 1390w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=150,102 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=300,204 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=768,523 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=680,463 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=1200,817 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/easy-co.webp?resize=50,34 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1390px) 100vw, 1390px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470093" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> The Easy Company</p></div></p>
<h1>Layoffs</h1>
<ul>
<li><strong>Tokyo-based news aggregator SmartNews <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/news-aggregator-smartnews-lays-off-40-of-non-japan-staff-with-further-reductions-planned-in-japan/">laid off 120 people</a> in the U.S. and China,</strong> with plans to implement a<strong> voluntary workforce reduction in Japan.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Fintech for kids Greenlight,</strong> which lets kids use a debit card and app with parental monitoring, <strong><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/greenlight-fintech-layoff/">laid off 104 employees</a></strong> — or more than 21% of its total headcount of 485 employees.</li>
<li><strong>Crime-reporting app Citizen <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/crime-reporting-app-citizen-lays-off-33-employees/">laid off 33 employees</a>, including at least 10 engineers.</strong> The app uses public police blotters to notify users about verified incidents in their area, but also allows users in select markets to upload their own reports and livestream.</li>
<li><strong>Right-leaning Twitter alternative Parler&#8217;s parent company laid off 75% of staff </strong>and chief execs, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/10/23549198/parler-parlement-technologies-layoffs-gettr-george-farmer-candace-owens" target="_blank" rel="noopener">leaving Parler</a> with just 20 employees. Kanye, as many expected, didn&#8217;t actually buy it.</li>
</ul>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/this-week-in-apps-chatgpt-app-scammers-instagram-revamp-and-a-consumer-spending-slowdown/">This Week in Apps: ChatGPT app scammers, Instagram revamp and a consumer spending slowdown</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/sarah-perez/">Sarah Perez</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/this-week-in-apps-chatgpt-app-scammers-instagram-revamp-and-a-consumer-spending-slowdown/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The slow-burn standardization of venture capital</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-slow-burn-standardization-of-venture-capital/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-slow-burn-standardization-of-venture-capital/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Natasha Mascarenhas]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 19:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EC Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups Weekly]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to Startups Weekly, a nuanced take on this week’s startup news and trends by Senior Reporter and Equity co-host Natasha Mascarenhas. To get this in your inbox, subscribe here. It took me a while, but I’m realizing that my startup love language is discussing any attempts to standardize the opaque and often informal world [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-slow-burn-standardization-of-venture-capital/">The slow-burn standardization of venture capital</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/natasha-mascarenhas/">Natasha Mascarenhas</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary"><em>W</em><em>elcome to Startups Weekly, a nuanced take on this week’s startup news and trends by Senior Reporter and Equity co-host </em><a href="https://www.instagram.com/natashathereporter/?hl=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Natasha Mascarenhas.</em></a><em> To get this in your inbox, subscribe <a href="https://techcrunch.com/newsletters/">here.</a></em></p>
<p>It took me a while, but I’m realizing that my startup love language is discussing any attempts to standardize the opaque and often informal world of venture capital. The clear tension is what entices me: How do you automate a process such as writing checks, which requires human buy-in and the art of trust in a way that leaves both parties happy.</p>
<p>There are funds <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/12/22/angellist-just-closed-a-25m-fund-to-back-startups-based-on-hiring-velocity/">that invest entirely based on data.</a> Or tools that help startups see all their <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/08/31/hum-capital-thinks-the-future-of-funding-is-a-return-to-old-school-wall-street/">financing options at the drop of a profile.</a> Or, as I covered this week, a tool for startups that lets companies simultaneously blast out the same application — or pitch — to multiple angel and pre-seed investors.</p>
<p>The tool, started by pre-seed firm Afore Capital, is based on <a href="https://www.commonapp.org/">Common App,</a> which sends one application to multiple colleges and universities. Afore&#8217;s take on the idea is to help founders rapidly pitch expert investors while also helping those investors get differentiated deal flow on a consistent basis. While it appears to be a low-stakes instrument — free for both parties to use — ease can sometimes come with a side of questions. Is Afore being too altruistic and sharing its intel? Does a blast offer the same signal as a warm intro?</p>
<p>Afore general partner Anamitra Banerji thinks that a funding-focused version of Common App will solve a classic conundrum: What happens when a startup isn’t a fit for your firm but is still a smart company that may make sense for your climate-focused emerging fund manager friend? Sometimes, those smart companies get lost in the cracks — think about the number of companies that don’t get into Y Combinator by a razor-thin margin — instead of being passed on to another firm.</p>
<p>Originally, Afore was thinking about sending companies that didn’t make it to its accelerator program to its network of outside investors. But Banerji said that now Afore sends startup applications to the network as soon as they submit, meaning that Afore sees it at the same time as other pre-seed investors.</p>
<p>“We’re taking the risk of exposing it to everyone else in the group and maybe losing the deal and allocation and things like that … but that kind of demonstrates to them, to us, that we’re not only sending them things we have passed on,” Banerji said.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>You can read my whole piece on TechCrunch+: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469568&amp;preview=true">“Is it time for a Common App for startup founders?”</a> DM me on <a href="https://twitter.com/nmasc_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://www.instagram.com/natashathereporter/?hl=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Instagram</a> if you want a discount code for TC+.</p>
<p>In the rest of this newsletter, we’ll talk about Carta, investor’s secret workflows and when the Kardashian strategy doesn’t quite work.</p>
<h2>Lawsuit and layoffs at Carta</h2>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/carta-previously-sued-for-gender-discrimination-is-now-suing-its-former-cto/">Carta is suing Jerry Talton, its former CTO</a>, alleging that he sent and received “sexually explicit, offensive, discriminatory and harassing messages with at least nine women including during work hours and on Carta’s systems.”</p>
<p><strong>Here’s why this is important: </strong>The lawsuit isn’t the only sign that Carta may be dealing with internal strife. The company confirmed that it had to lay off 10% of its staff in its second known workforce reduction over the pandemic.</p>
<p>It doesn’t help that several users of Carta’s services, which range from cap table management to fund administration, have been less than impressed by the platform in the recent months. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/carta-previously-sued-for-gender-discrimination-is-now-suing-its-former-cto/">TechCrunch spoke to a fund manager </a>who was transitioning away from the platform and who claims that his team had four different account managers in a less than two years, which “certainly didn’t help with continuity and understanding of our fund and needs.”</p>
<ul>
<li>Current and former Carta employees can reach out to me on Signal, a secure encrypted messaging app, at 925 271 0912. You can also DM me on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/nmasc_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">@nmasc_.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/crime-reporting-app-citizen-lays-off-33-employees/">Crime-reporting app Citizen lays off 33 employees</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/career-karma-conducts-another-round-of-layoffs-extends-runway-to-five-years/">Career Karma’s latest layoff underscores edtech’s new challenge</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/news-aggregator-smartnews-lays-off-40-of-non-japan-staff-with-further-reductions-planned-in-japan/">News aggregator SmartNews lays off 40% of US and China staff, with further reductions planned in Japan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/alphabet-robotics-division-intrinsic-hit-with-layoffs/">Alphabet robotics division Intrinsic hit with layoffs</a></li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_1763287" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1763287" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-1763287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="683" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg 2880w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Carta-Henry-Ward.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-1763287" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Carta</p></div></p>
<h2>SBFstack</h2>
<p>FTX’s infamous founder and former chief executive <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/ftx-sbf-launches-substack-i-didnt-steal-funds-and-i-certainly-didnt-stash-billions-away/">Sam Bankman-Fried started a Substack</a> this week. As my colleague Mary Ann Azevedo noted, it’s “a very unusual move for someone who was recently arrested and is facing eight counts of U.S. criminal charges.”</p>
<p><strong>Here’s why it&#8217;s important: </strong>As we discussed on Equity, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/frank-ly-the-kardashian-method-wont-work-for-sbf/">the Kardashian method of distraction</a> is not going to work for this former billionaire. There’s a weird sentiment around SBF’s actions lately, whether it’s calling him <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/04/sbfs-anticipated-not-guilty-plea-was-a-smart-play/">smart</a> for pleading not guilty or laughing at his Substack. that adds levity to a situation that ultimately should be taken quite seriously.</p>
<p>Him starting a Substack is no different; we’re all talking about it, thinking about him sidestepping his lawyer. But what if this isn’t as radical as we think? What if SBF sees that his noisy, outward conversation gets noticed, covered and amplified every time he speaks up, just because no one else has before? It’s a distraction; one that we may see more of until his expected trial in October.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2464014" style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg" alt="NEW YORK, US - JANUARY 03: Former FTX CEO and founder Sam Bankman-Fried arrives at Manhattan Federal Court in New York City on January 03, 2023. (Photo by Fatih Aktas/Anadolu Agency via Getty Images)" width="1024" height="667" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg 1932w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=150,98 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=300,195 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=768,500 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=680,443 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=1536,1001 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=1200,782 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-1245964106.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></p>
<p><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Fatih Aktas/Anadolu Agency / Getty Images</p>
<h2>The follow up</h2>
<p>You’ve probably been reading a lot about ChatGPT, OpenAI’s artificial intelligence tool that achieved virality with its savvy messaging ability. The tool, recently made available to the general public, is smart enough to answer serious and silly questions about profound topics, which has landed it in debates led by writers, educators, artists and more.</p>
<p>But beyond the initial excitement around the tool, I wanted to follow up on if it is actually making its way into people’s workflows. So, I dug into <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/some-investors-are-cautiously-implementing-chatgpt-in-their-workflows/?tpcc=tcplustwitter">how investors are using ChatGPT</a> in a piece for TC+ with Kyle Wiggers and Christine Hall.</p>
<p><strong>Here’s why it&#8217;s important:</strong> Some investors expressed that ChatGPT could be used for fact-checking purposes around market-size claims or growth potential; at the same time, so could Google. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/10/some-investors-are-cautiously-implementing-chatgpt-in-their-workflows/?tpcc=tcplustwitter">The argument for AI</a>, of course, would be that the content would be original and perhaps more targeted toward someone’s exact questions, while a general Google search may require extra digging and piecing different articles together.</p>
<p>As a nod toward the beginning of this newsletter, ChatGPT could be looked at as yet another way that venture tries to automate itself. It just depends on if investors think it is smart enough to reject startups, or if feedback is valued as the key currency of network building.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/openai-begins-piloting-chatgpt-professional-a-premium-version-of-its-viral-chatbot/">OpenAI begins piloting ChatGPT Professional, a premium version of its viral chatbot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/chatgpt-cybersecurity-threat/">Is ChatGPT a cybersecurity threat?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/benjihyam/status/1613363525493346304">ChatGPT is the new Clubhouse (question mark)</a></li>
</ul>
<p><div id="attachment_2451750" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2451750" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2451750" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg" alt="Artificial Intelligence - Chatbot concept" width="1024" height="683" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg 2121w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/GettyImages-1367281424.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2451750" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Carol Yepes / Getty Images</p></div></p>
<h2>Talking points</h2>
<h3>A non-exhaustive list of other news to note this week:</h3>
<ul>
<li>Packy McCormick closed Not Boring Capital Fund III, a $30 million investment vehicle seeking to invest in hard tech startups.</li>
<li>Microsoft announced <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/11/23550470/microsoft-employees-unlimited-time-off-2023">a controversial unlimited PTO policy.</a></li>
<li>Monique Woodard has <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexkonrad/2023/01/12/monique-woodard-new-fund-cake-ventures/?sh=32aec3f6b47a">closed $17 million for her debut fund at Cake Ventures.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexandralevine/2023/01/11/jp-morgan-fake-customers-frank-charlie-javice/">Per Forbes,</a> JP Morgan says that a startup that it recently acquired lied about millions of followers.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-64232515#:~:text=RRR%27s%20Naatu%20Naatu%20wins%20historic%20Golden%20Globe%20for%20best%20original%20song,-Published&amp;text=Indians%20are%20celebrating%20after%20Telugu,like%20Taylor%20Swift%20and%20Rihanna.">RRR won a Golden Globe.</a> That is all.</li>
<li>If you missed my most recent Startups Weekly, read it here: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/07/startup-resolution-number-one-follow-up-on-what-happened-last-year/">“Labor trends in 2023: Over-employment, fatigue and hope.”</a></li>
<li>TechCrunch is coming to Boston on April 20. I’ll be there with my favorite colleagues to interview top experts at a one-day founder summit.<a href="https://techcrunch.com/events/tc-early-stage-2023/"> Book your pass ASAP! </a></li>
</ul>
<p><em>Seen on TechCrunch</em></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/dungeons-and-dragons-ogl-wizards-of-the-coast/">Dungeons &amp; Dragons content creators are fighting to protect their livelihoods</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/tesla-keeps-slashing-prices-this-time-by-as-much-as-20/">Tesla keeps slashing prices, this time by as much as 20%</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/will-what-happened-at-ces-stay-at-ces/">Will what happened at CES, stay at CES?</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/our-obsession-with-pets-means-startups-aimed-at-vets-are-booming-as-digitail-shows/">Our obsession with pets means startups aimed at vets are booming, as Digitail shows</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/third-party-twitter-apps-tweetbot-twitterrific-echofon-down/">Third-party Twitter apps are facing issues, users say</a></p>
<p><em>Seen on TechCrunch+</em></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/youre-not-going-to-grow-into-your-2021-valuation/">You’re not going to grow into your 2021 valuation</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/sample-series-b-pitch-deck-mint-house/">Pitch Deck Teardown: Mint House’s $35M Series B deck</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/why-africa-had-no-unicorns-last-year-despite-record-fundraising-haul/">Why Africa had no unicorns last year despite record fundraising haul</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/web3-could-help-fashion-become-more-sustainable/">Web3 could help fashion become more sustainable</a></p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/pittsburghs-ai-expertise-may-give-rise-to-an-already-growing-startup-market/">Pittsburgh’s AI expertise may give rise to an already growing startup market</a></p>
<p>With that, I’m off to enjoy a weekend in Providence with some old friends. New England, how I missed you, your indulgently cozy weather and nostalgic streets.</p>
<p>Chat soon,</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/nmasc_" target="_blank" rel="noopener">N</a></p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-slow-burn-standardization-of-venture-capital/">The slow-burn standardization of venture capital</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/natasha-mascarenhas/">Natasha Mascarenhas</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-slow-burn-standardization-of-venture-capital/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The mirage of dry powder</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-mirage-of-dry-powder/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-mirage-of-dry-powder/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anna Heim]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 18:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[EC venture capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fundraising]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[lux capital]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[TechCrunch Exchange newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The Exchange]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469216</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Are VCs really sitting on record amounts of cash waiting to be deployed into new startups? If it sounds too good to be true, it probably is.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-mirage-of-dry-powder/">The mirage of dry powder</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/anna-heim/">Anna Heim</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">W</p>
<p><em>elcome to the TechCrunch Exchange, a weekly startups-and-markets newsletter. It’s inspired by the <a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/the-exchange/?utm_source=internal&amp;utm_medium=WPunit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">daily TechCrunch+ column</a> where it gets its name. Want it in your inbox every Saturday? Sign up <a href="https://techcrunch.com/newsletters?utm_source=internal&amp;utm_medium=WPunit" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>.</em></p>
<p><i>Are VCs really sitting on record amounts of cash waiting to be deployed into new startups? I wish. But if it sounds too good to be true, it probably is. — </i><a href="https://twitter.com/abracarioca" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><i>Anna</i></a></p>
<h2>Record levels, but…</h2>
<p>A recent <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/06/will-record-levels-of-dry-powder-trigger-a-delayed-explosion-of-startup-investment/">guest post</a> on TechCrunch+ wondered whether &#8220;record levels of dry powder [will] trigger a delayed explosion of startup investment.&#8221; The question relied on a postulate: That venture capitalists have raised plenty of funding that remains to be deployed.</p>
<p>The idea that dry powder has reached record levels is commonly shared, and it is backed by data.</p>
<p><div class="extra-crunch-offer-container"></div><p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-mirage-of-dry-powder/">The mirage of dry powder</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/anna-heim/">Anna Heim</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/the-mirage-of-dry-powder/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Is it time for a Common App for startup founders?</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/is-it-time-for-a-common-app-for-startup-founders/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/is-it-time-for-a-common-app-for-startup-founders/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Natasha Mascarenhas]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 14:00:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[fundraising]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pre-seed]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Seed]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469568</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Is it time for a Common App that helps startup founders pitch a ton of investors all at once? Afore Capital wants to make it happen.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/is-it-time-for-a-common-app-for-startup-founders/">Is it time for a Common App for startup founders?</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/natasha-mascarenhas/">Natasha Mascarenhas</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Venture capitalists may control capital, but one currency that they’re always in search of is an elusive, evolving one: deal flow. Betting early on the next big startup is enough to cement the entire <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/17/how-venture-capital-works/">return of a fund</a> (and then some) — and help that plucky investor make a name for themselves.</p>
<p>This reality makes Afore Capital’s latest product launch appear all the more benevolent. The venture firm, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/05/04/afore-150-million-pre-seed-standard-deal/">which just closed a $150 million fund in May 2022</a>, is launching what it describes as a common application for pre-seed startup founders. Similar to the well-known undergraduate college admission application, a startup Common App would allow founders to seamlessly pitch multiple investors using the same basic form and pitch deck — all at once.</p>
<p>Here’s how it works: Afore Capital has an accelerator-like program, Afore Alpha, that offers a standard pre-seed deal to founders. The application includes questions about the founding team, pitch deck, recent wins, inspiration and, interestingly, whether the startup has applied to or interviewed at Y Combinator for the firm’s internal benchmarking process.</p>
<p>Those accepted land a $1 million lead investment via a $10 million post-money SAFE, a deal that Afore notes is five times more capital and five times the valuation that accelerators like YC and Techstars offer.</p>
<p>Now, the same founding teams that apply to Afore’s program will automatically have their application blasted to 30-some investors in the venture firm’s network. The cohort, which Afore dubs as pre-seed experts, includes Trail Run Capital’s Allison Barr Allen, The New Normal Fund’s Allison Pickens, Night Ventures’ Em Herrera and Cambrian Ventures’ Rex Salisbury.</p>
<p><div class="extra-crunch-offer-container"></div><p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/is-it-time-for-a-common-app-for-startup-founders/">Is it time for a Common App for startup founders?</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/natasha-mascarenhas/">Natasha Mascarenhas</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/is-it-time-for-a-common-app-for-startup-founders/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Amazon quietly tests even cheaper Prime membership in India</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/amazon-prime-lite-membership-india/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/amazon-prime-lite-membership-india/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jagmeet Singh]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 12:17:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Commerce]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amazon]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amazon India]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[india]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470434</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Amazon is quietly piloting a new tier for its Prime membership in India, providing customers with access to popular benefits such as free two-day delivery and ad-supported Prime Video in standard definition at a lower price. The new tier, called Prime Lite, is currently available to select customers at a discounted annual price of $12 [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/amazon-prime-lite-membership-india/">Amazon quietly tests even cheaper Prime membership in India</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/jagmeet-singh/">Jagmeet Singh</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Amazon is quietly piloting a new tier for its Prime membership in India, providing customers with access to popular benefits such as free two-day delivery and ad-supported Prime Video in standard definition at a lower price.</p>
<p>The new tier, called Prime Lite, is currently available to select customers at a discounted annual price of $12 (999 Indian rupees). This is a cost-effective alternative to the regular Prime membership, which is priced at $18 (1499 Indian rupees) per year, or $2.20 (179 Indian rupees) per month. [H/T <a href="https://onlytech.com/exclusive-amazon-india-testing-ad-supported-prime-lite-membership-for-rs-999-per-year/">OnlyTech</a>]</p>
<p>Amazon&#8217;s Prime membership has been available in India <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2016/07/26/amazon-prime-launches-in-india-initially-without-prime-video-service/">since 2016</a>. It was priced at $12 a year for some time, though the company increased its pricing to $18 in December 2021. In the U.S., the Prime subscription is <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/prime/pipeline/partner_landing">available</a> at $139 per year or $14.99 per month.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2470435" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470435" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470435" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg" alt="Amazon Prime Lite" width="1024" height="683" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/amazon-prime-lite-benefits.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470435" class="wp-caption-text">Amazon has listed Prime Lite membership benefits on its website</p></div></p>
<p>Amazon has <a href="https://www.amazon.in/gp/help/customer/display.html/?nodeId=202044240">listed</a> the benefits of its Prime Lite membership on its Indian website and <a href="https://www.amazon.in/gp/help/customer/display.html?nodeId=G2B9L3YR7LR8J4XP">included</a> the new tier in its terms and conditions page.</p>
<p>The new offering comes just weeks after Amazon <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/19/amazon-quietly-launches-prime-gaming-in-india/">launched Prime Gaming</a> in India. The gaming-focused service is complementary to Amazon Prime and Prime Video subscribers.</p>
<p>The company did not respond to a request for comment Saturday.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/amazon-prime-lite-membership-india/">Amazon quietly tests even cheaper Prime membership in India</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/jagmeet-singh/">Jagmeet Singh</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/14/amazon-prime-lite-membership-india/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Twitter brings its &#8220;For You&#8221; and &#8220;Following&#8221; dual-timeline view to the web</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/twitter-brings-its-for-you-and-following-dual-timeline-view-to-the-web/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/twitter-brings-its-for-you-and-following-dual-timeline-view-to-the-web/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ivan Mehta]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 05:25:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Algorithmic Feeds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elon Musk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Twitter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[web interface]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470429</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>After updating its iOS app to display both algorithmic and chronological timelines side-by-side, Twitter is rolling out this update to the web interface. Earlier this week, the company renamed &#8220;Home&#8221; (algorithmic timeline) and &#8220;Latest&#8221; (chronological timeline) to &#8220;For You&#8221; and &#8220;Following&#8221;. The &#8220;For You&#8221; timeline now appears first in both the iOS app and the [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/twitter-brings-its-for-you-and-following-dual-timeline-view-to-the-web/">Twitter brings its &#8220;For You&#8221; and &#8220;Following&#8221; dual-timeline view to the web</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/ivan-mehta/">Ivan Mehta</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">After updating its iOS app to <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/twitter-makes-algorithmic-timeline-default-on-ios/">display both algorithmic and chronological timelines side-by-side</a>, Twitter is rolling out this update to the web interface.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, the company renamed &#8220;Home&#8221; (algorithmic timeline) and &#8220;Latest&#8221; (chronological timeline) to &#8220;For You&#8221; and &#8220;Following&#8221;. The &#8220;For You&#8221; timeline now appears first in both the iOS app and the web.</p>
<p>While you have to swipe between these timelines on the phone, you have to click on the timeline tabs to switch between them on the web. The good part is that at least in the web version, Twitter seems to remember users&#8217; choices. So even if a user closes the tab or the window and reopens Twitter, they will see whatever timeline you selected earlier.</p>
<p>Twitter said in its announcement that this view is coming to the Android app soon, too. Algorithmic timeline for everyone!</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="550" data-dnt="true">
<p lang="en" dir="ltr">You can now easily switch between “For you” and “Following” on web. Android coming soon <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f440.png" alt="👀" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>
<p>&mdash; Twitter Support (@TwitterSupport) <a href="https://twitter.com/TwitterSupport/status/1613968597692317701?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 13, 2023</a></p></blockquote>
<p><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script></div>
<p>One advantage of the new web view is that if you use Twitter lists, the revamped interface makes it easier to jump from one pinned list to another. Earlier, the only way to access lists on the web was to through <em>More &gt; Lists. </em>Quite tedious.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><div id="attachment_2470431" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470431" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2470431" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?w=680" alt="" width="680" height="253" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg 1208w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=150,56 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=300,112 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=768,286 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=680,253 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=1200,447 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screenshot-2023-01-14-at-10.33.55-AM.jpg?resize=50,19 50w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470431" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> TechCrunch</p></div></p>
<p>On Friday, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/third-party-twitter-apps-tweetbot-twitterrific-echofon-down/">third-party Twitter clients started experiencing massive issues</a> with users of many apps being unable to access content or log into their accounts. Developers of these apps said that they tried to contact Twitter but didn&#8217;t hear back. At the time of writing the issue is still persistent.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="y7RlD9BkKi"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/twitter-makes-algorithmic-timeline-default-on-ios/">Twitter makes algorithmic timeline default on iOS</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Twitter makes algorithmic timeline default on iOS&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/11/twitter-makes-algorithmic-timeline-default-on-ios/embed/#?secret=u5LDSXSPBp#?secret=y7RlD9BkKi" data-secret="y7RlD9BkKi" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/twitter-brings-its-for-you-and-following-dual-timeline-view-to-the-web/">Twitter brings its &#8220;For You&#8221; and &#8220;Following&#8221; dual-timeline view to the web</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/ivan-mehta/">Ivan Mehta</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/twitter-brings-its-for-you-and-following-dual-timeline-view-to-the-web/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sealed buys sensor startup InfiSense to fuel energy-saving services</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sealed-buys-sensor-startup-infisense-to-fuel-energy-saving-services/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sealed-buys-sensor-startup-infisense-to-fuel-energy-saving-services/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Harri Weber]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 01:27:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Climate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Mergers and Acquisitions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sealed]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2469206</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Sealed built a business around predicting energy use and getting homeowners to ditch fossil fuels. So, naturally, the company&#8217;s first acquisition is a startup that tracks energy on a granular level. Sealed did not disclose the terms of the deal, but said in a statement that scooping up Burlington, Vermont-based InfiSense would help it &#8220;cut [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sealed-buys-sensor-startup-infisense-to-fuel-energy-saving-services/">Sealed buys sensor startup InfiSense to fuel energy-saving services</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/harri-weber/">Harri Weber</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Sealed built a business around predicting energy use and getting homeowners to ditch fossil fuels. So, naturally, the company&#8217;s first acquisition is a startup that tracks energy on a granular level.</p>
<p>Sealed did not disclose the terms of the deal, but said in a <a href="https://www.businesswire.com/news/home/20230112005187/en/Sealed-Acquires-Data-Software-Company-InfiSense-To-Increase-Energy-Data-Access" target="_blank" rel="noopener">statement</a> that scooping up Burlington, Vermont-based InfiSense would help it &#8220;cut home energy waste.&#8221;</p>
<p>Headquartered in Manhattan, Sealed finances and oversees electrification upgrades, such as replacing oil or gas heaters with electric heat pumps and insulation. Ridding homes of fossil fuels can lower energy bills, <a href="https://www.pbs.org/newshour/show/more-homes-using-heat-pumps-as-cheaper-greener-alternative-to-fossil-fuels" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cut household emissions</a> and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/09/climate-benefits-of-killing-gas-stoves-arent-what-you-think-but-the-health-benefits-are/">improve your health</a>. You may have seen this topic in the news recently, because <a href="https://www.vox.com/energy-and-environment/2023/1/11/23549303/gas-stove-regulation-explained" target="_blank" rel="noopener">potential stove regulations</a> are now the latest flashpoint in a <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/gas-stove-ban-culture-war/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">culture war over clean energy</a>.</p>
<p>To that point, InfiSense&#8217;s sensors and software monitor air quality in addition to energy use in buildings, and Sealed plans to share this sort of air-quality data with customers down the line.</p>
<p>Sealed is unique in covering installation and weatherization costs upfront. Instead, it charges a fixed fee based on the energy its <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/04/28/sealed-decarbonize-heat-pump-fifth-wall/">machine learning algorithms</a> predict homeowners will save over time. If Sealed underestimates a homes&#8217; energy use, it eats the cost — hence the need to hone those predictions.</p>
<p>The &#8220;lifeblood of our company is our ability to predict people&#8217;s energy usage over time, and that relies on great access to data,&#8221; co-founder and CEO Lauren Salz said in a call with TechCrunch. <span style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;">Currently, Sealed&#8217;s algorithms rely on monthly energy data from utilities, but b</span><span style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;">uying InfiSense will give it &#8220;access to a deeper level of data from customers,&#8221; Salz said. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;">Sealed plans to install InfiSense&#8217;s sensors in some of its customers&#8217; homes, but Salz said it won&#8217;t require them. The data Sealed gathers will inform its predictions as well as enable it to offer curious customers an up-close look at their energy usage and air quality.</span></p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sealed-buys-sensor-startup-infisense-to-fuel-energy-saving-services/">Sealed buys sensor startup InfiSense to fuel energy-saving services</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/harri-weber/">Harri Weber</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sealed-buys-sensor-startup-infisense-to-fuel-energy-saving-services/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sequoia Capital&#8217;s Alfred Lin in his first public interview since the implosion of FTX (video)</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sequoia-capitals-alfred-lin-in-his-first-public-interview-since-the-implosion-of-ftx-video/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sequoia-capitals-alfred-lin-in-his-first-public-interview-since-the-implosion-of-ftx-video/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Connie Loizos]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Jan 2023 00:10:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[alfred lin]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FTX]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sequoia capital]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470299</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Last night, at an industry event hosted in San Francisco by this editor, venture capitalist Alfred Lin of Sequoia Capital sat down for a one-on-one conversation about the evolution of his storied investment firm, which has enjoyed a largely unblemished record of stunning success &#8212; a record since marred by its roughly $200 million investment [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sequoia-capitals-alfred-lin-in-his-first-public-interview-since-the-implosion-of-ftx-video/">Sequoia Capital&#8217;s Alfred Lin in his first public interview since the implosion of FTX (video)</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/connie-loizos/">Connie Loizos</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Last night, at an <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/145636603@N06/albums/72177720305218232/with/52624810887/">industry event</a> hosted in San Francisco by this editor, venture capitalist Alfred Lin of Sequoia Capital sat down for a one-on-one conversation about the evolution of his storied investment firm, which has enjoyed a largely unblemished record of stunning success &#8212; a record since marred by its roughly $200 million investment in the crypto currency exchange FTX.</p>
<p>The investment, once a source of pride for the firm, has tarnished not only Sequoia but also Lin, who led the deal on behalf of Sequoia and who was also the firm&#8217;s point of contact with CEO Sam Bankman-Fried for a year and a half. He spoke thoughtfully yesterday about how he feels today about a bet gone so wrong.</p>
<p>Asked, for example, whether looking back, there were signs that Lin sees now that he missed earlier, he answered after a pause: &#8220;I thought [Bankman-Fried] was very smart . . . He answers questions very logically and very succinctly. Could we have spotted any tells? I don&#8217;t know. There&#8217;s what I know today and what I knew at the time. If I knew at the time, we wouldn&#8217;t have invested. So today, I think the thing that gets me to reassess is . . . it&#8217;s not that we made the investment. It&#8217;s the year-and-a-half working relationship afterward, and I still didn&#8217;t see it. And that is difficult.&#8221;</p>
<p>If it was particularly challenging for Lin given that just a year earlier, he <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexkonrad/2021/04/13/sequoia-alfred-lin-2021-midas-list-new-no-1/?sh=3fc4f8c66102" target="_blank" rel="noopener">topped</a> Forbes&#8217; annual Midas List, he didn&#8217;t say so. But he suggested the experience remains disturbing to him because Bankman-Fried seemed to seize on what the venture industry sees as one of its greatest strengths.</p>
<p>Explained Lin, it&#8217;s &#8220;a trust business. And yes, we need to trust and verify, and we try to verify what we can. But we start from a position of trust, because if we don&#8217;t trust the founders that we work with, why would you ever invest in them?&#8221;</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2470353" style="width: 809px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470353" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2470353 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg" alt="" width="799" height="533" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg 799w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg?resize=680,454 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/52624804642_c1fe580456_c.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 799px) 100vw, 799px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470353" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> <a href="https://www.danipadgett.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dani Padgett </a></p></div></p>
<p>Lin had a lot more to say about FTX, including whether he has sympathy today for Bankman-Fried. &#8220;I feel bad&#8221; for the disgraced founder instead of sympathetic, Lin said, suggesting that he&#8217;s trying to reserve judgment until all the facts come out. Lin said he believes Bankman-Fried was capable enough to have &#8220;raised money or propped up&#8221; the company &#8220;in a legit way.&#8221;</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>Lin defended Sequoia&#8217;s decision to manage its positions in its portfolio companies well past the point that they go public.</p>
<p>Lin also confirmed during the event that in a gesture to its limited partners, Sequoia last year reduced its management fees on two funds that it rolled out a year ago &#8212; a $950 million ecosystem fund that it uses to back other managers&#8217; funds and a $600 million crypto fund. Lin said that rather than charge its backers on committed capital, which is standard in the industry, it is charging them management fees on the invested capital alone.</p>
<p>On that front, he said that just 10% of the crypto fund has been deployed, adding that Sequoia remains &#8220;long-term optimistic&#8221; about crypto, despite the uncomfortably close correlation between many of the biggest crypto outfits. (Asked whether such codependencies have been a revelation since FTX&#8217;s implosion, Lin responded: &#8220;The whole economy is interrelated.&#8221;)</p>
<p>Lastly, Lin shared his views regarding how generative AI &#8212; one of the buzziest areas of interest for the venture industry right now &#8212; is changing the opportunity for both VCs and investors.</p>
<p>Full video of the conversation follows.</p>
<div class="embed breakout embed--video embed--youtube"><iframe title="StrictlyVC in conversation with Alfred Lin of Sequoia Capital" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Gf-d-Hrx6_A?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sequoia-capitals-alfred-lin-in-his-first-public-interview-since-the-implosion-of-ftx-video/">Sequoia Capital&#8217;s Alfred Lin in his first public interview since the implosion of FTX (video)</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/connie-loizos/">Connie Loizos</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/sequoia-capitals-alfred-lin-in-his-first-public-interview-since-the-implosion-of-ftx-video/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bugatti&#8217;s new electric scooter is bigger with W16 Mistral vibes</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/bugattis-new-electric-scooter-is-bigger-with-w16-mistral-vibes/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/bugattis-new-electric-scooter-is-bigger-with-w16-mistral-vibes/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kirsten Korosec]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 23:05:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Transportation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bugatti]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CES]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CES 2023]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[electric scooters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[micromobility]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[transportation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470155</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Somewhere hidden amid the thousands of flashy displays and exhibits at CES 2023 in Las Vegas was the newly upgraded 2023 Bugatti electric scooter. TechCrunch never saw it. Did anyone? Luckily, details and images of the 2023 model, a 10% larger, more premium electric scooter, have now been released into the world. Bugatti, through a [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/bugattis-new-electric-scooter-is-bigger-with-w16-mistral-vibes/">Bugatti&#8217;s new electric scooter is bigger with W16 Mistral vibes</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kirsten-korosec/">Kirsten Korosec</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Somewhere hidden amid the thousands of flashy displays and exhibits at <a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/ces/">CES 2023</a> in Las Vegas was the newly upgraded 2023 Bugatti electric scooter.</p>
<p>TechCrunch never saw it. Did anyone?</p>
<p>Luckily, details and images of the 2023 model, a 10% larger, more premium electric scooter, have now been released into the world.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/07/05/vw-offloads-bugatti-to-rimac-to-form-new-ev-company-bugatti-rimac/">Bugatti</a>, through a partnership with tech accessory company Bytech, launched a $1,200 electric scooter in 2022. The two companies paired up again for a second-generation scooter that is beefier, equipped with new features and colors, and has larger &#8220;self-repairing&#8221; tires.</p>
<p>The 2023 scooter is 10% larger than its predecessor and is equipped with a 36-volt/15.6Ah battery and an electric motor with a maximum output of 1,000 watts, according to the companies. That battery and motor combo allows the scooter to handle up to an 18-degree incline, max speed of 22 miles per hour and can cover 35 miles on a single charge, according to the company. (That&#8217;s up from the 22-mile range in the previous model.)</p>
<p>No word yet on the pricing for this bigger second-generation model. Perhaps this is one of those &#8220;if you have to ask&#8221; moments.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2470301" style="width: 2010px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470301" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2470301 size-full" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg" alt="2023 Bugatti Electric Scooters Premium 2" width="2000" height="1155" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg 2000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=150,87 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=300,173 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=768,444 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=680,393 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=1536,887 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=1200,693 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/2023-Bugatti-Electric-Scooters-Premium-2.jpg?resize=50,29 50w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2470301" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Bugatti/Bytech</p></div></p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>The overall expanded size extends to a larger deck area for standing and a 10-inch tire (the previous one was nine inches) with a pneumatic tubeless design that comes with a built-in glue repair mechanism that repairs potential tire punctures. (The technology sounds a lot like tubeless tires used in bicycles. The tires can be filled with a sealant that is released and coats the interior if there is a puncture.)</p>
<p>The new Bugatti scooter now has passcode protection, a touchscreen that displays speed, rider mode, battery life and headlight operations. The scooter is equipped with leather handle grips and comes in three colors, including a new yellow and black design that gives homage to Bugatti founder Ettore Bugatti (apparently his favorite color combo) and the W16 Mistral roadster, which has a similar color scheme.</p>
<p>At the end of those leather handles are two small LED lights. For added safety and visibility, the turn signals are synchronized and displayed on the accompanying MIPS certified helmet.</p>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/tag/ces-2023"><img decoding="async" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/ces-2023-banner.jpg" alt="Read more about CES 2023 on TechCrunch" /></a></p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/bugattis-new-electric-scooter-is-bigger-with-w16-mistral-vibes/">Bugatti&#8217;s new electric scooter is bigger with W16 Mistral vibes</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kirsten-korosec/">Kirsten Korosec</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/bugattis-new-electric-scooter-is-bigger-with-w16-mistral-vibes/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Daily Crunch: 2 Tesla models qualify for EV tax credits after company marks prices down by 20%</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/daily-crunch-2-tesla-models-qualify-for-ev-tax-credits-after-company-marks-prices-down-by-20/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/daily-crunch-2-tesla-models-qualify-for-ev-tax-credits-after-company-marks-prices-down-by-20/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Christine Hall]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 23:05:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Venture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Daily Crunch]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[venture capital]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470190</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hello, friends, and welcome to Daily Crunch, bringing you the most important startup, tech and venture capital news in a single package.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/daily-crunch-2-tesla-models-qualify-for-ev-tax-credits-after-company-marks-prices-down-by-20/">Daily Crunch: 2 Tesla models qualify for EV tax credits after company marks prices down by 20%</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/christine-hall/">Christine Hall</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary"><em>To get a roundup of TechCrunch’s biggest and most important stories delivered to your inbox every day at 3 p.m. PST,</em><a href="https://techcrunch.com/newsletters/"><em> subscribe here</em></a><em>.</em></p>
<p>The team who went to CES is back at their desks. If you missed the barrage of stories — or simply couldn’t stay on top of them — <a href="https://twitter.com/bheater" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Brian</a> wrote up an amazing <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/ces-2023-debrief/">CES 2023 debrief</a>. Give that a skim, and you’ll be safe in the knowledge that you didn’t miss anything major as you grab your favorite easy chair and a book to settle in for the weekend.  — <a href="https://twitter.com/ChristineMHall" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Christine</a> and <a href="http://twitter.com/haje" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Haje</a></p>
<h2>The TechCrunch Top 3</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/tesla-keeps-slashing-prices-this-time-by-as-much-as-20/"><strong>Slasher movie, but IRL</strong></a>: Tesla is reducing its prices again, this time for U.S. buyers, by as much as 20%,<a href="https://twitter.com/kirstenkorosec" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Kirsten</a> reports. This new lower base, which dips below $55,000, “is important because it allows buyers to qualify for the $7,500 federal tax incentive,” she writes.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/fintech-mayfair-emerges-from-stealth-to-offer-businesses-a-higher-yield-on-their-cash/"><strong>Claws out</strong></a>: Fintech startup Mayfair debuted its high-yield APR for businesses, buoyed by $10 million in funding from investors like Tiger Global. <a href="https://twitter.com/bayareawriter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mary Ann</a> has more on how the company is able to offer such a high interest rate.</li>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/google-says-india-antitrust-order-poses-threat-to-national-security/"><strong>If A then B</strong></a>: <a href="https://twitter.com/refsrc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Manish</a> writes about Google warning India that if its antitrust ruling is allowed to stand, it will pose a threat to national security and cause Android device prices to rise in the region.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Startups and VC</h2>
<p>It seems like SPACs aren’t completely dead yet, as World View, a company developing stratospheric balloons for Earth observation and tourism, is heading to the public markets, <a href="https://twitter.com/breadfrom" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Aria</a> reports. The company announced Friday that it would merge with special purpose acquisition company (SPAC) Leo Holdings Corp. II <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/stratospheric-balloon-company-world-view-to-go-public-in-350m-spac-deal/">in a deal worth $350 million, as it seeks to build out what it calls “the stratospheric economy.”</a></p>
<p>And we have five more for you:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>E Ink leaves monochrome behind</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/harrisonweber" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Harri</a> writes that E Ink’s latest color displays have her<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/e-ink-color-tech-epaper-magazines/"> dreaming of electronic paper magazines</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Twitter rival raises moneys</strong>: Twitter rival<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/twitter-rival-t2-raises-its-first-outside-funding-1-1m-from-a-group-of-high-profile-angels/"> T2 raises its first outside funding — $1.1 million </a>from a group of high-profile angels, reports <a href="https://twitter.com/ingridlunden" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ingrid</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Layoffs in crypto</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/refsrc" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Manish</a> reports that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/crypto-com-cuts-20-jobs-amid-unforeseeable-industry-events/">Crypto.com cuts 20% of jobs </a>amid &#8220;unforeseeable&#8221; industry events.</li>
<li><strong>Layoffs in crime reporting</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/asilbwrites">Amanda</a> reports that crime reporting app <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/crime-reporting-app-citizen-lays-off-33-employees/">Citizen lays off 33 employees</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Layoffs in fintech</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/JagmeetS13" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jagmeet</a> reports that Greenlight, a kids-focused fintech startup, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/greenlight-fintech-layoff/">lays off 104 employees to optimize expenses</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2>You&#8217;re not going to grow into your 2021 valuation</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2469989" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2469989" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2469989" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg" alt="" width="1024" height="685" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg 2116w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=300,201 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=768,514 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=680,455 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=1536,1028 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=2048,1370 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=1200,803 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/GettyImages-113030995.jpg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2469989" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> <a href="https://www.gettyimages.in/search/photographer?photographer=nfsphoto" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nfsphoto <span class="screen-reader-text">(opens in a new window)</span></a> / Getty Images</p></div></p>
<p>Many, if not most, of the founders who are attached to their 2021 valuations are living in a fantasy, according to Jeremy Abelson and Jacob Sonnenberg of Irving Investors.</p>
<p>For this TC+ post, they worked out &#8220;the simple math behind how long it will take companies to price their IPO at a flat round to their previous 2021 valuations.&#8221;</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>Companies with 75% YoY growth &#8220;can entertain the discussion,&#8221; but &#8220;if you are growing sub 30%, there is a strong chance that growing into your 2021 valuation is impossible.&#8221;</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="afGd97KnMl"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/youre-not-going-to-grow-into-your-2021-valuation/">You&#8217;re not going to grow into your 2021 valuation</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;You&#8217;re not going to grow into your 2021 valuation&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/youre-not-going-to-grow-into-your-2021-valuation/embed/#?secret=WLhkis12VE#?secret=afGd97KnMl" data-secret="afGd97KnMl" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>Three more from the TC+ team:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The right funds, the right way</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/cantequera">Carlos Antequera</a> shares <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/4-tips-to-find-the-funding-that-fits-your-business/">4 tips to find the funding that fits your business</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Much strategery</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/rebecca_szkutak" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Becca</a> asks whether it makes sense to <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/does-it-ever-make-more-sense-to-raise-a-structured-round-over-taking-a-valuation-cut/">raise a structured round over taking a valuation cut?</a></li>
<li><strong>Crypto chaos continues</strong>: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/crypto-in-for-a-choppy-year-of-slow-capital-deployment-investors-say/">Crypto in for a &#8220;choppy year&#8221; of slow capital deployment</a>, investors share with <a href="https://twitter.com/jacqmelinek" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jacquelyn</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/techcrunchplus/"><em>TechCrunch+</em></a><em> is our membership program that helps founders and startup teams get ahead of the pack.</em><a href="https://link.techcrunch.com/click/26685582.342535/aHR0cHM6Ly90ZWNoY3J1bmNoLmNvbS9zdWJzY3JpYmUvP3V0bV9tZWRpdW09VENuZXdzbGV0dGVyJnRwY2M9VENkYWlseW5ld3NsZXR0ZXI/6036d5494a049802a929497cBf82fd2bd"><em> You can sign up here</em></a><em>. Use code “DC” for a 15% discount on an annual subscription!</em></p>
<h2>Big Tech Inc.</h2>
<p>Are you scooting around Paris right now? Well, this could be your last time. <a href="https://twitter.com/romaindillet" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Romain</a> has a lengthy look at how <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/scooters-in-paris-are-at-a-crossroad-and-it-could-shape-the-future-of-micromobility/">scooters in Paris are at a crossroads</a> as the city ponders whether to put the brakes on renewing contracts with three companies. As <a href="https://getyarn.io/yarn-clip/73555077-0b46-4a17-ba24-28c515a2ef92">Michael Scott said</a>, “Buckle up, it’s going to be a bumpy one.”</p>
<p>Meanwhile, <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahintampa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/kirstenkorosec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kirsten</a> paired up on a scoop that Tokyo-based <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/news-aggregator-smartnews-lays-off-40-of-non-japan-staff-with-further-reductions-planned-in-japan/">news aggregator SmartNews laid off 40% of staff in the U.S. and China</a>.</p>
<p>And we have five more for you:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>The tweet is on</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/indianidle" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ivan</a> writes that Twitter users are reporting that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/third-party-twitter-apps-tweetbot-twitterrific-echofon-down/">third-party apps on the site are facing issues</a>. Meanwhile, over at Twitter alternative Mastodon,<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/medium-embraces-twitter-alternative-mastodon-with-launch-of-its-own-community/"> Medium launches its own community</a>. <a href="https://twitter.com/sarahintampa" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sarah</a> has more.</li>
<li><strong>A little bit of history repeating</strong>: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/author/devin-coldewey/">Devin</a> writes that President Biden’s <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/bidens-call-to-unite-against-big-tech-abuses-sure-sounds-familiar/">call to “unite against big tech abuses”</a> sounds kinda familiar.</li>
<li><strong>Layoffs in robotics</strong>:<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/alphabet-robotics-division-intrinsic-hit-with-layoffs/"> Alphabet’s robotics division</a> is letting people go,<a href="https://twitter.com/bheater" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> Brian</a> reports.</li>
<li><strong>If you like clickety-clack on your keyboard</strong>: <a href="https://twitter.com/fredericl" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Frederic</a> reports that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/keychron-gets-it-right-with-its-q10-alice-style-keyboard/">Keychron gets it right</a> with its Q10 Alice-style keyboard.</li>
<li><strong>Do you hear what I hear?</strong>:<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/vall-es-quickie-voice-deepfakes-should-worry-you-if-you-werent-worried-already/"> VALL-E’s quickie voice deepfakes</a> should worry you, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/author/devin-coldewey/">Devin</a> writes.</li>
</ul>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/daily-crunch-2-tesla-models-qualify-for-ev-tax-credits-after-company-marks-prices-down-by-20/">Daily Crunch: 2 Tesla models qualify for EV tax credits after company marks prices down by 20%</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/christine-hall/">Christine Hall</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/daily-crunch-2-tesla-models-qualify-for-ev-tax-credits-after-company-marks-prices-down-by-20/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>HBO’s ‘The Last of Us’ is a video game adaptation that&#8217;s actually good</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/the-last-of-us-hbo-series-review/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/the-last-of-us-hbo-series-review/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lauren Forristal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 22:34:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Gaming]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Media & Entertainment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[HBO Max]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470171</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This weekend, HBO and HBO Max will premiere the first episode of “The Last of Us,&#8221; a post-apocalyptic thriller based on the popular video game. On Sunday, January 15, it will debut on HBO at 9:00 p.m. ET and stream in 4K on HBO Max. The series will have nine episodes in total and follows [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/the-last-of-us-hbo-series-review/">HBO’s ‘The Last of Us’ is a video game adaptation that&#8217;s actually good</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/lauren-forristal/">Lauren Forristal</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">This weekend, HBO and HBO Max will premiere the first episode of “<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/11/02/hbo-series-the-last-of-us-premieres-this-january/">The Last of Us,</a>&#8221; a post-apocalyptic thriller based on the popular video game. On Sunday, January 15, it will debut on HBO at 9:00 p.m. ET and stream in 4K on HBO Max. The series will have nine episodes in total and follows the plot of the 2013 game where a fungus outbreak turns half of the world’s population into flesh-eating zombies &#8212; a.k.a. “clickers.”</p>
<p>Starring “The Mandalorian” actor Pedro Pascal as Joel, and “Game of Thrones” actress Bella Ramsey as Ellie, “<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/09/26/hbo-max-releases-the-last-of-us-trailer/">The Last of Us</a>” centers around these two characters who, at first, want nothing to do with each other. Joel and his confidante, Tess (played by Anna Torv), are tasked with smuggling Ellie out of the quarantine zone in Boston and across the U.S. As the story progresses, Ellie and Joel’s dynamic shifts as they start to depend on each other.</p>
<p>“The Last of Us” is HBO’s first foray into adapting a video game into a series. But you wouldn’t know it based on the quality. After so many video game adaptation fails, the show will likely be a relief to many “Last of Us” fans. Granted, it was co-written by the game’s creator, Neil Druckmann, so there was little room for it to flop in the first place. HBO’s “The Last of Us” is Druckmann’s love letter addressed to the millions of loyal fans that help keep the decade-long franchise alive.</p>
<p><strong>(<em>“The Last of Us” spoilers ahead.</em>)</strong></p>
<div class="embed breakout embed--video embed--youtube"><iframe title="The Last of Us | Official Trailer | HBO Max" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uLtkt8BonwM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p>On the surface, “The Last of Us” may just seem like another survival story with zombies. However, unlike the stomach-churning gore that’s associated with the genre, the HBO series doesn’t focus on dramatic, long-winded shootouts and shots of the undead being sliced in half. Instead, it focuses on the human relationships between the uninfected as their world turns more uncertain by the minute.</p>
<p>What makes this show so great, in our opinion, is the fact that viewers don’t need to play the game to understand it. <span style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;">Although HBO’s “The Last of Us” is very accurate to the timeline of the game and has Easter eggs sprinkled throughout, there are some key differences that help the story speak to a larger audience.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 1rem; letter-spacing: -0.1px;"> For instance, the game takes place in 2033, whereas the show is set in 2023. This was done to help viewers &#8220;</span>connect a little bit more,&#8221; co-creator Craig Mazin said in a <a href="https://www.cnet.com/culture/entertainment/the-last-of-us-hbo-adaptation-goes-way-beyond-the-playstation-games/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CNET interview</a>. &#8220;If I&#8217;m watching a show in the year 2023 and it takes place in 2043, it&#8217;s just a little less real. I thought it might be interesting to just say, &#8216;Hey, look, in this parallel universe, this is happening right now,'&#8221; Mazin added.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>Another distinction that we’ve noticed so far is how in-depth the show goes with Joel’s backstory. The beginning cutscene of the video game is only about 15 minutes long, whereas HBO’s “The Last of Us” takes a more drawn-out approach.</p>
<p>The first episode begins with a flashback from 2003, when the initial fungal outbreak occurs. In this scene, Joel appears as a less intense man, sleeping through his alarm and facing simple problems like forgetting to buy pancake mix. Also, Joel’s daughter, Sarah (played by Nico Parker), gets a a lot of airtime, with clips of her cooking scrambled eggs, fixing her dad’s watch and baking cookies with her next-door neighbor. These scenes are unique to the show and give viewers more time to get to know the father-daughter duo, which makes the events that follow that more heart-wrenching.</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2470251" style="width: 690px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470251" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-2470251" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?w=680" alt="" width="680" height="394" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png 2110w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=150,87 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=300,174 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=768,445 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=680,394 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=1536,890 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=2048,1186 2048w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=1200,695 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Screen-Shot-2023-01-13-at-4.34.42-PM.png?resize=50,29 50w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2470251" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> HBO</p></div></p>
<p>The episode then jumps to 2023 when Joel is a smuggler in a quarantine zone guarded by FEDRA (Federal Disaster Response Agency) soldiers, while a militia group led by Marlene (Merle Dandridge) called “The Fireflies” aims to revolt against military oppression and restore government control.</p>
<p>Viewers then meet Ellie, a teen that&#8217;s immune to the fungus and is being held captive by The Fireflies. Like in the game, the series will mainly focus on Joel and Ellie&#8217;s relationship and how their views on the world differ.</p>
<p>Other characters who have yet to be introduced include Frank (Murray Bartlett), Bill (Nick Offerman), Kathleen (Melanie Lynskey), Florence (Elaine Miles), Riley (Storm Reid), Perry (Jeffrey Pierce) and Henry (Lamar Johnson).</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="rsMiQd7f8y"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/11/02/hbo-series-the-last-of-us-premieres-this-january/">HBO series ‘The Last of Us’ premieres this January</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;HBO series ‘The Last of Us’ premieres this January&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2022/11/02/hbo-series-the-last-of-us-premieres-this-january/embed/#?secret=skH0UzUHSw#?secret=rsMiQd7f8y" data-secret="rsMiQd7f8y" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>&#8220;The Last of Us&#8221; will likely do well for HBO Max, despite the streaming service <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/12/hbo-maxs-ad-free-monthly-subscription-price-is-increasing-by-1/">increasing</a> its subscription price earlier this week.</p>
<p>Similar to its other highly anticipated shows like the &#8220;Game of Thrones&#8221; spinoff, &#8220;<a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/23/house-of-the-dragon-series-premiere-is-the-biggest-in-hbos-history-with-almost-10-million-viewers/">House of the Dragon</a>,&#8221; the company went all out to promote its newest series. For instance, Warner Bros. Discovery hosted a two-hour immersive experience and screening of the first episode in New York City, giving guests an array of &#8220;The Last of Us&#8221; themed goodies, photo opportunities and more.</p>
<p>On January 15, HBO Max is also launching<em> </em><a href="https://listen.hbo.com/the-last-of-us-podcast" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>“</em>The Last of Us Podcast,”</a> hosted by Troy Baker, the voice actor who plays Joel in the game. Druckmann and Mazin will also be featured in episodes as they discuss how they made the show and other behind-the-scenes stories. Each episode will be released every Sunday in tandem with the show.</p>
<div class="embed breakout embed--video embed--youtube"><iframe title="Coming Soon - The Official The Last of Us Podcast | HBO Max" width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-GcTQ80zJtc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/the-last-of-us-hbo-series-review/">HBO’s ‘The Last of Us’ is a video game adaptation that&#8217;s actually good</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/lauren-forristal/">Lauren Forristal</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/the-last-of-us-hbo-series-review/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>BlackRock acquires minority stake in SMB 401(k) provider Human Interest</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/blackrock-acquires-minority-stake-in-smb-401k-provider-human-interest/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/blackrock-acquires-minority-stake-in-smb-401k-provider-human-interest/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mary Ann Azevedo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 22:13:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Fintech]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[401k]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BlackRock]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Human Interest]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470252</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Investment giant BlackRock announced Friday it is taking a minority stake in venture-backed fintech startup Human Interest. Terms of the deal were not disclosed. Human Interest’s digital retirement benefits platform allows users “to launch a retirement plan in minutes and put it on autopilot,” according to the company. It also touts that it has eliminated [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/blackrock-acquires-minority-stake-in-smb-401k-provider-human-interest/">BlackRock acquires minority stake in SMB 401(k) provider Human Interest</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/mary-ann-azevedo/">Mary Ann Azevedo</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">Investment giant BlackRock announced Friday it is taking a minority stake in venture-backed fintech startup <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/08/04/human-interest-raises-200m-at-a-1b-valuation-plans-for-an-ipo/">Human Interest</a>.</p>
<p>Terms of the deal were not disclosed.</p>
<p>Human Interest’s digital retirement benefits platform allows users “to launch a retirement plan in minutes and put it on autopilot,” according to the company. It also touts that it has eliminated all 401(k) transaction fees. The startup told TechCrunch previously that it works with “every kind of SMB” — from tech startups to law offices, to dentists to dog walkers, to manufacturing firms, to social justice nonprofits.</p>
<p>The San Francisco–based company has raised a total of $336.7 million in funding since it was founded by Paul Sawaya and Roger Lee in 2015. The Rise Fund, TPG’s global impact investing platform, led a $200 million round for Human Interest in August 2021 that propelled it to unicorn status. Other backers include SoftBank Vision Fund 2, Crosslink Capital, NewView Capital, Glynn Capital, U.S. Venture Partners, Wing Venture Capital, Uncork Capital, Slow Capital and Susa Ventures, among others. Since the initial closing of that round, Human Interest said <a href="https://humaninterest.com/pressroom/articles/blackrock-invests-in-human-interest/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in a blog post</a> that it has seen has over 400% growth in the number of customers and revenue. At the time of that raise, execs told TechCrunch that the company was targeting a traditional IPO sometime in 2023, hoping to have “$200 million+ in run-rate revenue before going public.” In August of 2021, it was at “tens of millions of run-rate revenue, and adding millions of new revenue each month, according to execs.</p>
<p>“BlackRock has an amazing team focused on providing high-quality retirement saving and investment options. We are excited to work with BlackRock to find ways to bring retirement within reach of millions of additional workers in the coming years,” said Jeff Schneble, CEO of Human Interest, in a written statement.</p>
<p>&#8220;We look forward to helping Human Interest close the access gap,” said Anne Ackerley, head of BlackRock’s Retirement Group, in a statement.</p>
<p>Human Interest co-founder Lee<span style="font-weight: 400;"> moved on years ago, recently founding another startup, </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/10/04/this-startup-wants-to-help-other-startups-figure-out-compensation/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Comprehensive.io</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and launching layoff tracker </span><a href="https://layoffs.fyi/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Layoffs.FYI</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> soon after the COVID-19 pandemic hit.</span></p>
<p><i>Want more fintech news in your inbox? Sign up</i><a href="https://techcrunch.com/newsletters"> <i>here</i></a><i>.</i></p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="MIT948HhfJ"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/02/11/401k-provider-human-interest-doubles-valuation-with-55m-fundraise/">401(k) provider Human Interest doubles valuation with $55M fundraise</a></p></blockquote><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;401(k) provider Human Interest doubles valuation with $55M fundraise&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2021/02/11/401k-provider-human-interest-doubles-valuation-with-55m-fundraise/embed/#?secret=wju2UC7d0i#?secret=MIT948HhfJ" data-secret="MIT948HhfJ" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/blackrock-acquires-minority-stake-in-smb-401k-provider-human-interest/">BlackRock acquires minority stake in SMB 401(k) provider Human Interest</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/mary-ann-azevedo/">Mary Ann Azevedo</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/blackrock-acquires-minority-stake-in-smb-401k-provider-human-interest/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>5 of the best journaling apps to log your thoughts and experiences</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/5-best-journaling-apps-log-your-thoughts-and-experiences/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/5-best-journaling-apps-log-your-thoughts-and-experiences/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aisha Malik]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 21:42:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[digital-journal]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[journaling]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[journaling apps]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2470065</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As we look to the year ahead, you may be interested in creating new habits and setting goals. Journaling is a popular practice that helps you reflect on your life, while also keeping track of your goals. If you&#8217;re looking to get into journaling and would prefer to keep a digital journal instead of a [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/5-best-journaling-apps-log-your-thoughts-and-experiences/">5 of the best journaling apps to log your thoughts and experiences</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/aisha-malik/">Aisha Malik</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">As we look to the year ahead, you may be interested in creating new habits and setting goals. Journaling is a popular practice that helps you reflect on your life, while also keeping track of your goals. If you&#8217;re looking to get into journaling and would prefer to keep a digital journal instead of a physical one, you can choose from numerous journaling apps available across iPhone and Android.</p>
<p>Whether you want to store specific memories about your everyday life or reflect on your day with a few sentences before bed, there are many apps out there that are designed to help you keep track of your thoughts and experiences. We compiled a list of some of the best ones to help you pick one that’s to your liking.</p>
<h2>Day One</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2470078" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470078" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470078" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg" alt="Day One app" width="1024" height="685" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg 1832w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=300,201 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=768,514 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=680,455 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=1536,1028 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=1200,803 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/day-one-app.jpeg?resize=50,33 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470078" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Day One</p></div></p>
<p><a href="https://dayoneapp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Day One</a> is a personal journaling app that is somewhat like a freeform digital diary. The app features daily prompts to keep you on top of your goals, and includes customizable templates that help you save time when journaling. Each entry automatically tracks the time, date, weather, moon phase and more. Day One lets you bring in content from other apps, like Photos and Safari.</p>
<p>A portion of the app is designed to help users reminisce about the past. For example, there is an “On This Day” feature that allows you to revisit past memories. What makes the app unique is the ability to add tags to entries, which can make it easier to find specific entries from the past. Day One also features a map view that shows you all of the places you have journaled from.</p>
<p>The app is a good fit for people who want an open-ended journal, as opposed to a structured format. Day One is free to use, but also offers a $3 monthly subscription that unlocks premium features. The app is available on<a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/day-one-journal-private-diary/id1044867788" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.dayoneapp.dayone&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android.</a></p>
<h2>5 Minute Journal</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2470075" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470075" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470075" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg" alt="5 minute journal app" width="1024" height="633" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg 1491w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=150,93 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=300,186 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=768,475 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=680,420 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=1200,742 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/5-minute-journal-app.jpeg?resize=50,31 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470075" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> 5 Minute Journal</p></div></p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>The 5 Minute Journal app offers a guided gratitude journaling format. Each morning and evening, you receive specific prompts to reflect on your day and your goals. The goal of the app is to encourage you to reflect on your life in just five minutes, twice a day. In the morning, you may be asked to write about what you’re grateful for, and in the evening, you could be asked to write about some good things that happened that day.</p>
<p>You can set daily notifications to keep up with your journaling habit. There’s also an option to receive daily inspiring quotes that you can share to your social media accounts. In addition, you can add a photo to your posts to have a visual aspect when tracking everyday moments.</p>
<p>The app is a good fit for people who want to get into mindfulness with the help of a structured format. The 5 Minute Journal is free to use but also offers a $4.99 monthly subscription that includes additional features. The app is available on <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/5-minute-journal-self-care/id1062945251" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.intelligentchange.fiveminutejournal&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android</a>.</p>
<h2>Daylio</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2470069" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470069" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470069" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg" alt="Daylio app" width="1024" height="563" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg 1403w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=150,83 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=300,165 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=768,423 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=680,374 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=1200,660 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/daylio-app.jpeg?resize=50,28 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470069" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Daylio</p></div></p>
<p><a href="https://daylio.net/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Daylio</a> is an easy to use journaling app that helps you quickly track your daily mood and activities. The app is perfect for people who want to keep their journaling short and sweet, and don’t really want to write anything. If you do want to expand on an entry, you can add notes. You can pick the things you want to track, such as your social activities, hobbies, sleep, health, chores, food and more.</p>
<p>The app also lets you create daily, weekly or monthly goals to motivate you. You can choose from preset goals, such as drinking more water or meditating, or you can create custom goals. You can also build habits and collect achievements along the way. In addition, you can back up and restore your entries on your Google Drive.</p>
<p>Daylio is a good fit for people who want an alternative to traditional journaling apps. The app is free to use, but also offers a $2.99 monthly subscription that unlocks premium features. Daylio is available on <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/daylio-journal-goals-habits/id1194023242" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.daylio&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android.</a></p>
<h2>Momento</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2470081" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470081" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470081" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png" alt="Memento app" width="1024" height="636" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png 1520w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=150,93 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=300,186 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=768,477 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=680,422 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=1200,745 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/memento.png?resize=50,31 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470081" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Memento</p></div></p>
<p><a href="https://momentoapp.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Momento</a> is a multipurpose journal that can be used for many different things. You can use it as a personal life journal or as a work journal. There are several templates that you can choose from if you want to track specific things, such as health, food or travel. You can add photos and location tags to your journal entries to keep a detailed record of your everyday life.</p>
<p>What makes Momento unique is the ability to connect the app with your social networks to automatically import your activities, photos and videos. The app also lets you relive your memories by browsing by day, month or year. There’s also a “This Day” feature that allows you to look back on what you were doing exactly a year ago.</p>
<p>Momento is a good journaling option for people who want to capture everything about their everyday lives. The app is free to use, but also has a $2.49 monthly subscription that gives you access to more features. The app is available on <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/momento-private-journal-diary/id980592846" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iOS</a> only.</p>
<h2>DailyBean</h2>
<p><div id="attachment_2470082" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2470082" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2470082" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg" alt="DailyBean app" width="1024" height="545" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg 1751w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=150,80 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=300,160 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=768,409 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=680,362 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=1536,818 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=1200,639 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/dailybean-app.jpeg?resize=50,27 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2470082" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> DailyBean</p></div></p>
<p>DailyBean is a simple app that lets you record your everyday life with a few taps in a way that almost feels like a game. You can choose what you want to track, such as your emotions, social activities, the weather, your meals, romantic life and more. To add an entry, you start off by tracking how you felt about your day using one of five mood beans. Then you can add additional details about your emotions. For example, you can note if you felt refreshed or gloomy that day.</p>
<p>You can also track how much sleep you got that day, and there’s an option to add up to three photos to your daily entries. If you want to go beyond the simple means of tracking your day, you can add notes to your entries. The app&#8217;s calendar view also gives you an overview of how you have been feeling recently.</p>
<p>DailyBean is a good fit for people who don’t want to spend too much time journaling and want something simple. The app costs $1.99 per month after a 7-day free trial. DailyBean is available on <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/dailybean-simplest-journal/id1553223828" target="_blank" rel="noopener">iOS</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.bluesignum.bluediary&amp;hl=en_US&amp;gl=US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Android</a>.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="JUvU8bs6VI"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/30/5-best-apps-track-reading-discover-new-books/">5 of the best apps to track your reading and discover new books</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;5 of the best apps to track your reading and discover new books&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/30/5-best-apps-track-reading-discover-new-books/embed/#?secret=RLqlHp0dwf#?secret=JUvU8bs6VI" data-secret="JUvU8bs6VI" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/5-best-journaling-apps-log-your-thoughts-and-experiences/">5 of the best journaling apps to log your thoughts and experiences</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/aisha-malik/">Aisha Malik</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/5-best-journaling-apps-log-your-thoughts-and-experiences/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deconstructing &#8216;The Twitter Files&#8217;</title>
		<link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/deconstructing-the-twitter-files/</link>
					<comments>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/deconstructing-the-twitter-files/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Devin Coldewey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 20:49:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Government & Policy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Social]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elon buys twitter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Elon Musk]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Twitter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[twitter files]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://techcrunch.com/?p=2462482</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The bombast with which the so-called Twitter Files have been released is incongruous with the mundanity of their content. Even so, as the circus folds up the big top and the barkers return to their Substacks, it is worth a thorough retrospective to put these breathlessly delivered, revelation-flavored products in context. That few large news [&#8230;]</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/deconstructing-the-twitter-files/">Deconstructing &#8216;The Twitter Files&#8217;</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/devin-coldewey/">Devin Coldewey</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="speakable-summary">The bombast with which the so-called Twitter Files have been released is incongruous with the mundanity of their content. Even so, as the circus folds up the big top and the barkers return to their Substacks, it is worth a thorough retrospective to put these breathlessly delivered, revelation-flavored products in context.</p>
<p>That few large news outlets have opted to report much of the information in these threads has been attributed to complaisance, partisanship, complicity with government interference or various species of corruption. The banal truth is that, if other newsrooms are anything like our own, they read each as a matter of diligence, and simply found nothing new or interesting to report, or what little there was contaminated by the dubious circumstances of their presentation.</p>
<p>What&#8217;s important to understand at the outset — and what the authors make clear from the start — is that no one involved in the selection and analysis of the internal communications appears to have any familiarity with (let alone expertise in) how social media and tech platforms are moderated or run. This is not said in order to poison the well — it matters because this lack of familiarity is in great part the reason these stories were published to begin with, and it explains the editorial slant they are given.</p>
<p>In each Twitter Files thread, we see unfounded assumptions, insinuations and personal interpretations given equal weight as facts, more or less establishing these as opinion pieces rather than factual reporting. That alone will have spiked a great deal of coverage, as however salacious the theory, little of what is actually provided satisfies editorial standards in many a newsroom.</p>
<p>It must also be obvious by now that this ostensible act of transparency was conducted with a definite goal: to discredit the previous moderation and management teams, and advance a narrative of systematic anti-conservative activity at Twitter. This has resulted, both deliberately and by neglect of basic best practices, in harassment and targeting of individuals.</p>
<p>Plainly this is all orchestrated by Elon Musk, whose spite is equally plain in the wake of his botched purchase of the platform — an event that has been catastrophic to his wealth and reputation. But catastrophe loves company, and he seems insistent that all receive a portion of his ruin.</p>
<p>That said, given the natural curiosity of our readership on these matters, I thought it may be of interest to catalogue the claims in one place, as well as what rendered most of them unreportable, despite occasionally containing notable information.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 1: <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1598822959866683394" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Handled&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: &#8220;An incredible story&#8221; of how &#8220;connected actors&#8221; had accounts deleted and stories suppressed, with a clear left-leaning bias</em></p>
<p>The inaugural thread unambiguously and repeatedly shows working moderators grappling honestly with difficult decisions.</p>
<p>It also shows the inbox of a content moderation response team: not a dark and secret back channel but an official means for governments (the U.S. and others), individuals, companies, law enforcement and anyone else with special insight or purpose to communicate with the company&#8217;s dedicated department. There are no surreptitious &#8220;connected actors,&#8221; this is essentially customer service. The assertion that there were &#8220;more channels, more ways to complain, open to the left&#8221; is completely unsupported.</p>
<p>The question of First Amendment violations is a massive red herring, aided by Musk, who publicly aired his misinterpretation of it in the replies. As the thread notes, &#8220;there’s no evidence &#8211; that I&#8217;ve seen &#8211; of any government involvement in the laptop story.&#8221; Government requests, as documented and discussed publicly for years, are routine. Private requests, like the Biden campaign flagging non-consensually shared nude images of Hunter Biden as violations of Twitter&#8217;s terms of service, are routine.</p><div class="piano-inline-promo"></div>
<p>Here as in other threads, the source documents themselves may well be of interest, but are not reliable as presented and do not demonstrate the claims stated. And it must be recorded here how slapdash the redaction and presentation of the information was, giving a sense of carelessness and overhaste to these supposedly momentous reports.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 2: <a href="https://twitter.com/bariweiss/status/1601023770717626368/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Secret&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: &#8220;Secret blacklists&#8221; and &#8220;shadow bans&#8221; were common at Twitter</em></p>
<p>The second thread is an exercise in fear, uncertainty and doubt that depicts the tools of a functioning social media moderation team as those of a secret speech-controlling elite. Flags and moderation functions are not public by design, as some of the information is proprietary to Twitter, personally identifiable to the account, or the type of thing to be taken advantage of by malicious actors, who would redline behavior if they knew exactly how the system worked.</p>
<p>By the definition applied here, much of what goes on in <em>any</em> company is &#8220;secret.&#8221; Google, Facebook, Microsoft, Sony, Amazon — any company that maintains and monitors large numbers of users and communications has a &#8220;secret&#8221; system like this. It was nice to peek behind the curtain, which was <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/09/musks-twitter-files-offer-a-glimpse-of-the-raw-complicated-and-thankless-task-of-moderation/">why I did report it</a> in that context; I would have done the same if one of those other companies&#8217; non-public moderation practices had been exposed.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="8wvj99Bx0p"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/09/musks-twitter-files-offer-a-glimpse-of-the-raw-complicated-and-thankless-task-of-moderation/">Musk&#8217;s &#8216;Twitter Files&#8217; offer a glimpse of the raw, complicated and thankless task of moderation</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Musk&#8217;s &#8216;Twitter Files&#8217; offer a glimpse of the raw, complicated and thankless task of moderation&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2022/12/09/musks-twitter-files-offer-a-glimpse-of-the-raw-complicated-and-thankless-task-of-moderation/embed/#?secret=7uJlIX2401#?secret=8wvj99Bx0p" data-secret="8wvj99Bx0p" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>But in keeping with the intended narrative, the thread only shows examples of moderation actions that affect a handful of conservative fringe accounts. We can&#8217;t know if and how these tools were used in other circumstances, such as putting a left-leaning account on a &#8220;trends blacklist,&#8221; because that data is withheld — &#8220;secret,&#8221; as Weiss would no doubt put it. It would be irresponsible to draw conclusions based on such purposefully manipulated data.</p>
<p>The thread also does a bit of prestidigitation in the matter of &#8220;shadow banning,&#8221; which Twitter publicly denies doing according to its own, also public definition. Weiss redefines the term as something Twitter <em>does</em> do (industry-standard moderation practices) and concludes that the company has lied retroactively. The disingenuous presentation discourages coverage.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 3: <a href="https://twitter.com/bariweiss/status/1602364197194432515" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Interaction&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: &#8220;Decisions by high-ranking executives to violate their own policies&#8221; in the ban of Donald Trump, and &#8220;<span class="css-901oao css-16my406 r-poiln3 r-bcqeeo r-qvutc0">ongoing, documented interaction with federal agencies</span>&#8220;</em></p>
<p>The deliberations of a social media moderation team put in the unprecedented situation of deciding whether and how to suspend a sitting president&#8217;s account (and how to adjust policies going forward) are interesting in a fundamental way; however, the way this information is presented is again too suspect for any reporter to trust and report. With no access to the original chat logs, it is impossible to say whether the conversations here are accurately represented or, as is far more likely given how the narrative in which they are couched, selectively shown (though in fairness, the process by which these logs were given to the authors is not entirely in their control). What little we are privy to is not particularly notable.</p>
<p>The &#8220;interaction&#8221; with federal agencies is also given a FUD treatment. As noted above, law enforcement and governments are of necessity in constant contact with every social media company — indeed, with all of tech and much of commerce and industry in general. It really is part of their job, and yes, there are agents and specialists designated for social media and tech duty, just as there are some detailed to shipping, manufacturing, finance, etc. Whatever one&#8217;s opinion on this practice (and let me just say, I am no bootlicker myself), it surely isn&#8217;t news. The attempt to transmute these &#8220;interactions&#8221; into &#8220;intimidation&#8221; or &#8220;obligation&#8221; is not successful.</p>
<p>A presidential election following several marked by attempts (successful or not) at interference by foreign adversaries is of natural interest to the FBI, among other authorities, and a weekly check-in seems the bare minimum to keep each other informed of potential influence campaigns, trends in cybersecurity, relevant intelligence and so on. Let us not forget that Twitter amounts to essential communications infrastructure for every government agency at this point; monitoring it is an important but quite ordinary matter. It would be far more surprising and worth investigating if this contact <em>didn&#8217;t</em> exist.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 4: <a href="https://twitter.com/ShellenbergerMD/status/1601720455005511680" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Policy&#8221;</a><br />
</strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: Twitter changes its policies in order to ban Trump, and &#8220;expresses <span class="css-901oao css-16my406 r-poiln3 r-bcqeeo r-qvutc0">no concern for the free speech or democracy implications</span>&#8220;</em></p>
<p>The discussion documented here is only partial, but it seems to show, as before, the team grappling with evolving circumstances and figuring out in real time how the company should respond. In one quoted chat message, former head of trust and safety Yoel Roth puts it quite clearly: &#8220;Policy is one part of the system of how Twitter works&#8230; we ran into the world changing faster than we were able to either adapt the product or the policy.&#8221;</p>
<p>As a private company running its own fast-moving social platform, obviously Twitter changes its policies regularly, and also makes exceptions to them at its discretion; in fact had made them before in favor of Trump. This was a notable exception, of course, but also the result of extensive internal discussion — which acknowledges both the ad hoc nature of the actions and policies, and their gravity as well. It seems strange for this thread to say no discussion was had when one is clearly shown here and in the next thread. (Perhaps it&#8217;s a matter of opinion what &#8220;expressing concern&#8221; looks like.)</p>
<p>All of this was also widely, <em>widely</em> discussed and reported by pretty much everyone in the world at the time.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="igX3IuaiTe"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/01/08/why-twitter-banned-president-trump/">Why Twitter says it banned President Trump</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Why Twitter says it banned President Trump&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2021/01/08/why-twitter-banned-president-trump/embed/#?secret=TSaTgoZAam#?secret=igX3IuaiTe" data-secret="igX3IuaiTe" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<h3><strong>Part 5: <a href="https://twitter.com/bariweiss/status/1602364197194432515" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Unprecedented&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: Twitter&#8217;s choice to ban Trump goes against previous decisions and is part of a pattern of politically biased censorship</em></p>
<p>Again, reading the actual discussions of dozens of people throughout the company — not &#8220;a handful&#8221; as it is characterized — in an unprecedented situation is <em>interesting</em>, but difficult to report on given the lack of context and editorialized presentation. These internal debates are more or less what anyone would expect, and hope, of a company trying to figure out how to handle this.</p>
<p>The chat logs do offer a note of specificity long after the fact, but the (by this point obligatory) attempt to cast it as an elite group making directed choices to &#8220;influence the public discourse and democracy&#8221; is again unsupported, and also contradictory with the notion, elsewhere advanced, that this group was being controlled by the FBI and other government agencies.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 6: <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1603857534737072128" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Subsidiary&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: The FBI has infiltrated Twitter and exerts &#8220;constant and pervasive&#8221; influence</em></p>
<p>&#8220;The #TwitterFiles show something new: agencies like the FBI and DHS regularly sending social media content to Twitter through multiple entry points, pre-flagged for moderation.&#8221;</p>
<p>It may be new to some, but as noted above, this is quite an ordinary and well-documented practice: for law enforcement, and political parties, and government agencies, and private companies, etc., to call content or accounts to the attention of a platform&#8217;s moderation team. It has been done for a long time, and in fact much of it is publicly declared by major tech companies in their <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/08/19/twitter-claims-increased-enforcement-of-hate-speech-and-abuse-policies-in-last-half-of-2019/">regular Transparency Reports</a>, which list government requests and orders, what they pertained to and how many resulted in some kind of action, or provoked a challenge or request for a warrant. Notably the thread actually shows this kind of pushback happening.</p>
<p>This type of form email can be found in every platform&#8217;s moderation team inbox. Incidentally, the description of so prosaic a greeting as &#8220;Hello Twitter Contacts, FBI San Francisco is notifying you of the below accounts&#8230;&#8221; as having a &#8220;master-canine quality&#8221; is a real puzzler. I&#8217;m genuinely unsure who is meant to be the master and who the canine.</p>
<p>There is of course room for debate on how much the government (among other entities) can or should request, legally, procedurally and ethically speaking. As is the revolving door of high-level corporate and lobbyist positions and government officials. Fortunately for us, just such a debate has been ongoing for two decades. It surely must have bemused many reporters in this space that a topic discussed so widely and for so long is being treated as new or controversial.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 7: <a href="https://twitter.com/ShellenbergerMD/status/1604871630613753856" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Discredited&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: A conspiracy orchestrated by the FBI and intelligence community to preemptively discredit the Hunter Biden laptop story</em></p>
<p>Even if anyone at any newsroom thought it was worth re-(re-)litigating the laptop story, which was discussed <em>ad nauseam</em> at the time, the way information is presented in this thread is dangerously disingenuous.</p>
<p>The sleight of hand occurs in drawing connections between things with no actual connection — conspiracy theory &#8220;logic.&#8221; For instance, two facts: One, the FBI was aware of the laptop, and had collected it; two, the FBI sent some documents to Twitter just before the NY Post published its story. These are presented as if clearly linked.</p>
<p>But as the other threads made clear, these FBI document drops were quite a regular occurrence, as often as weekly (in fact later threads complain information was shared <em>too</em> frequently). And there is no evidence the FBI considered the laptop a specific &#8220;hack-and-leak&#8221; threat, let alone expressed that to parties like Twitter (the general be-on-lookout months earlier is weak tea). Not only is the significance of either fact unsupported individually, but they are connected in the thread in an unsupported way.</p>
<p>This type of suggestive free association occurs repeatedly. And magically, an elaborate &#8220;influence operation&#8221; uniting the FBI, IC, a think tank, and a few other villains is assembled, like a corkboard with pins and yarn criss-crossing it. (Never mind that subsequent threads show they could barely organize a cross-agency conference call.) Under even the slightest scrutiny this vast conspiracy evaporates, and what is left is clearly a loose collection of people talking about potential cyberthreats in a tense election season.</p>
<p>Few newsrooms would approve of presenting such feats of conjecture as fact, if any reporter even considered using such flimflam as the basis of their own article.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 8: <a href="https://twitter.com/lhfang/status/1605292454261182464" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Covert&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: Twitter &#8220;directly assisted the U.S. military&#8217;s influence operations&#8221;</em></p>
<p>This claim is actually true — or was. We clocked the roll-up of this U.S. influence operation <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/25/meta-and-twitter-graphika-us-influence-campaign/">back in August</a>, but this was still a thread that we read with interest.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="lDRVC2O8x8"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/25/meta-and-twitter-graphika-us-influence-campaign/">Meta and Twitter purge web of accounts spreading pro-US propaganda abroad</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Meta and Twitter purge web of accounts spreading pro-US propaganda abroad&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2022/08/25/meta-and-twitter-graphika-us-influence-campaign/embed/#?secret=HUYL8zLCPH#?secret=lDRVC2O8x8" data-secret="lDRVC2O8x8" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>Every government performs propaganda operations here and there, with various degrees of success and secrecy (both low in this case); it&#8217;s table stakes in intelligence. We see networks of fake accounts <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/09/27/meta-disinformation-china-russia-us-midterms-ukraine/">rolled up frequently</a>, though understandably the ones that are given the most press are foreign operations intending to influence U.S. discourse; these grew so numerous that Facebook started <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/10/26/facebook-finds-more-disinformation-linked-to-iran/">bundling them into roundups</a> and we left off covering all but the most notable, since they were clearly rationing them for positive news cycles.</p>
<p>In this case, an ask was made to give a number of officially military-associated propaganda accounts slightly privileged status (immunity from spam reports, for instance). Twitter agreed, but later the military removed the association disclosure from the accounts, rendering them &#8220;covert,&#8221; though possibly the word overstates the case. This angered Twitter, but either they felt they could not renege on their deal with the Pentagon, or, given how small and ineffective these accounts clearly were, decided it didn&#8217;t really matter much one way or the other. (In retrospect, given the bad PR, they probably wish they had hammered it. But hindsight is 20/20, as most of the Twitter Files demonstrate.)</p>
<p>To observe a U.S. operation to influence discourse abroad is interesting, and it does (and did) prompt legitimate questions of how closely tech companies should work with the Defense Department and intelligence community. Ultimately we felt that peeling back this layer of the onion was laudable but further coverage on our part was superfluous.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 9: <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1606701397109796866" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Doorman&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: The FBI was the funnel for a &#8220;<span class="css-901oao css-16my406 r-poiln3 r-bcqeeo r-qvutc0">vast program of social media surveillance and censorship</span>&#8221; across government agencies</em></p>
<p>Here we see the government&#8217;s haphazard approach to communicating with tech, with multiple agencies and cross-agency task forces overdoing it in various ways (primarily too much email). The number of accounts being flagged by law enforcement and government was already high and rising; Twitter complained and worked hard to triage and prioritize as government requests competed with press, user flags and others for limited moderation attention.</p>
<p>It can&#8217;t be that surprising that the government would be overzealous in its efforts to tamp down on misinformation after years of asserting and soliciting opinions on how it might affect elections. Thousands of reports sounds like a lot, but count the number of police departments, state elections authorities, federal task forces and so on, then imagine each of them finding a handful of problematic accounts or tweets each day. They add up quite quickly; it&#8217;s a big (and troubled) country, and there&#8217;s only one Twitter. Other platforms were experiencing similar overloads and government communications.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="DMTq1tvzXl"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/08/13/twitter-pledges-to-dial-up-efforts-to-combat-election-misinformation/">Twitter pledges to dial up efforts to combat election misinformation</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Twitter pledges to dial up efforts to combat election misinformation&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2020/08/13/twitter-pledges-to-dial-up-efforts-to-combat-election-misinformation/embed/#?secret=AsLFfTdUiF#?secret=DMTq1tvzXl" data-secret="DMTq1tvzXl" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>That these requests were channeled through two primary channels, the FBI San Francisco office and the Foreign Influence Task Force, for flagging domestic and international issues respectively, is presented as ominous but feels simply practical. The alternative, hundreds of sources independently contacting Twitter, is infeasible.</p>
<p>Even if we were to credit some of the accusations, it&#8217;s hard to draw conclusions because the context (beyond even &#8220;the year 2020&#8221;) is exceptional. The period before and after the 2020 election was <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/08/13/twitter-pledges-to-dial-up-efforts-to-combat-election-misinformation/">absolutely rife with misinformation</a> and other social media issues. Meanwhile every government agency even tangentially related to elections was likewise overwhelmed and working overtime. It&#8217;s not clear what is meant to be shown beyond an admittedly bloated bureaucracy in action.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 10: <a href="https://twitter.com/davidzweig/status/1607378386338340867" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Rigged&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: &#8220;Twitter rigged the COVID debate&#8221; by &#8220;censoring,&#8221; &#8220;discrediting&#8221; and &#8220;suppressing&#8221; information and users according to government preferences</em></p>
<p>The words used above — rig, censor, discredit, suppress — are strong. But they are not accurate, and the author, apparently a professional quibbler, applies a sort of malicious hindsight to a handful of borderline cases.</p>
<p>The allegation here is that Twitter&#8217;s moderation team chose to use CDC recommendations as the basis for its COVID-related misinformation policy. This is neither new nor controversial, and not really even a sensible complaint. It is the role of that agency to study, justify, document, and promulgate best practices in health emergencies. What other authority should Twitter have sought for such a policy? None is suggested. Indeed no realistic alternative exists. It was a public health and misinformation emergency and clear lines needed to be drawn — fast, and rooted in some kind of authority — in order that moderation could occur at all. Twitter used the CDC in its capacity as expert agency in drawing some of those lines.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="fRQGgE5Vtw"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/03/18/twitter-coronavirus-covid-19-misinformation-policy/">Twitter broadly bans any COVID-19 tweets that could help the virus spread</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Twitter broadly bans any COVID-19 tweets that could help the virus spread&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2020/03/18/twitter-coronavirus-covid-19-misinformation-policy/embed/#?secret=FJ7lzb5hsb#?secret=fRQGgE5Vtw" data-secret="fRQGgE5Vtw" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>It is stated in the thread categorically that &#8220;information that challenged that view&#8230; was subject to moderation, and even suppression.&#8221; Sure, sometimes. And sometimes things that should have been removed weren&#8217;t. Moderation is messy and 2020 was messiness epitomized. Mistakes were inevitable, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/03/18/twitter-coronavirus-covid-19-misinformation-policy/">as Twitter made clear at the outset</a>; it&#8217;s trivial to go back and find a few among the decisions in their millions. It&#8217;s also pointless and subjective, and feels a bit spiteful.</p>
<p>All the thread offers is a &#8220;what if&#8221; the bar for debate had been moved an arbitrary amount in the direction the author prefers. But it conflates that notion with the idea that, because the bar was not placed correctly in his opinion (one of his quibbles is with masks, it seems germane to note here), that open debate was &#8220;censored.&#8221; We have seen censorship and this is not it.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 11: <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1610394197730725889" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Workload&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: Federal agencies leveraged and then overwhelmed channels for reporting accounts</em></p>
<p>This thread was, like the earlier one, interesting in that the documents quoted show exactly the kind of improvised, scattershot approach expected by a disorganized government in response to the growing disinfo and state-sponsored digital influence ecosystem.</p>
<p>Twitter gave them the same inch they gave everyone else — a line to the moderation team — but the feds took a mile, and then weren&#8217;t sure what to do with it. The result was more noise and less signal, until Twitter had to tell them to get their act together and decide on a few reliable points of contact (our scary &#8220;funnels&#8221; from earlier) and documentation methods. It&#8217;s always grimly entertaining to see the government flail like this, but such logistical squabbles don&#8217;t seem worth reporting. Keep in mind this was also in the spring and summer of 2020, when all hell was breaking loose in pretty much every way.</p>
<p>As for the repeated assertion that Twitter was paid off by the feds, those are statutorily required consultation fees the FBI <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2022/12/20/no-the-fbi-is-not-paying-twitter-to-censor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">incurred through its requests for investigation</a> (Mike Masnick&#8217;s reluctant reality checks on this and other contentions have been invaluable).</p>
<p>One note on the &#8220;narrative&#8221; side: The thread notes an &#8220;astonishing variety of requests&#8221; for account suspensions from officials. But only one is actually cited: Democratic Senator Adam Schiff&#8217;s office &#8220;asks Twitter to ban journalist Paul Sperry.&#8221; The request (denied) is, if you read it, actually flagging &#8220;many&#8221; accounts harassing a staffer (whose name is imperfectly redacted) and pushing QAnon conspiracy theories. Of the two named, one was already being suspended and the other was shortly after for other reasons. The choice and framing of this single example is telling. I would have liked to hear more of this &#8220;astonishing variety.&#8221;</p>
<h3><strong>Part 12: <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1610372352872783872" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Russian&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: The intelligence community infiltrated Twitter&#8217;s moderation process after politicians perceived the company&#8217;s response to alleged Russian bot networks as inadequate</em></p>
<p>In this first place, this all happened a long time ago, and is mostly just internal emails about some news cycles where politicians were saying Twitter hadn&#8217;t done enough to prevent Russian election interference. It&#8217;s not really clear what story all these snippets are meant to tell.</p>
<p>Second, I remember writing about this back in 2018, and the thread is pretty misleading. Although the thread quotes estimates of accounts found from two to a couple dozen, their investigation as summarized <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/official/en_us/topics/company/2018/2016-election-update.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a> puts the number <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/01/19/twitter-updates-total-of-russia-linked-election-bots-to-50000/">closer to 50,000</a>.</p>
<div class="embed breakout">
<blockquote class="wp-embedded-content" data-secret="XXFvDLIAtw"><p><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/01/19/twitter-updates-total-of-russia-linked-election-bots-to-50000/">Twitter updates total of Russia-linked election bots to 50,000</a></p></blockquote>
<p><iframe class="wp-embedded-content" sandbox="allow-scripts" security="restricted" title="&#8220;Twitter updates total of Russia-linked election bots to 50,000&#8221; &#8212; TechCrunch" src="https://techcrunch.com/2018/01/19/twitter-updates-total-of-russia-linked-election-bots-to-50000/embed/#?secret=R906QpRaLP#?secret=XXFvDLIAtw" data-secret="XXFvDLIAtw" width="800" height="450" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no"></iframe></div>
<p>He also says these searches were &#8220;based on the same data that later inspired panic headlines,&#8221; for instance <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/10/30/russian-backed-content-may-have-reached-126-million-on-facebook/">mine</a>. But that&#8217;s not true. Facebook was reporting impressions from 80,000 posts placed by suspected Russian disinformation accounts. Twitter was looking independently for such activity in its own data.</p>
<p>Conflating them isn&#8217;t just wrong, it&#8217;s misleading and kind of weird. Again, it&#8217;s not really clear what&#8217;s being claimed here, and really important context and events are excluded from the account.</p>
<p>Last, and least supported, was the big claim that Twitter &#8220;let the &#8216;USIC&#8217; into its moderation process.&#8221; As noted above many times, government entities were already in the process, making requests on a regular basis as they have for a long time and on every platform. The change flagged here is that &#8220;any user identified by the U.S. intelligence community as a state-sponsored entity conducting cyber operations against targets associated with U.S. or other elections&#8221; can&#8217;t buy ads. Considering the fallout from Twitter and Facebook taking money from accounts later linked to state-sponsored propaganda, this seems&#8230; smart. Open to abuse by the government, sure, but it&#8217;s hardly unique in that respect.</p>
<h3><strong>Part 13: <a href="https://twitter.com/AlexBerenson/status/1612526697038897167" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;Jabs&#8221;</a></strong></h3>
<p><em><strong>Claim</strong>: Pfizer board member and former FDA commissioner colluded with Twitter to silence COVID vaccine skeptics and bolster profits</em></p>
<p>This thread seems to concern a &#8220;misleading&#8221; label on a single tweet by one guy who claimed &#8220;there&#8217;s no science justification for #vax proof if a person has prior infection.&#8221; Scott Gottlieb, formerly FDA head and now on the Pfizer board, flagged the tweet to a third party (another of those funnels), who flagged it to Twitter, which evaluated it and labeled it. A second tweet sent the same way was not actioned.</p>
<p>Neither the scale nor the nature of these events are notable.</p>
<p>It must also be mentioned that this thread is authored by Alex Berenson, whom The Atlantic gave the dubious distinction of being <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2021/04/pandemics-wrongest-man/618475/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">&#8220;The Pandemic&#8217;s Wrongest Man.&#8221;</a> Berenson, losing no time in joining the other authors in this golden opportunity to plug a freshly minted newsletter, says he too is a target: &#8220;Gottlieb’s action was part of a larger conspiracy that included the Biden White House and Andrew Slavitt, working publicly and privately to pressure Twitter until it had no choice but to ban me. I will have more to say about my own case and will be suing the White House, Slavitt, Gottlieb, and Pfizer shortly.&#8221;</p>
<p>This, I think, speaks for itself.</p>
<p><strong>Part Etc&#8230;</strong></p>
<p>Further installments in the series may appear (indeed one <a href="https://twitter.com/mtaibbi/status/1613589031773769739" target="_blank" rel="noopener">did</a>, on &#8220;The Russiagate Lies,&#8221; while I was editing this piece), and like the above they will be covered on their merits. But let the above also serve as a counterweight to allegations that the press was predisposed to dismiss the Twitter Files outright. Though skepticism is a necessary characteristic of the trade, new information like that forming the core of these threads is always welcomed.</p>
<p>But the promise of the project has largely been squandered by the way that new information has been selectively and purposefully presented. Furthermore, the delta between the claims and the evidence for those claims has only widened as Musk has ventured increasingly far afield for willing participants.</p>
<p>In the past such sensitive data dumps have been collaborated on by multiple outlets and legal experts, who examine, redact, investigate and ultimately publish the files themselves. Many journalists, including those of us at TechCrunch, would have valued the opportunity to pore over the data to see how it confirms, contradicts or expands any of the claims above or stories already reported. Until that happens, honest skepticism and concern over amplifying misinformation or a billionaire&#8217;s vendetta take precedence over repeating the unsupported and, frankly, increasingly outlandish theories given the Musk seal of approval.</p>
<p>But even his imprimatur is fleeting. In a tweet promoting Berenson&#8217;s thread, Elon Musk wrote: &#8220;Some conspiracies are actually true.&#8221;</p>
<p><div id="attachment_2468741" style="width: 1034px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2468741" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="breakout size-full wp-image-2468741" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png" alt="" width="1024" height="514" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png 1287w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=150,75 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=300,151 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=768,385 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=680,341 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=1200,602 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/screen_shot_2023-01-11_at_11.01.05_am.png?resize=50,25 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><p id="caption-attachment-2468741" class="wp-caption-text"><strong>Image Credits:</strong> TechCrunch / Twitter</p></div></p>
<p>And some aren&#8217;t. He deleted the tweet soon after.</p>
<p><a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/deconstructing-the-twitter-files/">Deconstructing &#8216;The Twitter Files&#8217;</a> by <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/devin-coldewey/">Devin Coldewey</a> originally published on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://techcrunch.com">TechCrunch</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://techcrunch.com/2023/01/13/deconstructing-the-twitter-files/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
