<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>WildLIFE</title>
	<atom:link href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife</link>
	<description>Any student. Any species.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 21:39:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>http://blogs.cornell.edu/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>You Better Belize It</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/11/09/you-better-belize-it/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Maison Scheuer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 21:27:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[belize]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[belize zoo]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Cornell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[jaguar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[one health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[planetary health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ZAWS]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2431</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<img src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo.png">
Maison Scheuer ('2025) and classmates share how their dreams came true as students enrolled in Dr. Noha Abou-Madi's International Experience in Wildlife Health and Conservation course at Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine.   <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/11/09/you-better-belize-it/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" class=" wp-image-2432 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-300x228.png" alt="" width="395" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-300x228.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-1024x777.png 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-768x583.png 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-198x150.png 198w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-150x114.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo-1050x797.png 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Group-Photo.png 1429w" sizes="(max-width: 395px) 100vw, 395px" />There was once a time in my life when I could only dream about performing a physical exam on a sedated jaguar in the Belizean jungle, but that dream, along with many others, became a reality as a student enrolled in Dr. Noha Abou-Madi’s International Experience in Wildlife Health and Conservation course. Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine (CUCVM) has been partnered with the Belize Zoo since 2011 to provide state-of-the-art veterinary care while simultaneously fulfilling the dreams of adventurous veterinary students looking to hone their clinical skills. After having to cancel this trip multiple times throughout the COVID-19 pandemic, Dr. Noha Abou-Madi could not be more excited to offer this course once again to those with career goals involving wildlife and zoological medicine. In this course, students travel to the Belize Zoo where they stay for a week to gain hands-on experience with various mammals, birds, and reptiles native to Belize.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2433 alignright" style="font-size: 12px;" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-300x224.png" alt="" width="399" height="298" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-300x224.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-1024x763.png 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-768x572.png 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-1536x1145.png 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-201x150.png 201w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-150x112.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo-1050x782.png 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Sophie-Photo.png 1558w" sizes="(max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" /></p>
<p>International Experience in Wildlife Health and Conservation provides students with opportunities that go beyond the core curriculum, offering depth and breadth of knowledge in zoological and conservation medicine. Previous student Sophie Yasuda ‘25 stated, “one of my favorite parts of the trip was being able to participate in every aspect of the animals’ veterinary care and learn about each component from knowledgeable veterinarians. Being able to conduct physical exams, monitor anesthesia, observe dental procedures, collect samples, and run lab work on species as majestic and diverse as jaguars and harpy eagles was an incredible experience. In addition, it was a valuable learning experience to work in an unfamiliar hospital and extremely rewarding to feel our group turn into a cohesive and close-knit team.”</p>
<p>After working with an otter, kinkajou, and fer-de-lance, Erin Guntrum ‘25 recalls that her most memorable experience of the trip was auscultating the heart of one of the jaguars. She thought that the heart sounds were abnormal, but she was unable to figure out exactly what was abnormal about them &#8211; a murmur, an extra heart sound, an abnormal rhythm, etc. She worked closely with Veterinary Resident of Zoological Medicine Dr. Melissa Hanson to discover a split S2 sound &#8211; something that Dr. Hanson explained can be a normal finding in a larger animal where the aortic and pulmonic valves do not always close with perfect synchronicity. This was a memorable experience for Erin because despite not being able to identify the exact heart sound, she was able to recognize a difference between the heart sounds she heard in the jaguar and the ones she has been taught in CUCVM’s core curriculum. As a student developing her clinical skills, this felt like a win to Erin, and I agree!</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2434 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Erin-Photo-225x300.png" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Erin-Photo-225x300.png 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Erin-Photo-113x150.png 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Erin-Photo.png 702w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" />The relationship between the Belize Zoo and CUCVM is one that not only fosters students’ education and clinical skills as they pertain to zoological medicine, but also as they pertain to conservation. The Belize Zoo is highly committed to the animals within their direct care, but they also care for those that live beyond their gates. Erin Guntrum ‘25 recalls a lecture that we received highlighting the integral role that zoos play in the realm of conservation in which we learned that the Belize zoo has been purchasing land to be utilized as wildlife corridors to once again connect wild populations that have been separated by human establishments. Members of the Belize zoo are very aware that the human population is expanding and so too is development, nonetheless they are trying their best to ensure that land exists for wildlife in the future.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2435 alignright" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me-244x300.jpg" alt="" width="273" height="336" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me-244x300.jpg 244w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me-833x1024.jpg 833w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me-768x944.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me-122x150.jpg 122w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Me.jpg 972w" sizes="(max-width: 273px) 100vw, 273px" /></p>
<p>The Belize Zoo’s conservation efforts were very motivating for some, including Sophie Yasuda ‘25 who stated, “my decision to apply to the course stemmed from my desire to contribute to the preservation of wild populations through a career as a wildlife veterinarian. During my time at the Belize Zoo, I was inspired not only by the quality of veterinary care provided by Cornell’s doctors, but also by the amazing care provided by the keepers at the zoo and the impact the zoo has on improving public perception of native wildlife. Overall, the experience strengthened my desire to use my veterinary degree to contribute to wildlife conservation.” Emma Fralin ‘25 was also very encouraged by the zoo’s conservation efforts and is certain that visitors receive the same inspiration. She states, “the care that the animal keeper’s exemplified for their animals was practically palpable. I am confident that this care and respect translates to every visitor of the Belize Zoo.”</p>
<p>International Experience in Wildlife Health and Conservation is a course unlike any other, offering an experience of a lifetime. From monitoring the anesthesia of a spider monkey to drawing blood from a white-tailed deer in the field, you really get to do it all. This trip is a must for those seeking a well-rounded veterinary education in zoological, wildlife, or conservation medicine. I think Erin Guntrum ‘25 truly encapsulates how we all felt after our experience at the Belize Zoo when she said, “I’ve always dreamed of being a zoo or wildlife veterinarian. And this trip was so special because it was really the first time that I got to live out that dream &#8211; and it really affirmed that this is what I want to do, and that this is something I can do.”</p>
<hr />
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2436 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo-300x279.png" alt="" width="300" height="279" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo-300x279.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo-768x714.png 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo-161x150.png 161w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo-150x139.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/11/Bio-Photo.png 994w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>Maison Scheuer is the 2022-2023 WildLIFE Blog Editor and a proud member of Cornell ZAWS. Her<span class="TextRun Highlight SCXW12472497 BCX8" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US" data-contrast="auto"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8"> passions lie at the intersection of veterinary medicine and wildlife conservation.</span> She<span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8"> loves to travel and has spent time in</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8"> Canada, Thailand, Alabama, Belize, and Honduras where she</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8"> studied Columbian ground squirrels, elephant conservation, wildlife rehabilitation, and veterinary medicine.</span></span> Though <span class="TextRun Highlight SCXW12472497 BCX8" lang="EN-US" xml:lang="EN-US" data-contrast="auto"><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">particularly interested in One Health and </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">i</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">nternational </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">m</span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">edicine, she has also discovered a love for small animal medicine through her experience </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">working </span><span class="NormalTextRun SCXW12472497 BCX8">as a veterinary technician at a full-service exotics and small animal private practice.</span></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guidance from Graduates: Dr. Ben Jakobek (DVM ‘20)</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/09/26/guidance-from-graduates-dr-ben-jakobek-dvm-20/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colleen Sorge]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 21:25:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[advice]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[caribou]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[guidance from graduates]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rhinos]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2417</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<img src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1.jpg"> 
Dr. Ben Jakobek (DVM '20) shares impactful wildlife experiences that will inspire others to protect our beautiful planet.  <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/09/26/guidance-from-graduates-dr-ben-jakobek-dvm-20/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2421 alignright" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-224x300.jpg" alt="" width="224" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-224x300.jpg 224w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-764x1024.jpg 764w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-768x1030.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-1146x1536.jpg 1146w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-112x150.jpg 112w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1-1050x1408.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek1.jpg 1432w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" />If Dr. Benjamin Jakobek decides to write a book, I will be first in line to buy it. As he tells me about some of the projects he’s been a part of, including capturing and collaring muskox in Nunavik and working to transport caribou to a protected environment, he is a reminder to all of us aspiring veterinarians that we will one day have the capability and arguably, the responsibility, to help protect wild animals and places around the world. After obtaining his DVM from Cornell University College of Veterinary Medicine in 2020,  Dr. Jakobek completed a one-year small animal rotating internship at the University of Prince Edward Island. Now, he is a zoological medicine resident and a master’s student at the University of Montréal focusing on free-ranging wildlife health management. Though each day’s work is different, Dr. Jakobek divides the bulk of his time between the Granby Zoo, the Aquarium of Québec, the University of Montréal’s wildlife pathology service and raptor clinic, as well as federal and provincial wildlife agencies. His current program gives him the opportunity to hone his research and his clinical skills into something he calls “the opportunity of a lifetime.” This program has allowed him to work on research projects ranging from studying toxoplasmosis in endangered beluga whales to environmental interventions against Lyme disease, among many others.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2423 alignleft" style="font-size: 16px;" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-300x144.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="144" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-300x144.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-1024x491.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-768x368.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-250x120.jpg 250w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-150x72.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1-1050x504.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek-1.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>Though Dr. Jakobek knew throughout his vet school years that he hoped to work in conservation medicine, his experiences during his time as a student were varied. “One of the things I love about veterinary medicine is there’s so much to learn. I took on everything that I could that interested me. I got involved in projects where I felt like I could bring something useful to the table, even if it was just my time and my passion.” Thankfully, opportunities abound. “As a vet student it’s not hard to find really cool projects. In fact, I think at Cornell specifically there’s truly an abundance of unique opportunities.” His summer in Indonesia with Dr. Robin Radcliffe’s rhino conservation program was an impactful experience. “That reaffirmed for me the fact that I wanted to do wildlife conservation work and also be working internationally as much as possible.” From there, Dr. Jakobek continued to chase down experiences that excited him, including externships with the provincial and state wildlife departments of British Columbia and Alaska and with White Oak Conservation Center in Florida. Dr. Jakobek emphasizes pursuing a path that interests you rather than taking steps only because they feel like what you’re supposed to do. “I think that it comes down to what you make out of whichever experience you end up having.” This attitude also extended to the rotations he completed at Cornell during his clinical year. To work with exotic and wildlife species, he says, it helps to have as strong of a background you can have in “just about everything.”</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2419 alignright" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek3-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek3-300x225.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek3-200x150.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek3-150x113.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek3.jpg 756w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">According to Dr. Jakobek, his time at Cornell influenced more than just his clinical skills. “Cornell inspired me to see the incredible things that can be achieved through thoughtful research. At Cornell, I gained a lot from just talking to people. I had the opportunity to have conversations with professors there, who are people that have had an immense positive impact on our world. My connections with people at Cornell didn’t necessarily stop after I finished my studies, and my experiences there have served as a foundation for my learning and development. I strive to continue to adhere to the professional and academic excellence that I think Cornell encourages.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2420 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-200x300.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-200x300.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-100x150.jpg 100w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4-1050x1575.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jacobek4.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" />Looking towards his future, Dr. Jakobek remains interested in both clinical medicine and research. He is particularly drawn to work in more remote areas of the world. “I think this appeals to me because it’s in those remote places that you find rich biodiversity and natural habitats often needing research and support for their protection.” Another highlight of his residency has been working alongside different community stakeholders to conserve habitats and safeguard wild species. He describes a particularly impactful experience transporting caribou alongside wildlife biologists, indigenous peoples, wildlife technicians, and veterinarians, all of whom wanted to ensure the survival of this particular caribou population, of which there were only seventeen individuals remaining. Of course, while his experiences during his residency have been rewarding, he is also frequently reminded of the progress still to be made. “This work [with caribou] shows how important it is to protect wildlife habitats while we still have them and value wildlife, while we have the great fortune to be able to share the planet with them.”</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2422 size-medium alignright" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-169x300.jpg" alt="" width="169" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-169x300.jpg 169w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-576x1024.jpg 576w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-768x1365.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-864x1536.jpg 864w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-84x150.jpg 84w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984-1050x1867.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/09/Jakobek4-e1664223981984.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 169px) 100vw, 169px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When asked to share some advice with current students, Dr. Jakobek was quick to emphasize our </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">value as individuals even as we may feel compelled to devote all of our time and energy to our veterinary</span> studies. “I would tell students not to undervalue the other things that make you who you are outside of being a vet student. Of course academic success and veterinary knowledge are crucial components of your career as a veterinarian, but I’ve found that people’s interest in me often is in some of the things that I thought were a very small part of me.” In Dr. Jakobek’s case, this includes interests in aviation, film, media, and a knack for languages. Another inestimable component of success is the ability to work well with others. “If you’re somebody that people enjoy being around, that’s not something you should take for granted. Being an honest, sociable, likable person goes a very long way, especially since wildlife medicine and conservation is often just as much about people as it is about animals.” Naturally, the field being so small means that it is also quite competitive, something Dr. Jakobek is well aware of. “You probably won’t get every opportunity that you try for. When you don’t get those opportunities it’s less likely that it was because of you, and not just a result of this field’s competitive nature. But, at the end of the day, if you know that you want to work in wildlife conservation, you know what tools you’re going to need to be effective, and you’re ready to learn and you’re ready to put yourself out there, then you finally will get the opportunity of a lifetime. And it’s hard to believe but those opportunities will then just keep coming.” Asked for some parting advice, Dr. Jakobek’s words are motivational: “I’ll tell you that when you finally get the opportunities you’ve been waiting for, make the absolute most of them and remember how important your work is for our beautiful planet.”</p>
<hr />
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2394 alignleft" style="font-size: 12px;" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="271" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-166x150.jpg 166w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-150x136.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" />Colleen Sorge, Class of 2024, is a Cornell DVM student from Long Island, NY. She obtained her undergraduate degree in Animal Science from Cornell University in 2020. She has a wide range of interests within the veterinary field, including both small animal and wildlife medicine.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guidance from Graduates: Dr. Zachary Dvornicky-Raymond (BS &#8217;15, DVM &#8217;19)</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/04/12/guidance-from-graduates-dr-z/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colleen Sorge]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2022 13:00:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[alumni]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife health]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Recent graduate Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond (BS '15 DVM'19) discusses his path in the world of conservation medicine.  <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/04/12/guidance-from-graduates-dr-z/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For Dr. Zachary Dvornicky-Raymond, a career in conservation may have been an inevitability. An animal lover for as long as he can remember, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond recalls watching the Discovery Channel and Animal Planet as a child and idolizing Steve Irwin. “As I grew up and was attending zoos and learning more about the world, I came to realize that all of the animals that I loved and was so interested in were disappearing. So I always knew I wanted to figure out a way to help them.” While he was certain he wanted to work in wildlife conservation as a child, he wasn’t sure how. Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond notes that he always loved the sciences, especially biology, growing up. He then decided to go to college to pursue a major in biology, knowing that he would someday apply it to conservation. Through some formative experiences in undergrad, including a heartfelt discussion with our own Dr. Abou-Madi when he was a zookeeper intern, he learned that he could merge two major interests: medicine and conservation. His hard work paid off when he got a phone call one wintry morning from Dr. Beth Bunting &#8212; he had been offered a spot in Cornell Vet’s Class of 2019. To him, this was a dream come true; he accepted. </span></p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-2401 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-1024x1022.jpg" alt="" width="389" height="389" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-1024x1022.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-768x767.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1-1050x1048.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr1.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 389px) 100vw, 389px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond is particularly grateful for the opportunity he had to develop his interests during his eight years at Cornell. In vet school, some of his favorite courses included Conservation Medicine, Captive Wildlife Management, and a wide range of large animal and production courses. He calls these domestic animal courses “just as important for your development as a zoological veterinarian” as more overtly zoo-related courses. Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond served as Vice President of the Zoo and Wildlife Society, during which time he co-developed the WildLIFE Blog. He was also Vice President of the Theriogenology Club during his time as a student and took on opportunities to continue developing his research skills, including an Expanding Horizons project in Namibia working with the Cheetah Conservation Fund. “We’re sitting on a gold mine at Cornell,” he says of the Expanding Horizons Program. “The opportunity to go abroad as a vet student and have agency in a project and work on something completely novel to you is an experience that is completely worth it, whether or not you want to work abroad.”</span><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignright wp-image-2403 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="283" height="377" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-225x300.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-113x150.jpg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193-1050x1400.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr2-1-e1649117107193.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 283px) 100vw, 283px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Zoo/wildlife-related experiences aside, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond also emphasizes “leaning into things that aren’t necessarily just of professional interest, but that also speak to the heart.” This spirit of exploration should also, in his opinion, inform externship decisions. “Do something that you definitely want to do and do something somewhat related to it that you’re not sure about.” For Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond, this included an externship at a traditional zoological institution, the Brookfield Zoo, and a preceptorship at White Oak Conservation Center. Through these experiences, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond came to love population medicine and the semi-free ranging wildlife model. Faculty also play an integral role in the self-discovery process. “Ultimately people are faculty at Cornell for a reason. They want to be there and they deserve to be there. You know they worked hard to get there and they want to help. They want to nurture.” Faculty at Cornell played an integral role in helping him choose his next steps after receiving his DVM. </span><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-2404 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-214x300.jpg" alt="" width="292" height="410" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-214x300.jpg 214w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-729x1024.jpg 729w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-768x1079.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-1094x1536.jpg 1094w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-107x150.jpg 107w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3-1050x1475.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr3.jpg 1367w" sizes="(max-width: 292px) 100vw, 292px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> After graduation, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond completed a small animal rotating internship at VCA West Los Angeles to “gain confidence and competence in my clinical skills.” He is quick to emphasize the many potential pathways to a career in conservation medicine, including internships in large animal and equine medicine. After completing his first internship, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond went on to Colorado State University to complete a zoological medicine and surgery specialty internship, all while the pandemic was turning the veterinary community and the world at large upside down. “Learning how to extrapolate information and learning how to work in completely novel scenarios were the biggest things that I took away from that.” From there, Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond felt called to return to his love for population-based medicine, and found Fossil Rim Wildlife Center to be the ideal next destination. His current role as the David E. Wildlt Fellow in Zoological Medicine there gives him an abundance of opportunities. “This place is amazing, and being able to take all of that medicine that I learned in the past two years and now apply it in a different setting with new challenges is really personally fulfilling. And I’m starting to get a better appreciation for what it means to be a veterinarian as it relates to conservation, which is really cool.”</span><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr4.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignright wp-image-2405 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr4-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="294" height="391" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr4-225x300.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr4-113x150.jpg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr4.jpg 360w" sizes="(max-width: 294px) 100vw, 294px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond is still charting the course he wants to follow when his time at Fossil Rim ends, but for him the uncertain, ever-evolving nature of conservation is part of what makes the work so special. While he is partial to umbrella and keystone species and is particularly drawn to his favorite animal, the tiger, he is thrilled by the countless ways to help save wild places and species. “There is so much to understand, to learn, and to try. I have the veterinary medicine part down, but that is not the end-all-be-all when it comes to saving animals. Conservation is about people. And so that’s the aspect of One Health that I haven’t spent as much time with. I’ve got a pretty good handle on one-third of it, but there’s two-thirds left and I want to be able to work with a transdisciplinary team and continue to grow. I don’t know where I’m going to be in a year and that makes me nervous, but I know where I want to be. And as long as I keep my eye on the North Star, I think it will be okay. This world is changing very rapidly and people are starting to pay attention to One Health and the health of our ecosystems, so I’m hopeful that that translates into a need. You can only remain hopeful, and I encourage you to stay hopeful.”</span></p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-2406 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-278x300.jpg" alt="" width="352" height="380" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-278x300.jpg 278w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-950x1024.jpg 950w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-768x828.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-1425x1536.jpg 1425w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-139x150.jpg 139w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5-1050x1132.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/05/zdr5.jpg 1781w" sizes="(max-width: 352px) 100vw, 352px" /></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While the years since his graduation have been action-packed, it wasn’t long ago that Dr. Dvornicky-Raymond was in our shoes, and he is eager to share his advice for current vet students. First, keep an open mind. “Being a traditional zoo vet at a zoo is one pathway. There are so many different ways that you can have an impact on the natural world and on wildlife conservation that are not just being a zoo vet. So do not be discouraged by people that say there are no jobs in zoological medicine. Those people have a very narrow sight. They’re not thinking big enough.” The current state of the world, he says, calls for novel solutions to problems, and he believes that there is a place for everyone and their unique talents in this sphere. “Don’t feel like you have to go all-or-nothing, as long as you’re doing something. If you care about it, find some way to get involved.” For his parting advice, he’s willing to veer into sentimental territory. “Follow your heart. I know I sound like a Disney character right now. You’re going to hear a lot of naysayers and you’re going to encounter a lot of challenges, but remember that at the end of these challenges is a life of whatever you choose to do. And you have to make sure that you are fulfilled in doing that. There are ways that each person differs that will guide you to where you’re supposed to be. So follow your heart and don’t let </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">people tell you what to do.” </span></p>
<hr />
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2394 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg" alt="" width="272" height="246" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-166x150.jpg 166w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-150x136.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 272px) 100vw, 272px" />Colleen Sorge, Class of 2024, is originally from Long Island, NY. She graduated with a B.S. in Animal Science and a minor in English from Cornell University. She often finds herself missing her humanities courses in vet school and is thrilled she can combine her passions for writing and for veterinary medicine as the WildLIFE Blog Editor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guidance from Graduates: Dr. Matt Marinkovich (DVM ‘14)</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/02/21/guidance-from-graduates-dr-matt-marinkovich-dvm-14/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colleen Sorge]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 13:00:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[planetary health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ZAWS]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zoo medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2390</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dr. Matt Marinkovich ('14) discusses his career path leading him to his role at the San Diego Zoo! <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/02/21/guidance-from-graduates-dr-matt-marinkovich-dvm-14/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2392 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="252" height="336" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-225x300.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-113x150.jpg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1-1050x1400.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-1.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 252px) 100vw, 252px" />Dr. Matt Marinkovich always had a passion for wildlife but was initially unsure as to what career path might suit him best. “I always knew I wanted to do something with wildlife or something conservation related, but it took a little while to find what that niche was, whether PhD or vet school. I had a couple experiences at SeaWorld San Diego when I was in undergrad and at the National History Museum in Santa Barbara working with the Marine Mammal Stranding Network that led me to really feel like veterinary medicine was the route to go.” After taking 3 gap years, he began his time at Cornell Vet, going on to complete his DVM in 2014.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dr. Marinkovich is quick to acknowledge the role that Cornell played in his success, recalling formative moments like an Expanding Horizons experience with the Mountain Gorilla Veterinary Project and praising the faculty he worked with as a student. “You have people there who are really quality professors, but also really quality people and really good mentors. I think I learned a ton from them both from an academic standpoint and also what it means to be a good clinician.” His experiences at Cornell have largely shaped his approach to clinical practice. “There’s still a million things that I don’t know. I’m still surprised every day and challenged every day which is one of the reasons I love wildlife medicine. But in vet school you really develop that approach to cases and that approach to working with others and being part of a team.” Asked what Cornell courses he suggests, Dr. Marinkovich recommends casting a wide net. “The nice part about being a student interested in zoo or wildlife is that everything is applicable. There’s no class and no species that isn’t applicable to your potential future profession. I just tried to soak up as much as I could and be a sponge as much as I could.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">After graduation from vet school, Dr. Marinkovich completed rotating small animal and emergency and critical care specialty internships, both at the Animal Medical Center, before matching with the UC Davis San Diego Zoo Wildlife Alliance Sea World Zoo Residency. After completing his residency in 2019, he began his current position working as a clinical veterinarian at the San Diego Zoo. The work is just as exciting as it sounds! “My dream was to end up at a place like San Diego Zoo, which has a very high-volume clinical case load. We have tons of animals and we provide very high level care to all of the wildlife in our care.” A highlight of the position, he says, is the ability to apply teamwork to particularly challenging cases, as the zoo currently has six veterinarians, a fellow, and a resident. While the medical care of the zoo’s animals takes up the bulk of his time, Dr. Marinkovich also has the opportunity to help support international conservation efforts. “The San Diego Zoo is very involved with Hawaiian forest bird conservation and we have facilities in Maui and the Big Island. I’ve been out there several times to provide medical treatment for the animals in our care out there. I went to Madagascar when I was a resident to help provide emergent medical care to tortoises from a recent confiscation.” Today his favorite cases are usually the ones that demand the most time, facilitating a personal connection. Dr. Marinkovich recalls treating a ring-tailed lemur as a resident and the fulfillment he felt nursing the individual back to health. “That’s an animal that I’ll still go and visit at the zoo years later.” On another occasion, he worked alongside radiologists and human respiratory specialists to diagnose and treat bronchomalacia in an adult male orangutan. “Cases like that where we’re alerted to a problem, we diagnose the source of the problem, and we develop novel ways to fix that problem, especially in a species that is important to us and the greater conservation world are really exciting and really valuable.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2393 alignright" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-225x300.jpeg" alt="" width="381" height="508" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-225x300.jpeg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-768x1024.jpeg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-113x150.jpeg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739-1050x1400.jpeg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/marinkovich-2-e1645326716739.jpeg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 381px) 100vw, 381px" />While well aware that the field of zoological medicine is competitive, Dr. Marinkovich has a refreshing viewpoint. “I think really just focusing on becoming the best vet you can be is the number one step. I think what we look for in terms of a good resident is someone who has a really good foundation in veterinary medicine, and that involves all species. The next time you have to help pull a calf, it may be an exotic bovid rather than a dairy cow.” His perspective, he says, is largely informed by his respect for mental health. “I’m a huge proponent of mental health and being happy with what you’re doing and enjoying each step of the journey. I think you need to take each step and try to get the most out of each experience for what it is. It’s great if zoo residency or working a zoo job works out, but if not, being a vet is an awesome job and you still have that to be fulfilled by. You have to try to not let the quest for that elusive zoo resident position to be the end all and be all of what it means to be fulfilled in this field. Developing your skill sets, really focusing on your own mental health, and who you are as a vet and as a person is going to set you up for success.” </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Regardless of one’s exact career trajectory, Dr. Marinkovich emphasizes the abundant opportunities to contribute to conservation and the health of wildlife species. “There are so many really interesting and fulfilling ways to be a veterinarian involved with wildlife and conservation. A lot of those opportunities may not have all been fully explored or fleshed out yet, so the sky’s the limit if you are passionate about something. I think our field will be better off because of that. There is an increasing need for people who have a skill set and a passion for the world around them and the wildlife that’s in it. It is a daunting time for people who are passionate about wildlife, but there are a lot of opportunities to find your niche and the way that you are going to make your mark.”  </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr />
<div class="entry-content">
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-2394 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="271" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-166x150.jpg 166w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/02/colleen-150x136.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" />Colleen Sorge, Class of 2024, is originally from Long Island, NY. She graduated with a B.S. in Animal Science and a minor in English from Cornell University. She often finds herself missing her humanities courses in vet school and is thrilled she can combine her passions for writing and for veterinary medicine as the WildLIFE Blog Editor.</p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Conversations with Classmates: Carolina Baquerizo&#8217;s Summer with SEZARC</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/01/27/2379/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Carolina Baquerizo]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2022 13:00:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Wildlife Opportunities Outside CUCVM]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[internship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[one health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[reproduction]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[summer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zoo medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2379</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hear from Carolina Baquerizo '24 about her extraordinary summer with the South-East Zoo Alliance for Reproduction and Conservation! <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2022/01/27/2379/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>Q: Where was your internship this summer?!</b></p>
<p><b>A: </b> <span style="font-weight: 400;">In pursuit of a career in zoological medicine, my life has made twists and turns that I could have never imagined. As a Florida girl at heart, I knew I wanted to return to my home state for a summer internship involving wildlife medicine. With the help of my mentor, Dr. Osofsky, Director of the Cornell Wildlife Health Center, I became acquainted with a gem in Northeast Florida: the South-East Zoo Alliance for Reproduction and Conservation (SEZARC). Directed by Dr. Linda Penfold, SEZARC works on reproduction challenges in several US zoos and aquariums across the country. Some of their work involves fertility checks, assisted reproduction, and contraception in wildlife. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2384" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-225x300.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-113x150.jpg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675-1050x1400.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/3-e1643243457675.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></p>
<p><b>Q: What work did you participate in at your internship?</b></p>
<p><b>A: </b> <span style="font-weight: 400;">The internship involved many hands-on opportunities. In the lab, I learned how to examine semen characteristics microscopically from stingrays, sharks, tigers, okapis, and many other species! I learned how to utilize ELISA to detect hormone concentrations in elephant stool samples. In the field, I learned how to collect and cryopreserve semen samples from tigers and cheetahs for genome banking purposes. I conducted literature searches on reproduction information for various zoo animals in the office.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In addition to interning at SEZARC, the organization’s connections with other conservation/zoological facilities in North Florida opened up some unexpected doors. I shadowed zoo veterinarians from White Oak Conservation and the Jacksonville Zoo! Under the supervision of White Oak vets, I vaccinated a rhino calf and attended an okapi echocardiogram. At the Jacksonville Zoo, I attended routine elephant health checks and shadowed roseate spoonbill pre-shipment exams. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2382" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-225x300.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-113x150.jpg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311-1050x1400.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/2-e1643243358311.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></p>
<p><b>Q: What did you gain from this experience?</b></p>
<p><b>A:</b> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Before this internship, I lacked actual research experience. SEZARC allowed me to explore research with the ability to ask lots of questions! From literature searches, data collection and entry, lab work, and paper writing, I feel I left with a well-rounded understanding of the purpose of wildlife reproduction research for conservation. SEZARC combined my passions for zoological medicine and theriogenology in ways I could have never imagined. I hope to continue working in research as a veterinary student and a zoo veterinarian hopeful.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-2385" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-300x225.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-768x576.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-200x150.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-150x113.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4-1050x788.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/4.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<hr />
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2387 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-285x300.jpg" alt="" width="285" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-285x300.jpg 285w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-973x1024.jpg 973w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-768x808.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-1460x1536.jpg 1460w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-143x150.jpg 143w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5-1050x1105.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2022/01/5.jpg 1825w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px" />Carolina Baquerizo, Class of 2024, received her BS in Biological Science from Florida State University. She began volunteering at Zoo Miami when she was 15 and has held multiple zoological internships since then. She aspires to become a zoo veterinarian as a way to participate in </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">ex situ</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> conservation work.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Faculty Focus: A Conversation with Dr. Robin Radcliffe</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/11/17/faculty-feature-a-conversation-with-dr-robin-radcliffe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Colleen Sorge]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 12:50:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Externships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Resources]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wildlife Opportunities Outside CUCVM]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[engaged cornell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faculty feature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[faculty focus]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[In the News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[planetary health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[research]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wildlife Health Cornell]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2364</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hear from Dr. Robin Radcliffe about his training, his current work, and his tips for aspiring wildlife veterinarians! <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/11/17/faculty-feature-a-conversation-with-dr-robin-radcliffe/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Several weeks ago my Block III tutor group was abuzz with the news that our tutor, Dr. Robin Radcliffe, and his colleagues had been honored with the 2021 Ig Nobel Prize in recognition of their work evaluating the efficacy of transporting rhinoceroses by hanging them upside down from helicopters. The prize, awarded every year since 1991, aims to &#8220;honor achievements that <em>first make people laugh, and then make them think</em>.&#8221; To those of us in the tutor group interested in conservation and wildlife medicine, it was a welcome reminder that we are surrounded by faculty at Cornell who have done what can sometimes feel like the impossible: forged a career in the world of zoo and wildlife medicine. Charged with renewed inspiration, I reached out to Dr. Radcliffe in the hopes of learning more about his career trajectory and his current work.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2365 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="367" height="275" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-300x225.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-768x576.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-200x150.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-150x113.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2-1050x788.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 367px) 100vw, 367px" /></p>
<p>Dr. Radcliffe obtained his veterinary degree from the University of Minnesota alongside his twin brother &amp; fellow Cornell faculty member, Dr. Rolfe Radcliffe. Says Dr. Radcliffe, “We went from kindergarten through vet school together.” While a vet student Dr. Radcliffe pursued wildlife-centric externships and experiences, though he is quick to note, “I was a little bit disheartened by vet school because there weren’t as many opportunities as there are now in wildlife.” After obtaining his DVM, Dr. Radcliffe worked in a mixed animal practice and then spent a year working exclusively with camelids before returning to Fossil Rim Wildlife Center, where he had been an extern, to work as an associate veterinarian. He later took over as Director of Animal Health. While at Fossil Rim, Dr. Radcliffe completed the requirements for board certification in the American College of Zoological Medicine through the experiential track. Of his somewhat unconventional route to board certification he says, “I preferred the experiential pathway because I wasn’t interested in a zoological position. I knew I wanted to work with field conservation and free-ranging wildlife populations, and even now there’s only one approved wildlife health residency. There’s probably going to be more coming, but when I went to school there were no approved wildlife residencies so it was harder then.” He spent about a decade at Fossil Rim Wildlife Center working largely with rhinoceroses before moving to the International Rhino Foundation and eventually, to Cornell. At Cornell, Dr. Radcliffe teaches, conducts ongoing research into a wide variety of endangered species, and has developed training programs, most significantly, the Engaged Cornell Program.</p>
<p>The diversity of his work is part of what appeals to him, according to Dr. Radcliffe, though in recent years he has been taking on more projects close to home. “I’ve spent a good part of my career traveling all over the world which was great—I loved it—but I’m also very interested in making sure that we conserve and protect the wildlife right here at home. I think that’s important. If you’re going to do international work, I think it’s essential that you address or at least have some experience with conservation in your own part of the world because so much of it is communities and people.” While he has tremendously enjoyed the opportunities that his job has afforded, he notes, “Most people think that it’s so glamorous to be a wildlife veterinarian, and it can be, but there’s so much work that goes into a successful partnership and a field project that people don’t necessarily recognize up front. I do spend a lot of time on that, on communication with partners, grant writing, and helping to sustain the projects that I am invested in.” Another fundamental part of successful projects abroad, according to Dr. Radcliffe, is a commitment to maintaining relationships with research partners. “I think for me, the most important thing is curiosity, and not just scientific curiosity, but curiosity about the place you’re going and the environment, the people, the language, the culture. You should go into a place prepared to learn the language and appreciate the culture. For me, a long term partnership is one in which I come away with it feeling like I have friendships and long term relationships there. I can communicate with my colleagues any time, day or night. They will help me in a pinch and I’ll do anything for them. It’s also little things, like when we publish anything, we always include the local authors and, more often than not, the local authors are lead authors on the publication.”</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2366 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="404" height="269" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-300x200.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-768x512.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-225x150.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-150x100.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3-1050x700.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/11/dr.-radcliffe-3.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 404px) 100vw, 404px" />For students looking to enter the increasingly competitive field, Dr. Radcliffe’s first suggestion is to capitalize on the opportunities we have here at Cornell Vet. “I think there’s a lot of expertise here at Cornell and there’s a lot of opportunities.” These include Engaged Cornell, Expanding Horizons, and a myriad of courses aimed at students interested in pursuing careers in zoo, wildlife, and exotics medicine. Dr. Radcliffe teaches a 3-part course called <em>Conservation with Communities for One Health</em>, which reflects the multi-disciplinary mindset crucial to effective conservation work. Both undergraduate and veterinary students are able to take this course, and a subset of them travel in teams to field sites in the Congo, Uganda, and Indonesia to participate in projects with institutions that Dr. Radcliffe has built relationships with over the years, including the Jane Goodall Institute and WWF-Indonesia. Coursework aside, Dr. Radcliffe encourages students to take advantage of networking opportunities and to pursue externships that excite them.</p>
<p>Between training the next generation of wildlife veterinarians and working to save endangered species, Dr. Radcliffe has a full plate to say the least. Amid the challenges his work presents he remains optimistic, citing a recent experience in Alaska working with gyrfalcon. “Their attitude in Alaska is let’s save the gyrfalcon and the Arctic ecosystem before everything’s gone. My message for future wildlife students is this: let’s be proactive and use our resources the best we can because it’s very expensive to recover endangered species, it’s very expensive to do so in a zoo in a captive setting. The Alaskan attitude, which I love, is let’s take care of our species before they become endangered!” In the case of already endangered species like Javan and Sumatran rhinos, there are tremendous obstacles to overcome. Still, Dr. Radcliffe feels his most impactful work may be done in mentoring colleagues and training students. “That’s the kind of impact that I feel is the most important that I can make in the long term.”</p>
<hr />
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2240 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-300x271.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="271" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-300x271.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-1024x924.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-768x693.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-166x150.jpg 166w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-150x135.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot-1050x948.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2020/09/colleenheadshot.jpg 1202w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" />Colleen Sorge, Class of 2024, is originally from Long Island, NY. She graduated with a B.S. in Animal Science and a minor in English from Cornell University. She often finds herself missing her humanities courses in vet school and is thrilled she can combine her passions for writing and for veterinary medicine as the WildLIFE Blog Editor.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Gazelles, Brain Surgery, Elephants and Kestrels: A Spontaneous, Life-Altering 4 Months in Israel</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/10/24/gazelles-hedgehogs-elephants-and-kestrels-a-spontaneous-life-altering-4-months-in-israel/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jared Zion]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 13:00:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Externships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wildlife Opportunities Outside CUCVM]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ecology]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international experiences]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[one health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife health]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife rehab]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zoo medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2343</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Jared Zion ('23) details his extraordinary experience at The Israeli Wildlife Hospital in Tel Aviv, Israel. Click to find out more! <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/10/24/gazelles-hedgehogs-elephants-and-kestrels-a-spontaneous-life-altering-4-months-in-israel/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Amid the COVID-19 pandemic, much like everyone else, my summer externship plans were severely impacted. However, in the middle of spring semester 2021, I sought out an opportunity over 5000 miles away that resulted in being one of the most rewarding experiences of my life. The Israeli Wildlife Hospital in Tel Aviv, Israel, which operates as a non-profit organization with shared ownership through the Ramat Gan Safari/Zoological Center and Israeli National Parks Authority, is responsible for the treatment, management and release of all wildlife brought to its doors. As the sole wildlife hospital in the country, this unique hospital manages a heavy and varied daily caseload, treating both wildlife and zoo animals. The hospital employs a multi-faceted team of veterinary professionals, supported by zookeepers, technicians, curators, ecologists, zoologists, and volunteers to work collaboratively to provide advanced animal care. It was in this setting that I was able to experience nearly all facets of wildlife/zoological animal care – my first clinical experience with such varied wildlife/zoo patients.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2348 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto5-231x300.png" alt="" width="231" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto5-231x300.png 231w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto5-116x150.png 116w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto5.png 605w" sizes="(max-width: 231px) 100vw, 231px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sometimes triaging upwards of 20+ patients per morning, animals in need of care were brought in from park rangers and ordinary citizens. Creating a prioritized triage and assessment of the patients was paramount for the maximal survival of the patients. In addition to individual requirements, fluid therapy was a hallmark of initial care, at times requiring catheterization. As a result, I fine-tuned my clinical skills/techniques, facilitated catheters, participated in numerous surgeries and devised treatment plans and dietary/husbandry techniques with the veterinarians and keepers.  </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">An all-hands-on deck participation was often required for the most fragile of patients, from raptor chicks like common and lesser Kestrels and Scops Owls to non-raptor winged animals like kingfishers, swallows, bee-eaters, and occasionally bats. In terms of small mammals, Western Eurasian hedgehogs infected with Scabies were a common occurrence – sometimes with more severe crusting, and/or unrelated trauma. Further diagnostics employing imaging modalities, fluid plans, dosing/delivering medications, etc. rapidly and efficiently were often needed.Patients often needed temporary homes or to be quarantined to prevent </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">the spread of pathogens between patients. I was impressed by the incredible knowledge of the head keepers, who were so attuned to each species’ requirements and were able to direct appropriately.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2347 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto4-266x300.png" alt="" width="266" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto4-266x300.png 266w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto4-133x150.png 133w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto4.png 371w" sizes="(max-width: 266px) 100vw, 266px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The diversity of animals I was exposed to was awesome! Highlights included treating an African elephant in the zoo with signs of colic, chameleons from the Galilee region, stone-curlews, eagle owls,  and a large male ibex with a broken femur. Throughout the three-month externship and while working in visual distance of zebras, rhinos, waterfowl, and the like, I participated in the care of many different types of animals, each of which had specific species protocols. For example, critical protocols for hooved animals like gazelles and ibexes (often brought in as a hit-by-car accidents) were in place to prevent the spread of harmful disease. Foot and Mouth disease is a highly contagious aphthovirus with varying strains throughout the Middle East. If introduced, this would be detrimental to the Safari animals. Impromptu field work required us to meet the park rangers at the gate of the safari, perform a quick and calm physical assessment, collect blood, run an ELISA and once negative, bring the patient into the grounds for a full evaluation. Additionally with these ungulates, capture myopathy was another real and serious implication, given the animal’s extensive journey to the hospital from the wild.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Israel is a small country and the team must constantly create appropriate treatment and release plans for their patients, taking into consideration neighboring countries’ cultural and animal care differences as many of the species are migratory and traverse through borders. Often, we saw raptors with lead bullets, metabolic bone disease, and clear signs of cut wings and rope strangulations. These examples highlight the cultural differences in neighboring countries in direct contrast to Israel’s strict animal care laws &#8211; preventing wild animal ownership and hunting.</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2345 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto2-199x300.png" alt="" width="231" height="348" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto2-199x300.png 199w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto2-100x150.png 100w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto2.png 397w" sizes="(max-width: 231px) 100vw, 231px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">One case involving the complete exam/work up, diagnosis and neurologic surgical treatment of a female ibex with </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sarcocystis neurona</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> sticks out in my memory. The young female ibex was brought to the hospital with an appreciable left-sided head tilt and ipsilateral circling. Radiographs including skull images were taken, revealing no obvious insult or head trauma. Thereafter, a conservative treatment protocol was devised. Without any resumption of clinical signs over the next days, one of the country’s top neuro-specialists from the Koret School of Veterinary Medicine came to perform a thorough neurologic exam and advise the team towards the course of action. A CT was needed in which I, along with one of the house veterinarians, transported the ibex and another neurologic in-patient (a fox) to a nearby advanced small animal practice to perform the CT. A large cyst was evident in the CT images and CSF fluid was collected and analyzed.</span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Sarcocystis neurona</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> was the top differential and we prepped for surgery. It was incredible to watch the surgery and experience this so early in my veterinary career. The surgery was a profound success as the gelatinous cyst (confirmed to be </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sarcocystis neurona</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">) atop the cerebellum was removed. Within days of treatment her head tilt resolved and approximately two weeks post-surgery, I participated in her release back to the wild. Driving south, to the Mitzpe Ramon Crater in the Negev desert, the beautiful scenery and landscape was only surpassed by the joy of seeing the release of the ibex to her native environment. She darted out of her carrier and seemed to appreciate the scenery as much as I did. With a parting glance, the animal successfully reintegrated back to her land. The magic of this story was so special that it was written about in the “Yediot Achranot” [one of the major newspapers in Israel] with my name written in Hebrew attached – quite the feature!</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2346 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto3-229x300.png" alt="" width="229" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto3-229x300.png 229w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto3-114x150.png 114w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/blogphoto3.png 612w" sizes="(max-width: 229px) 100vw, 229px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Among the usual stresses that come with the end of a semester, I would never have imagined experiencing intense rocket attacks. As sirens sounded, video from the safari displayed a peculiar behavior: adult elephants began circling the calves in a predatory-protective mode <a href="https://www.ynetnews.com/environment/article/BkbDNgOF00"> https://www.ynetnews.com/environment/article/BkbDNgOF00</a>. Furthermore, the safari itself was directly impacted when a missile landed adjacent to one of the monkeys exhibits, and shrapnel pierced the back of one primate and simultaneously burned the wings of a nearby bird. Safari veterinarians quickly performed lifesaving treatments on the animals and fortunately, none lost their lives. Both stories were broadcast in the Israeli media outlets and garnered an overflow of support from the Israeli population. While those 11 days were truly frightening, with sirens blaring throughout the night and day at any moment, interceptions from Israel’s Iron Dome Defense system overhead, I was grateful to have a strong support network of family, friends and Cornell faculty willing to work with me to complete the semester.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The four months I spent in Israel posed a truly unforgettable experience. I befriended people from all over the world, explored the country, improved my Hebrew knowledge and underwent substantial personal development. I learned an array of clinical skills, zoological knowledge, and management skills from experts. The high quality of medicine at the Israeli Wildlife Hospital with an incredibly knowledgeable, understanding, positive, and welcoming team made this experience unforgettable.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For students interested in externship opportunities, the team is eager to welcome veterinary students and I couldn’t recommend this experience any further. They may be reached at </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">hospital@safari.co.il</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">(Hebrew knowledge not required) and follow them on Instagram @Israel.wildlife.hospital and the Ramat Gan Safari: @Safari_Israel</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Israeli Wildlife Hospital Homepage:</span></p>
<p><a href="https://www.wildlife-hospital.org.il/en/%D7%93%D7%A3-%D7%94%D7%91%D7%99%D7%AA-copy/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">https://www.wildlife-hospital.org.il/en/%D7%93%D7%A3-%D7%94%D7%91%D7%99%D7%AA-copy/</span></a></p>
<hr />
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2349 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/jared-300x294.png" alt="" width="300" height="294" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/jared-300x294.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/jared-153x150.png 153w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/jared-150x147.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/jared.png 756w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" />Jared Zion, Class of 2023, hails</span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> from New York City. Since Jared’s start at Cornell, he has been in pursuit of exploring unique veterinary opportunities. His passion for non-traditional species is driven by the uniqueness, individual requirements and complexities in every patient &#8211; harnessing a huge drive through his path in veterinary medicine. Some of the most important things in Jared’s life involve creating genuine connections, travel, learning about different cultures, and creating a balanced, stress-minimal life that will enhance  his career working with such a variety of species in the future. </span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fishy Adventures &#8211; AQUAVET® Edition</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/10/03/fishy-adventures-aquavet-edition/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Hery Rios-Guzman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 03 Oct 2021 19:27:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aquatic medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[AQUAVET]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marine mammals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[summer]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[zoo medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2333</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hery Ríos-Guzmán ('24) discusses his summer with AQUAVET and the possibilities within aquatic veterinary medicine. Keep reading to learn more! <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/10/03/fishy-adventures-aquavet-edition/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2334 aligncenter" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-225x300.jpeg" alt="" width="225" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-225x300.jpeg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-768x1024.jpeg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-1152x1536.jpeg 1152w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-113x150.jpeg 113w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1-1050x1400.jpeg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1.jpeg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I want to be an aquatic veterinarian when I grow up. And no, that doesn’t mean that I just want to work with fishes. Well, at least not entirely. Aquatic veterinary medicine is not so much a field within veterinary medicine, but a completely parallel entity. In other words, there is an aquatic veterinary job for every terrestrial veterinary job. And that means that there is more to aquatic animal medicine than “just fishes.” For example, production animal vets are akin to aquaculture vets, whereas zoo/wildlife vets are typically mirrored by aquarium veterinarians. And there are plenty of other examples, too! Isn’t that super cool?!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You may be wondering how the heck you’ve never heard of any of this. Truth be told, the lack of exposure to aquatic animal health is a real problem within veterinary curricula nationwide. Granted, it would be very hard to cram even more information into an already packed curriculum. Hope is not lost, however! There are various extracurricular courses that you can take advantage of if you feel like aquatic animal medicine is for you. MARVET, SeaVet, and AQUAVET are just some of these amazing opportunities. All three are very different in terms of length, cost, and location, but they will undoubtedly expose you to the amazing world of aquatics. I know that AQUAVET did so for me.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">AQUAVET is a summer program that is open to veterinary students (and veterinarians) from all over the world. It consists of three courses, AQUAVET I – III, each of which is focused on a particular aspect of aquatic veterinary medicine. AQUAVET III is dedicated to clinical aspects of marine mammals, while AQUAVET II is focused on the histology and histopathology of various aquatic species. The course I was fortunate to take this past summer,  AQUAVET I, is a one-month crash course on all things aquatic. It provides information on the anatomy, pathology, husbandry, and clinical aspects of a plethora of aquatic animals. From invertebrates like jellyfish and corals to vertebrates like sea turtles and marine mammals, AQUAVET I does it all! In addition to learning about these animals, I also learned important diagnostic techniques, such as fin clips, venipuncture, necropsies, and gill endoscopies. To finish it all off, I got to perform supervised surgery on a fish!</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2335 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="440" height="330" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2-300x225.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2-768x576.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2-200x150.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2-150x113.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-2.jpg 960w" sizes="(max-width: 440px) 100vw, 440px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As you might imagine, there is absolutely no way that all of this can occur in a one-month time frame and not be a tremendous amount of work. Believe me when I say it is! With ten-hour workdays, five days a week (and some work on Saturdays, too), it’s a LOT of work. Fortunately, AQUAVET I isn’t all work and no fun. In fact, it feels just like summer camp for fish nerds! I got to meet amazing people from veterinary schools all over</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> the United States and beyond. When we weren’t studying, my AQUAVET cohort and I were playing volleyball on the sand courts, enjoying the breeze of the Rhode Island shores, or enjoying one of the many social activities that were part of AQUAVET. It was truly amazing to make connections with students who get as excited as I do when someone so much as mentions something remotely aquatic-related. AQUAVET truly made me feel like I finally found my people.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In addition to networking with students, I got the chance to meet many incredible lecturers. In fact, it’s common for there to be more lecturers than students during AQUAVET I. I received lectures from government officials, aquarium and aquaculture veterinarians, and veterinarians who have created their own jobs. The best thing about having so many lecturers come in, coupled with the fact that this field is so small, is that they all want to see you succeed. I even got a letter of recommendation from one of the professors at AQUAVET that allowed me to win a scholarship!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All in all, AQUAVET I was an amazing experience that I will cherish for years to come. It provides the opportunity to obtain aquatic animal resources and develop clinical skills related to all types of animals while building relationships with like-minded people. Without a doubt, AQUAVET has made me a more resilient veterinary student, one who is better prepared for a future as an aquatic veterinarian.</span></p>
<hr />
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2336 alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-229x300.jpg" alt="" width="229" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-229x300.jpg 229w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-781x1024.jpg 781w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-768x1007.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1172x1536.jpg 1172w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-114x150.jpg 114w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery-1050x1376.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/10/hery.jpg 1465w" sizes="(max-width: 229px) 100vw, 229px" />Hery Ríos-Guzmán, Class of 2024, obtained his Animal Science/Pre-Vet degree from the University of Puerto Rico – Mayagüez. The island environment in which he grew up influenced his professional interests and put him on the path to aquatic veterinary medicine. He has special interests in conservation medi</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">cine and hopes to use his knowledge to improve coral reef health around the world.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Summer With Man’s Closest Living Relatives</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/03/10/a-summer-with-mans-closest-living-relatives/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Mariacamila Garcia Estrella]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 18:15:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[chimpanzees]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[engaged cornell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[field work]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Jane Goodall]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2316</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<img src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5.jpg">
Camila Garcia Estrella ('23) details her trip to work with chimpanzees at the Jane Goodall Institute. Keep reading to learn more.  <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/03/10/a-summer-with-mans-closest-living-relatives/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div id="attachment_2319" style="width: 521px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2319" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2319" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" width="511" height="287" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2.jpg 1600w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-300x169.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-768x432.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-1536x864.jpg 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-250x141.jpg 250w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-150x84.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila2-1050x591.jpg 1050w" sizes="(max-width: 511px) 100vw, 511px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2319" class="wp-caption-text">Tchimpounga at Sunset</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">In college, I fell in love with wildlife medicine and conservation. It’s a tough field to get into though, and at the time I didn’t know if I was really cut out for it. That all changed when I landed the internship of a lifetime with the Jane Goodall Institute at Tchimpounga Chimpanzee Sanctuary in the Republic of Congo. This internship was part of Dr. Robin Radcliffe’s One Health course in partnership with Engaged Cornell and it was the first time it was ever offered. I was the first undergraduate student from Cornell to intern with the Jane Goodall Institute (JGI) in Congo, so I really did not know what to expect. The internship was set up to pair a veterinary student with an undergraduate student to collaborate on a project for the summer. Unfortunately, my partner had a last minute complication and was unable to travel with me. I found this out the same day we were set to travel, just as I was about to catch my flight.</span></p>
<div id="attachment_2318" style="width: 310px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2318" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-medium wp-image-2318" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-300x200.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" width="300" height="200" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-225x150.jpg 225w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-150x100.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1-1050x700.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila1.jpg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2318" class="wp-caption-text">Camila in the Noumbi River in Conkouati-Douli National park en route to a Mandrill release site</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">Needless to say, this was not the ideal way to start off my experience in Congo and I would be lying if I said my anxiety wasn’t at an all time high at the thought of having the entire project relying on me. I learned right off the bat that no amount of planning will ever prepare you for a field experience like this. Things can change on the fly so you have to be flexible and roll with the punches. The original project consisted of looking at the cortisol levels of chimpanzees to evaluate at which point in their rehabilitation process they were most stressed. This data would then be used to improve husbandry and rehabilitation practices. This wasn’t exactly what I ended up doing during my time at the sanctuary but I still go a lot out of the experience. In the end, I ended up assisting in several mini projects such as taking measurements of chimpanzees to create a morphometric index to establish malnutrition </span><span style="color: #000000;">parameters, taking water cultures of all the sanctuary’s faucets to ensure the water given to the chimps was properly sanitized, shadowing Dr. Rebeca Atencia while she treated several chimpanzee patients and more. I even got to observe a collaring procedure on a Mandrill in the middle of Conkouati Douli National Park&#8211;quite literally in the middle of the jungle!</span></p>
<div id="attachment_2320" style="width: 174px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2320" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2320 " src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-200x300.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" width="164" height="246" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-200x300.jpg 200w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-100x150.jpg 100w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3-1050x1575.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila3.jpg 1067w" sizes="(max-width: 164px) 100vw, 164px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2320" class="wp-caption-text">Working in the lab with the staff at JGI</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">Despite the incredible experience I ended up having, the first two weeks in Congo were quite difficult for me; I was alone, inexperienced, and thousands of miles away from home. I considered going home several times. Being the first student they had ever hosted only further complicated the situation as there was not a fully established program yet. However, I wasn’t about to let the opportunity of a lifetime go to waste, so I tried to make the best of the situation. I had to push myself out of my comfort zone like never before. I taught myself many things, such as how to work a portable autoclave, how to make my own cell culture medium, and even some basic microbiology from old books the vet kept in the lab. Another big challenge I faced was communicating with the sanctuary staff. This was difficult because not many of them spoke English, so I had to overcome a cultural and language barrier. Thankfully, I was somewhat proficient in French, and this helped me to communicate with my Congolese colleagues. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">Despite all the personal challenges, the good definitely outweighed the bad. The friendships I made, both human and non-human, were what got me through those initial tough times. Every morning I would start my day by walking around the sanctuary to say good morning to the chimps. In time, I came to know every single one by name and learn about their unique personalities. Some of the chimps I connected to most were Alex, Mbebo, Betou, Lemba, Lounama, Falero (the baby of the bunch), and my favorite gal, Youbi. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_2322" style="width: 182px" class="wp-caption alignright"><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2322" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-2322" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="172" height="172" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-300x300.jpg 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-150x150.jpg 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-768x768.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5-1050x1050.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila5.jpg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 172px) 100vw, 172px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2322" class="wp-caption-text">Drawing of Betou relaxing</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">These animals taught me so much about human instinct, and the more time I spent with them, the more I realized just how much they have in common with us. I learned how incredibly intelligent they really are, how cruel they can be, but also how kind and nurturing, not to mention hilarious.  The more time I spent with these animals the more it confirmed that wildlife/conservation medicine was the field for me. Though I still questioned if I had what it took, I got my answer one night when Youbi came into my life. </span></p>
<div id="attachment_2321" style="width: 249px" class="wp-caption alignleft"><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2321" decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2321 size-medium" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-239x300.jpg" alt="" width="239" height="300" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-239x300.jpg 239w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-815x1024.jpg 815w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-768x965.jpg 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-1222x1536.jpg 1222w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-119x150.jpg 119w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4-1050x1320.jpg 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/03/camila4.jpg 1273w" sizes="(max-width: 239px) 100vw, 239px" /></a><p id="caption-attachment-2321" class="wp-caption-text">Drawing of Camila and Youbi</p></div>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">One evening, the sanctuary was on high alert as we were to receive a new chimp from another sanctuary. This was Youbi. I remember the first time I saw her, she looked so tiny and fragile, could barely move and was basically a bag of bones. She was severely malnourished and anemic, as we soon found out. Youbi required an emergency blood transfusion. Dr. Rebeca Atencia, the head veterinarian selected Tchamaka as the donor, a strong, beautiful male chimp that lived at the sanctuary. We gave Youbi the transfusion, but were unable to anesthetize her fearing she wouldn’t wake up from anesthesia. Instead, some of the staff and I had to hold her down using our own strength. Chimpanzees are about four times stronger than the average person, so despite the extreme level of malnutrition/weakness she was in, it still took all the strength I had, plus that of another staff member to subdue Youbi while she received the transfusion. That transfusion worked wonders! It was as if with every drop of blood, Youbi regained a little bit of life back. For the next couple of days, I was tasked with feeding her, giving her her medicine, and providing enrichment. We would inject protein powder and iron supplements into all her food and after a few days she had the strength to move about the room.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400; color: #000000;">Youbi and I formed a bond like no other I have ever experienced. Being with her and taking part in her rehabilitation made me realize that I definitely have what it takes to thrive in this field. It gave me a renowned sense of purpose and I knew then that I had found my calling. This was an experience I will never forget. I will always treasure the memories of my time in Congo.  I am so thankful for having had this opportunity.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Aquadocs: An Aquatic Medicine Podcast</title>
		<link>https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/02/24/aquadocs-an-aquatic-medicine-podcast/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Michelle Greenfield]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 13:00:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[aquatic medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[aquatics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[marine mammals]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/?p=2305</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<img src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16.png">
Michelle Greenfield ('23) discusses the aquatic medicine podcast she started. Keep reading to learn more.  <a class="continue-reading-link" href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/2021/02/24/aquadocs-an-aquatic-medicine-podcast/"> Continue reading</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">While every good veterinary student learns the basics for dogs, cats, horses, and cows, there are usually few (if any) courses specifically focused on aquatic animals. Since before I can remember, all I have wanted to do is study and work with the animals that call the sea their home. Therefore, as someone who intends to pursue a career in aquatics, I am constantly searching for new learning opportunities to expand my understanding of aquatic medicine. As I scoured the internet looking for resources, I realized, there honestly aren’t very many places to look. Sure, there are textbooks and journal articles, and the occasional short summer course (shout out to AQUAVET which is an incredible summer program<a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16.png"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-2307" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16-300x291.png" alt="" width="300" height="291" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16-300x291.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16-768x744.png 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16-155x150.png 155w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16-150x145.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/Picture16.png 1025w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a> sponsored by Cornell), but manuscripts are often dense, and courses can be quite expensive. I am fortunate that Cornell offers a few courses in aquatic animal health—namely Fish Health Management and Anatomy and Histology of Fish—but these courses only touched the surface of all that there is to learn. They cover topics such as common diseases in fish and marine mammals, how to properly monitor water quality in an aquarium, and how to perform a fish necropsy. While these are important lessons for a career in aquatics, I wanted to learn beyond the scope of these courses. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Based off this desire to deepen my own knowledge of aquatic medicine along with lots of encouragement from some incredible Cornell faculty members, namely Dr. Rod Getchell and Dr. Jorge Colon, Aquadocs was formed. Aquadocs is the #1 podcast focused on aquatic medicine and is a top 50 life sciences podcast. On each episode, I interview veterinarians and other aquatic animal health professionals about their careers in the field, what research they are working on, and conservation projects they are involved with. My guests also share lots of advice and guidance for aspiring students interested in pursuing the field of aquatic medicine. Some of the most important advice I have received is that there is no one right path to success in this field, and that having a strong support network and mentorship is key. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I publish new episodes every Tuesday. Here are some of my favorite episodes I recorded (links in episode title): </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-2414 size-medium alignleft" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-300x289.png" alt="" width="300" height="289" srcset="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-300x289.png 300w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-1024x986.png 1024w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-768x740.png 768w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-1536x1479.png 1536w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-156x150.png 156w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-150x144.png 150w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga-1050x1011.png 1050w, https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/beluga.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/1neK2dhPfeM8erw0FDgAFE?si=4c8d5cbe77c54022"><i>Baby</i> <em>Beluga</em>:</a> How do you prepare for a baby beluga? Tune in as Dr. Chelsea Anderson, Georgia Aquarium Associate Veterinarian, describes her experience working with beluga whale Whisper and calf Shila born in May 2020.</p>
<p><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/3-the-astronaut-vet/id1528042513?i=1000491311149"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Astronaut Vet: </span></i></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">Dr. Rick Linnehan, the first veterinarian in space, discusses what it is like to be a NASA astronaut, and describes his journey from being a veterinarian for the Navy’s Marine Mammal Program to being amongst the stars (literally). </span></p>
<p><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/12-stethoscopes-for-dolphins/id1528042513?i=1000499007622"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stethoscopes for Dolphins: </span></i></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">What does a dolphin&#8217;s heart sound like? And how can you use a stethoscope in the water to hear it? Listen as Dr. Barb Linnehan, Deputy Director of Medicine at the National Marine Mammal Foundation, discusses her recent research article about bottlenose dolphin heart health. </span><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/21-manatee-medicine/id1528042513?i=1000508318972"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Manatee Medicine: </span></i></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">Every good vet student knows about cows&#8230; But what about SEA COWS? Tune in this week as we talk to Dr. Mike Walsh, a Veterinarian at the University of Florida, about Manatee health assessments. Every year, he and his colleagues visit Manatee breeding grounds to monitor these populations and ensure the animals are in good health. </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">By hosting and producing this podcast, I hope to teach listeners about aquatic animal health and inspire people around the world to care more about animals and the environments they live in. I want this podcast to be a resource for anyone who is interested in learning about aquatics and a place where people can come together to connect with others passionate about a similar aspect of veterinary medicine. Developing Aquadocs has been an incredible journey so far, and I know it is going to continue to grow for years to come! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you are interested in learning more about Aquadocs, please check out the episodes, which are available on your favorite podcast streaming services (Apple, Spotify, Google) and at </span><a href="http://www.aquadocspodcast.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.aquadocspodcast.com</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. I also post a lot of photos and advice for vet students on Instagram, so please follow us on Instagram and facebook @aquadocspodcast.</span></p>
<hr />
<p>ABOUT THE AUTHOR:</p>
<p><a href="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/MIchelle-Photo.jpg"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-2308" src="https://blogs.cornell.edu/wildlife/files/2021/02/MIchelle-Photo-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" /></a>Michelle Greenfield, class of 2023, is the producer and host of Aquadocs, the #1 podcast on aquatic medicine and a top 50 life sciences podcast. She has a degree in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology from Princeton University. Michelle has interned and volunteered at a number of organizations including the US Navy&#8217;s Marine Mammal Program and Sarasota Dolphin Research Program, Dolphin&#8217;s Plus, Hubbs SeaWorld Research Institute, and SANCCOB. Her research interests focus on bottlenose dolphin social behavior as well as regenerative medicine in horses and marine mammals.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
