<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Animal Place</title>
	<atom:link href="https://animalplace.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://animalplace.org</link>
	<description>Sanctuary, Advocacy, Adoption</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 20:12:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2018/09/cropped-AP_Circle_BW-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Animal Place</title>
	<link>https://animalplace.org</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Ideas and Recipes for an Easy Vegan Thanksgiving</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/veganthanksgiving/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=veganthanksgiving</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/veganthanksgiving/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 12:12:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://animalplace.org/?p=9989</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Are you lost in the dark about a vegan Thanksgiving?  We’ve got your back! This easy guide is just the beginning of what a turkey-friendly table can look like. In this article are several links to not only show you what to eat, but how to prepare dishes using simple recipes. Feeling extra creative? Get started experimenting early, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>Are you lost in the dark about a vegan Thanksgiving? </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’ve got your back!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This easy guide is </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">just the beginning</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> of what a turkey-friendly table can look like. In this article are several links to not only show you <em>what </em>to eat, but <em>how </em>to prepare dishes using simple recipes. Feeling extra creative? Get started experimenting early, adding your own special twist to each dish. Be sure to tag us on social media in all your delicious, turkey-friendly creations!</span></p>
<p><b>For the side dishes: </b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A <a href="https://nomnompaleo.com/post/138166087728/whole-roasted-cauliflower">whole roasted cauliflower</a> provides a hearty texture!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://itdoesnttastelikechicken.com/stuffed-roasted-butternut-squash/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Stuffed, baked butternut squash</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><a href="https://www.thefullhelping.com/20-wholesome-vegan-sweet-potato-recipes/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sweet potato dishes</span></a></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.thekitchn.com/vegan-mashed-potatoes-263095">Mashed potatoes</a> (of course!) made using plant-based milk and butter along with meatless gravy. <a href="https://simple-veganista.com/vegan-mushroom-gravy/">Mushroom gravy</a> is delicious, and Tofurkey brand offers a premade gravy that we absolutely love!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Rice, quinoa or couscous based dishes with candied pecans or walnuts, cranberries, and delicious fall veggies and greens</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://consciouslivingtv.com/blog/food/southern-candied-yams-vegan-man-style.html">Candied yams</a> with vegan marshmallows (Trader Joe’s and many other stores sell these. Dandie&#8217;s are a favorite at the sanctuary!) </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.delish.com/holiday-recipes/thanksgiving/a29167552/vegan-stuffing-recipe/">Stuffing</a> made with veggie broth (if you’re using store-bought, be sure to check the ingredients for animal derivatives)</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;"><a href="https://www.theedgyveg.com/2020/02/27/vegan-pigs-in-blanket-recipe/">Vegan “pigs” in a blanket</a>! Make these using a vegan sausage cooked inside crescent rolls. Field roast apple sage sausage and Tofurkey italian sausage work perfectly! You’ll have a sweet, flaky pastry outside, and a delicious savory inside.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Go non-traditional with vegan <a href="https://lovingitvegan.com/baked-vegan-mac-and-cheese/">Mac-n-cheese</a>! Pressed for time? Try <a href="https://vegetatio.com/content/best-vegan-mac-and-cheese-brands">store bought</a>! Annie’s, Daiya, and even Safeway have their own delicious boxed dairy-free mac.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>For the Main Course:</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">countless </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">vegan turkey-style roasts. Gardein, Field Roast, Tofurky and Trader Joe&#8217;s are three popular U.S. brands that offer their own vegan holiday roasts.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Not interested in turkey alternatives? <a href="https://minimalistbaker.com/1-hour-vegan-shepherds-pie/">Vegan shepherd’s pie</a> can be a hearty, delicious alternative. With a golden-brown, flaky mashed potato crust and a savory filling, shepherd&#8217;s pie is sure to impress omnivores and vegans alike. There are many recipes online, most using lentils and/or vegan ground meats as a base. Once you get the hang of it, it&#8217;s easy to create your own!</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>For the Dessert…</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Everyone loves pumpkin pie! <a href="https://theveganatlas.com/easy-vegan-pumpkin-pie-with-a-butternut-squash-option/">This recipe</a> creates the soft, silken pie texture we all love using tofu. You&#8217;d never know the difference. Not so keen on using tofu? This <a href="https://www.noracooks.com/vegan-pumpkin-pie/">simple alternative</a> uses only nine ingredients to create the perfect pumpkin pie. In our opinion, they&#8217;re both perfect!</span></li>
<li aria-level="1">Pumpkin <em>everything! </em>This delicious <a href="https://ilovevegan.com/healthy-pumpkin-pie-parfait-w-coconut-whip-gluten-and-soy-free/">pumpkin parfait</a> is creamy and light, while <a href="https://lovingitvegan.com/vegan-pumpkin-cheesecake/">pumpkin cheesecake</a> is the ultimate comfort food. <a href="https://lovingitvegan.com/vegan-pumpkin-cake/">Pumpkin cake</a> is always a hit, too.</li>
<li aria-level="1">Who doesn&#8217;t love <a href="https://www.mydarlingvegan.com/vegan-caramel-apple-cobbler/">apple cobbler</a>? Serve this up with your favorite vegan vanilla ice cream!</li>
<li aria-level="1">Did you know that many fruit pies are accidentally vegan? Pies with crumb toppings rather than shells are more likely to be free of animal products. Safeway&#8217;s dutch apple pie and cherry crumb pie are both vegan as is. Always be sure to check the ingredients! Feeling inspired to make one from scratch? Check out these <a href="https://bakedbyclo.com/apple-pie-crumb-topping/">dutch apple pie</a> and <a href="https://holycowvegan.net/vegan-cherry-pie/">cherry pie</a> recipes!</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><em>Written by Chelsea Pinkham</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/veganthanksgiving/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>1</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Animal Place asks Patagonia to Ditch Down</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/animal-place-asks-patagonia-to-ditch-down/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=animal-place-asks-patagonia-to-ditch-down</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/animal-place-asks-patagonia-to-ditch-down/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2022 01:43:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10741</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’ve launched a campaign to end the use of new down feathers. Join us by asking outdoor-wear company Patagonia to cut ties with down use! &#160; It used to be a popular animal rights saying: nobody needs a mink coat more than a mink. At one time, fur was the raging fashion statement. Few people [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-10713 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/10/E-alert-Photos-2022-10-25T142213.532.png" alt="" width="367" height="283" /></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’ve launched a campaign to end the use of new down feathers. </span><a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Join us by asking outdoor-wear company Patagonia to cut ties with down use!</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It used to be a popular animal rights saying: </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">nobody needs a mink coat more than a mink. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">At one time, fur was the raging fashion statement. Few people thought twice about slapping on a coat made from the skin of foxes, rabbits, raccoon dogs, coyotes, mink and more. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">As awareness began to spread about just how cruel the fur industry was, support tapered off. Public opinion shifted. Today, many conscious animal lovers decline to wear leather, snakeskin, and even wool.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>One material has received less backlash: down. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Down feathers are a popular filler in outdoor clothing and bedding. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">People rarely stop to think about the impact down use has on geese and ducks. </span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>No one needs these feathers more than the birds who they belong to.</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Down feathers often come from geese and ducks who spend their lives in commercial warehouses. These animals are unable to express any natural behaviors. Farmed ducks and geese are typically deprived of access to swimming water, which is essential to their wellbeing and health. A life without water can lead to painful foot issues as well as respiratory problems. It is standard practice to deprive animals on farms of veterinary care. It is believed that if veterinary costs outweigh an animal’s market value, it simply doesn’t make financial sense to pay for it. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Down feathers are a result of either painful live plucking, or slaughter. On farms around the world, these birds spend miserable lives indoors. They endure cycle after cycle of painful live plucking to yield maximum profit. Those who are slaughtered will suffer during the frightening trip on a crowded slaughterhouse truck. In the United States, birds are not included in the Humane Slaughter Act. This means it is completely legal for the animals to have their throats slit while fully conscious. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">All that suffering for a puffy jacket?</span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But it doesn’t have to be this way. </span><b>Luckily, there are other options.</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>There are many sustainable alternatives to down. Milkweed floss, bamboo fiber, and recycled synthetics are a few examples. Outdoor-wear company Patagonia has been researching the development of a new down alternative called </b><b><i>Plumefill.</i></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We’re asking our supporters to ditch down, and ask outdoor-wear company Patagonia to do the same! For years, Patagonia has been a leader in ethical business practices and sustainable products. Recently, the entire company, valued at $3 billion, was donated to combatting the climate crisis. </span><b>Sadly, Patagonia has not put the value of </b><b>animals&#8217; lives</b><b> ahead of using down in their products. </b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s true that Patagonia’s standards for down sourcing are higher than most. Anti live-plucking and anti force-feeding policies are supposed to reduce animal suffering. But at the end of the day, animals are still being slaughtered.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Does making an animal suffer less justify taking their life? </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our work as a sanctuary has led us to believe that animals’ lives have inherent value. Killing animals should be avoided wherever possible. </span><b>We believe that their lives are not ours to take.</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Join us in kindly asking Patagonia to continue to be an industry leader. The next leap for this company should be replacing all new down products with sustainable, plant-based or recycled alternatives. <a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy">Click here to take action and ask Patagonia to ditch down!</a></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/animal-place-asks-patagonia-to-ditch-down/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Encourage your local animal shelter to extend compassion to all animals</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/encourage-your-local-animal-shelter-to-extend-compassion-to-all-animals/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=encourage-your-local-animal-shelter-to-extend-compassion-to-all-animals</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/encourage-your-local-animal-shelter-to-extend-compassion-to-all-animals/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 18:40:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10730</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Crystal Kozlak, Food for Thought Program Manager &#160; Have you ever seen an animal shelter host a barbecue or pig roast? Many shelters serve animals to raise funds for animals. Their mission may focus on cats and dogs, but they do not consider their impact on farmed animals.  &#160; Animal Place&#8217;s Food for Thought [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">By Crystal Kozlak, Food for Thought Program Manager</span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Have you ever seen an animal shelter host a barbecue or pig roast? Many shelters serve animals to raise funds for animals. Their mission may focus on cats and dogs, but they do not consider their impact on farmed animals. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place&#8217;s Food for Thought Program seeks to bridge the gap between the animals we love and the animals killed for food. We ask animal welfare organizations to broaden their circle of compassion. We encourage them to adopt a policy to serve fully vegan or vegetarian food at their events. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you know someone who is involved in animal advocacy, sheltering, or rescue? The following thoughts are valuable to consider!</span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-10731 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-1-300x152.jpeg" alt="" width="381" height="193" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-1-300x152.jpeg 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-1.jpeg 512w" sizes="(max-width: 381px) 100vw, 381px" /></p>
<p><b>COMPANION VS. FARMED ANIMALS </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animals raised for food are no different from the animals with whom we share our homes. Just like cats and dogs, farmed animals are individuals with their own personalities. They have the capacity to feel happiness and they want to avoid fear and pain.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many people have rabbits, chickens, pot-bellied pigs, goats, and other species as companions. If any of these animals came into your shelter, you would provide them with the same level of care as a cat or dog. As a rescue organization, where do you draw the line between those you love and those on the dinner plate at events?</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>ANIMAL FARMING </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Farmed animals suffer in the food industry. In the meat industry, they are confined in small cages or large sheds with thousands of animals. They cannot move around freely or perform their natural behaviors. Farmers slaughter the animals at a young age. Dogs experience the same fate in certain Asian and African countries. People don’t eat dogs in the Western society. Animal welfare organizations work hard to rescue and protect dogs. Why are we comfortable eating other species?  </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the egg industry, chickens are debeaked. Debeaking is a process where farmers cut off the tips of a chicken&#8217;s beak with a hot metal blade. They do this to prevent chickens from pecking the farmers and the other chickens. They are not given any pain relief for this procedure. It is extremely painful and chickens will feel phantom pain for the rest of their lives. Declawed cats experience similar phantom pain. Animal welfare organizations advocate against declawing cats. They should avoid supporting the egg industry too. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In the dairy industry, female cows must give birth to produce milk. Once a cow gives birth, farmers take away her baby. The farmers don’t want the calf drinking her milk because it’s meant for human consumption. If the calf is female, she will go back into the same dairy system as her mom. If the baby calf is male, he is unwanted because he won&#8217;t be able to produce milk. Farmers slaughter male calves for veal at 18 weeks old. A female cow will be pregnant for about 5-6 times before they are slaughtered. Female dogs in puppy mills have a similar experience. Animal welfare organizations promote rescue instead of the breeding of animals. Your organization can extend your mission of compassion by boycotting the dairy industry.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This is a small fraction of the cruel practices farmed animals face. To learn more, please visit </span><a href="http://www.animalplace.org/museum/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place’s Virtual Museum</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-10732 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-2-200x300.png" alt="" width="271" height="407" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-2-200x300.png 200w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-2-300x450.png 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-2.png 341w" sizes="(max-width: 271px) 100vw, 271px" /></p>
<p><b>ADOPT A VEGAN OR VEGETARIAN MENU POLICY</b></p>
<p><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place’s Food for Thought Program</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> helps nonprofit organizations extend their compassion to all animals by adopting a vegan or vegetarian menu policy. This is a written, board-approved policy. It states your organization will only serve vegan or vegetarian foods at your events. Adopting a vegan or vegetarian menu policy aligns your menu with your mission of saving animal lives. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Here are a few </span><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/why-adopt-a-policy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">reasons to adopt a policy</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">:  </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Be a humane leader in the rescue community.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Our society expects animal protection organizations to adopt policies that do not support animal suffering.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>All animals deserve compassion. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">If a farmed animal came into your organization, you would provide them with the same level of care as dogs and cats. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Show dedication to saving lives.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Three million dogs and cats are killed in shelters across the US annually, yet more than 55 billion land and sea animals are killed for food each year. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Practice responsible donation use. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using donated money to buy only vegan foods for events is responsible and ethically consistent. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Protect the Environment.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Animal farming is one of the leading causes of climate change and environmental destruction.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>HOW TO ADOPT A POLICY </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Adopting a vegan or vegetarian menu policy is easy! Follow these </span><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/how-to-adopt-a-policy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">simple steps</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> and submit your policy. If you need help, please </span><a href="mailto:foodforthought@animalplace.org"><span style="font-weight: 400;">contact us</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. We’d be happy to write a custom policy for your organization.  </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Read our </span><a href="https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5ca7eb83840b162f614aa309/t/612808824a3b8e40ddb0d712/1630013578077/2021+FFT+Resource+PDF.pdf"><span style="font-weight: 400;">virtual brochure</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for answers to frequently asked questions.  </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-10733 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-3-300x200.jpeg" alt="" width="368" height="245" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-3-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-3-150x100.jpeg 150w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-3.jpeg 512w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px" /></p>
<p><b>VEGAN EVENT IDEAS</b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you need inspiration for what to serve at your next vegan event? We offer </span><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/menus"><span style="font-weight: 400;">sample event menus</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. A fun fundraiser you can do is a “Spayghetti and No Balls” for spay and neuter fundraising. Taco bars can easily be made vegan with beans, rice, grilled veggies, and salsas. For BBQ’s, you can cook up veggie burgers and grilled veggies or corn. Hosting a bake sale? Choose an egg alternative and plant-based milk for delicious vegan desserts. </span></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-10734 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-4-300x201.png" alt="" width="404" height="271" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-4-300x201.png 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-4-150x100.png 150w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/FFT-4.png 512w" sizes="(max-width: 404px) 100vw, 404px" /></p>
<p><b>GRANT OPPORTUNITIES </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Food for Thought offers several grant opportunities to help your organization adopt a vegan or vegetarian menu policy: </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/vegan-event-grant"><b>Vegan Event Grant</b></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Does your organization want to try a fully vegan event? With the Vegan Event Grant, we’ll reimburse the food expenses up to $1,000 for your organization’s first fully vegan event. This grant is perfect for organizations that are considering adopting a policy but have some concerns. It’s a great opportunity to try out a fully vegan event and see how your supporters respond.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">You may combine the Vegan Event Grant with the screening of the award-winning film </span><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/lastpig"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Last Pig</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> for the ultimate event!</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/vegan-ticket-subsidy-grant"><b>Vegan Ticket Subsidy Grant</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">With the Vegan Ticket Subsidy Grant, you&#8217;ll host an event where attendees can purchase their meal option ahead of time. Charge your attendees half-price for the vegan meal option and we’ll cover the other half up to $1,000! Hosting a gala is a perfect example of how you can use this grant.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/policy-grant"><b>Policy Grant</b></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Policy Grant is a one-time gift for organizations that adopt a new board-approved vegan or vegetarian menu policy. We offer $1,000 for a vegan menu policy or $250 for a vegetarian menu policy.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/encourage-your-local-animal-shelter-to-extend-compassion-to-all-animals/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>VICTORY: Cruel wild cow milking BANNED in Alameda County!</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/victory-cruel-wild-cow-milking-banned-in-alameda-county/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=victory-cruel-wild-cow-milking-banned-in-alameda-county</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/victory-cruel-wild-cow-milking-banned-in-alameda-county/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 22:18:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Mother cows like Honey and Babe suffered for years for “wild cow milking” at the Rowell Ranch Rodeo. One nursing mother even broke her neck and had to be euthanized. Honey and Babe say “thank you” for standing up for mothers like them! &#160; In early September, we reached out with a plea for help. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-9768 aligncenter" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="527" height="351" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o-300x200.jpg 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o-150x100.jpg 150w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o-768x512.jpg 768w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/50957570631_59b2f89032_o.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 527px) 100vw, 527px" /></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Mother cows like Honey and Babe suffered for years for “wild cow milking” at the Rowell Ranch Rodeo. One nursing mother even broke her neck and had to be euthanized. Honey and Babe say “thank you” for standing up for mothers like them!</span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>In early September, we reached out with a plea for help.</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> A rodeo in Alameda County was practicing a cruel event known as “wild cow milking”. “Meat breed” cows, that were not used to being handled by humans, were being turned out into an arena where they were met with unspeakable cruelty. The nursing mother cows were chased on horseback, placed in a headlock, and forcibly milked by a team of cowboys. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">The crowds thought this was funny. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Despite the terrified animals, the event always attracted crowds of cheering, laughing fans. This event has gone on for years. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>When the Alameda County Board of Supervisors announced a hearing to ban this event, we knew what we had to do. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">There was no allowing this opportunity to slip away. We reached out to you with an ask: send an email to the board of supervisors in support of the ban.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">And you delivered! </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">3,000 people stepped up and raised their voices. Our message was loud and clear: </span><b>leave the animals alone. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s not every day that our advocacy pays off. But this time, it did. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>This week the Alameda County Board of Supervisors voted </b><b>unanimously</b><b> to ban wild cow milking. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">We were shocked and delighted by the news!</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Thank you from the bottom of our hearts to everyone who participated in this campaign. </span><b>And it doesn’t end here. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">By signing up for our</span><a href="http://go.pardot.com/l/345601/2022-02-03/265p9qk"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> advocacy alerts</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">, you’ll be the first to know when an issue like this arises. </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Together, we can continue to change the world for animals. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">One small victory at a time! </span></i><b>Can we count you in?</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Our deepest gratitude goes out to Eric Mills of </span></i><a href="https://www.actionforanimals-oakland.com/"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Oakland-based Action for Animals</span></i></a><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Eric has dedicated his entire life to fighting rodeo cruelty. He led the way for this campaign and continues to break ground for animals abused for entertainment.</span></i></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/victory-cruel-wild-cow-milking-banned-in-alameda-county/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Full-time Animal Caregiver</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/full-time-animal-caregiver/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=full-time-animal-caregiver</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/full-time-animal-caregiver/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2022 23:32:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10696</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Job Description: The full-time Animal Caregiver assists in the care of 350 animals (pigs, chickens, cows, turkeys, sheep, goats, rabbits, donkeys) at the sanctuary under supervision of the Animal Care Director. Animal Caregivers are responsible for the cleaning, feeding, and medical care of the animals. See below for specific responsibilities and duties. Immediate Supervisor: Animal [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Job Description: The full-time Animal Caregiver assists in the care of 350 animals (pigs, chickens, cows, turkeys, sheep, goats, rabbits, donkeys) at the sanctuary under supervision of the Animal Care Director. Animal Caregivers are responsible for the cleaning, feeding, and medical care of the animals. See below for specific responsibilities and duties.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Immediate Supervisor: Animal Care Director</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Qualifications</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Passionate about working for and with farmed animals</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Keen interest in the animal welfare/rights movement is encouraged</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Good animal behavior and observation skills</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Strong communication and listening skills</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Able to follow detailed instructions and meet time sensitive demands</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Able to learn and process new information quickly</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Team player and self motivator</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Follows directions</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Reliable and dependable</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Able to work outdoors in all weather conditions, including cold/wet weather (average low is 35F) and hot summers (average high is 95-100F)</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Able to lift 40-50 pounds and perform strenuous/manual labor</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Work well with a variety of people</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Committed to Animal Place’s mission and a desire to be a part of the Animal Place family</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Willing to work on weekend/holidays/varying shift times</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Valid driver’s license and good driving record (subject to verification)</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Vegan diet preferred</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Job Duties</span></p>
<ul>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Animal feeding/watering and maintaining animal feed schedules</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Daily animal health care and maintaining treatment records</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Daily cleaning duties and maintaining the shelter areas</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Aiding with weekly health checks</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Assisting with veterinary visits and setting up treatment protocols</span></li>
<li><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Completing shelter projects as assigned</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Hours/Days: 40 hours/week, days vary; schedule subject to change at any time, required to work weekends and most holidays.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Salary: $20/hour</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Benefits: Health care coverage after 3-month probation period, 403(b) plan w/ match, paid vacation and holiday</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Start Date: Immediate</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">How to Apply: Send cover letter and resume to Humanresources @ animalplace.org or apply here: Full-Time Animal Caregiver | Animal Place.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place is fully committed to equal employment opportunity, and company policy prohibits unlawful discrimination based on race, color, creed, sex, gender, religion, registered domestic partner status, sexual orientation, marital status, age, national origin, physical or mental disability, medical condition, ancestry, or any other consideration made unlawful by federal, state, or local laws.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/full-time-animal-caregiver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Chance to Stop Rodeo Suffering</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/a-chance-to-stop-rodeo-suffering/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=a-chance-to-stop-rodeo-suffering</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/a-chance-to-stop-rodeo-suffering/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 22:04:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10670</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When she enters the arena, she circles the outskirts in an attempt to escape. The black Angus cow is already confused and exhausted. It’s a hot and dusty day. The crowd’s cheers are deafening to her sensitive ears. She’s never left the ranch she was born on, and she’s suddenly all alone in the wide [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When she enters the arena, she circles the outskirts in an attempt to escape. </span><b>The black Angus cow is already confused and exhausted. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">It’s a hot and dusty day. The crowd’s cheers are deafening to her sensitive ears. She’s never left the ranch she was born on, and she’s suddenly all alone in the wide open. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Then the cowboy on horseback enters. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">She picks up the pace as she realizes he’s chasing her. Humans rarely try to handle her at home. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">What’s going on?</span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">That’s when the rope is thrown around her neck. She skids to an abrupt stop. As the noose tightens around her throat, she calls out in pain and fear. Her terror escalates to unimaginable levels. She begins to open-mouth pant, something cows only do under extreme stress. Suddenly, she collapses. Instead of being helped to her feet, she’s put in a headlock position.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">But this cow has some fight left in her. </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">She rises to her feet and begins to backpedal, spin and buck. She tosses her head in violent anger. The crowd only cheers louder. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Can they not see her suffering? </span></i><b>This isn’t a fair fight. </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">She’s outnumbered. And she’s going to lose.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This isn’t a made-up or exaggerated scenario.</span><b> This is a description of a real video from the Rowell Ranch Rodeo in May of 2022.</b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The event described is called “wild cow milking”. It’s as unnecessary as it sounds. </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">And it’s all in the name of fun and entertainment for the humans watching.</span></i></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Now is the time to take action to end this atrocious cruelty. </b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Amendments have been proposed to the Alameda County Rodeo Ordinance to shut down rodeo cruelty. The proposed amendments would end the wild cow milking event, as well as ban tie-down calf roping and prohibit the use of flank straps and spurs in rodeos. </span><b><i>We only have until September 20th to make our voices heard! </i></b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Join us in calling on the Alameda County Board of Supervisors to support the proposed amendments. We’ve put together a sample email that will make it easy for you to speak out. </span><a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Click here to learn more and send your email now.</span> </a><b>Don’t hesitate. </b></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b><i>These animals need us now more than ever before!</i></b></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/a-chance-to-stop-rodeo-suffering/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Veterinarian Shares her Thoughts on Cruel &#8220;Wild Cow Milking&#8221;</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/veterinarian-shares-her-thoughts-on-cruel-wild-cow-milking/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=veterinarian-shares-her-thoughts-on-cruel-wild-cow-milking</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/veterinarian-shares-her-thoughts-on-cruel-wild-cow-milking/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 17:22:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10666</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Photo: Wild cow milking event in Texas. This week, we launched a campaign to combat rodeo cruelty in California. The Rowell Ranch Rodeo in Alameda County is infamous for an incredibly cruel event called “wild cow milking”.  The practice involves chasing down an unhandled and terrified cow on horseback, roping her, forcing her into a headlock [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class=" wp-image-10660 alignnone" src="http://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Wild-Cow-Milking-300x180.jpg" alt="" width="374" height="224" srcset="https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Wild-Cow-Milking-300x180.jpg 300w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Wild-Cow-Milking-1024x614.jpg 1024w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Wild-Cow-Milking-768x461.jpg 768w, https://animalplace.org/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/Wild-Cow-Milking.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px" /></p>
<p><em>Photo: Wild cow milking event in Texas.</em></p>
<p><strong>This week, we launched a <a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy">campaign</a> to combat rodeo cruelty in California.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Rowell Ranch Rodeo in Alameda County is infamous for an incredibly cruel event called “wild cow milking”.  The practice involves chasing down an unhandled and terrified cow on horseback, roping her, forcing her into a headlock position, and milking her before a screaming audience. A cow broke her neck and was killed in this exact event in 2014. We&#8217;ve been raising our voices against this cruelty for years.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">But for the very first time, there is hope for these animals. The Alameda County Board of Supervisors is considering a ban on the wild cow milking event as well as tie-down calf roping, flank straps and spurs in rodeos. We only have until September 20 to make our voices heard. You can take action and share your thoughts with the supervisors by sending an email </span><a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy"><span style="font-weight: 400;">here</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">!</span></p>
<p><strong>Featured below is a letter written to the Alameda County Board of Supervisors by Dr. Peggy W Larson, DVM MS JD. Dr. Larson is an experienced large animal veterinarian and has seen firsthand the harm that rodeos inflict on animals. Read her thoughts here:</strong></p>
<p><em>Animals should not be injured or killed for entertainment and that is what rodeo is. It bears no resemblance to ranching. I grew up on a cattle ranch in North Dakota and spent 8 years as a ranch <span class="mark30yf0xapx" data-markjs="true" data-ogac="" data-ogab="" data-ogsc="" data-ogsb="">vet</span>erinarian there. My ranch clients did not ride bulls, speed rope calves or make their expensive horses buck. Rodeo is not American &#8220;tradition&#8221;.    </em></p>
<p><em>As a former bareback bronc rider, pathologist and large animal <span class="mark30yf0xapx" data-markjs="true" data-ogac="" data-ogab="" data-ogsc="" data-ogsb="">vet</span>erinarian, I have both the experience and autopsy proof that rodeo injures and kills animals. Dr. Robert Bay from Colorado autopsied roping calves and found hemorrhages, torn muscles, torn ligaments, damage to the trachea, damage to the throat and damage to the thyroid. These calves never get a chance to heal before they are used again. Meat inspectors processing rodeo animals found broken bones, ruptured internal organs, massive amounts of blood in the abdomen from ruptured blood vessels and damage to the ligamentum nuchae that holds the neck to the rest of the spinal column.</em></p>
<p><em>Animals and humans share the same pain and fear centers in the brain. The fear center is the amygdala. The pain centers are the pre-frontal cortex and the hypothalamus. Animals feel pain and fear the same as humans!</em></p>
<p><em>As a former criminal lawyer, children that are exposed to and participate in animal abuse often grow up to abuse humans. I have seen children cry at rodeos when the calves are roped and slammed to the ground. It is time for this archaic rodeo &#8220;entertainment&#8221;  to end.</em></p>
<p>Peggy W Larson, DVM MS JD</p>
<p><strong>Want to help us do everything in our power to bring this cruelty to an end? </strong><a href="http://animalplace.org/advocacy">Submit your email now</a> and let your thoughts be heard. For greater weight, take a moment to personalize the email. Do you have friends and family who care about animals? Share our campaign far and wide to amplify your impact. <strong>Spread the word about this rare opportunity to make a change for animals abused for entertainment!</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/veterinarian-shares-her-thoughts-on-cruel-wild-cow-milking/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>West Coast Food for Thought Coordinator</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/west-coast-food-for-thought-coordinator/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=west-coast-food-for-thought-coordinator</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/west-coast-food-for-thought-coordinator/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 22:14:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10651</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Organization Description: Animal Place is a nonprofit animal rights organization promoting the complete protection of farmed animals and veganism. We operate several facilities throughout California. Our 600-acre sanctuary in Grass Valley, CA, serves as a permanent safe haven for farmed animals as well as an education and advocacy center. In conjunction with the sanctuary, Grass [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>Organization Description:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Animal Place is a nonprofit animal rights organization promoting the complete protection of farmed animals and veganism. We operate several facilities throughout California. Our 600-acre sanctuary in Grass Valley, CA, serves as a permanent safe haven for farmed animals as well as an education and advocacy center. In conjunction with the sanctuary, Grass Valley is also home to our 15-acre residential internship property and a 7-acre onsite guest house. The Rescue &amp; Adoption Center is situated on 12-acres in Petaluma, CA, and provides a temporary home for adoptable farmed animals with a special emphasis on chickens from the egg industry. If you are unfamiliar with Animal Place, visit our website at </span><a href="http://www.animalplace.org/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.animalplace.org</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> before applying.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Food for Thought Program Description: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place’s Food for Thought Program (FFT) encourages nonprofit animal welfare organizations to extend their compassion to all animals by adopting a vegan or vegetarian menu policy. The policy states that organizational funds will only be spent on vegan or vegetarian foods at their sponsored events and fundraisers. Adopting a policy aligns an organization’s menu with their mission of saving animal lives. The program is run by a remote team of part-time Coordinators located throughout the United States. Please thoroughly review the program website before applying: </span><a href="http://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><b>Job Status: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Part-time employee, 20hr/week, $15-$16 per hour depending on experience, vacation and sick time accrued hourly</span></p>
<p><b>Supervision: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Reports to Food for Thought Campaign Manager</span></p>
<p><b>Location: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Remote, must live in a state in the West Coast Region: CA, OR, WA</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><b>Job Description:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Food for Thought Coordinators are responsible for establishing and expanding the Food for Thought Program within their assigned region. Coordinators encourage and assist relevant nonprofits in adopting a vegan or vegetarian menu policy, develop content for the FFT website and social media, and network with animal welfare organizations at conferences and other events.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><b>Main Job Tasks and Responsibilities</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Develop and maintain a database of potential participating organizations</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Maintain clear, organized records within a shared Google Drive and Salesforce account;  follow standardized rules of record-keeping and up to date information</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Conduct research on target organizations&#8217; staff, board members, supporters, and relevant internal policies</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Introduce and present the FFT Program to appropriate staff members at organizations by email, telephone, video calls and occasionally in person</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Professionally and convincingly discuss veganism and animal rights to organizations in service of the FFT Program</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel, table, and speak on behalf of the program at relevant festivals, conventions, and conferences</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Travel to the annual FFT staff retreat</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Set and meet outreach goals and deadlines</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Develop content for the FFT website, quarterly e-newletter, and Animal Place social media that furthers the goals of the program</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Co-manage FFT social media accounts</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Teleconference weekly with Campaign Manager and a team of 2 other Coordinators</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Work collaboratively on program materials and strategic planning</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Lead projects and take direction from other Coordinators on projects</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understand Animal Place&#8217;s policies and positions regarding key animal protection issues; appropriately and accurately represent those policies when interacting with the public or otherwise representing Animal Place</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Perform other duties and functions as assigned by Campaign Manager</span></li>
</ul>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><b>Qualifications</b></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Able to work independently and as part of a small team with regular communication and rotating project-based leadership</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Comfortable with collaborative teamwork and editing by committee </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Excellent organizational skills: can set priorities, develop a work schedule, monitor progress towards goals, and track activities</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Excellent oral and written communication skills: able to communicate effectively with colleagues and senior management, able to skillfully represent the program to other nonprofit professionals in a variety of settings</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Comfortable leading difficult conversations with prospective program participants</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Understand the needs and concerns of animal groups</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Computer and social media savvy; experience with Google Drive, SquareSpace, Salesforce, Asana, Slack, Facebook, Instagram, Pardot or other email marketing software is essential.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Flexible schedule to accommodate travel to out-of-state conferences (2-4 per year) and the annual staff retreat</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">A personal computer and phone are needed with consistent and reliable internet access/phone service</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nonprofit, campaign or advocacy experience preferred</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Bachelor&#8217;s degree preferred</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Passionate about expanding veganism</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ready to help change attitudes and behaviors of others to move our world towards kindness and compassion for all</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">
<p></span></li>
</ul>
<p><b>How to apply:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Send your résumé and cover letter with the subject line: FFT West Coast Coordinator to </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">humanresources@animalplace.org</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Please thoroughly review the FFT website before applying: </span><a href="https://www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">www.foodforthoughtcampaign.org</span></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Animal Place is fully committed to equal employment opportunity, and company policy prohibits unlawful discrimination based on race, color, creed, sex, gender, religion, registered domestic partner status, sexual orientation, marital status, age, national origin, physical or mental disability, medical condition, ancestry, or any other consideration made unlawful by federal, state, or local laws.</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/west-coast-food-for-thought-coordinator/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Plant-based and no Time to Waste</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/easyvegan/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=easyvegan</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/easyvegan/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2022 08:00:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10631</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We understand it can feel like there are never enough hours in the day. Between making time for yourself, work, your family, and responsibilities, it’s easy for nutrition to fall through the cracks. If you’re looking to save time in the long run, we recommend meal prep. With a little work, you save time, money, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We understand it can feel like there are never enough hours in the day. Between making time for yourself, work, your family, and responsibilities, it’s easy for nutrition to fall through the cracks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re looking to save time in the long run, we recommend meal prep. With a little work, you save time, money, and some sanity!</span></p>
<p><strong>Here are a few tricks to make it as seamless as possible:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep it simple. Start with less ingredients and follow one pot recipes.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Cold meals are less work and easy for on the go!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Plan your meals before grocery shopping. Or prepare and portion ingredients to make them easier to throw together the morning of.</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Give yourself breaks. You don’t need to prep it all in one day. </span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you’re on a budget, frozen, seasonal, in-house brands, and bulk are the way to go!</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Make it fun! Throw on some music, ask a loved one to join, or binge your favorite show to make it feel like less work.</span></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>A nutritional and timely balanced lifestyle is more accessible than ever.  Here are a few favorite recipes that you can prepare in bulk and plan ahead of time.</strong></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A meal you can eat hot or cold &#8211; </span><a href="https://nutriciously.com/vegan-pesto-pasta/"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Nutritiously </span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Easy Vegan Pesto Pasta</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Switching out veggies, grains or dressings can easily spice this salad up &#8211; </span><a href="https://www.loveandlemons.com/orzo-salad/"><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Love and Lemons</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Orzo Salad </span></a></p>
<p>A flavorful and nutritious dish straight from Louisiana- <a href="https://monkeyandmekitchenadventures.com/healthy-vegan-jambalaya/"><em>Monkey and Me Kitchen Adventures </em>Jambalaya</a></p>
<p>Sweet, spicy, protein packed curry with budget-friendly ingredients- <em><a href="https://rainbowplantlife.com/vegan-red-lentil-curry/">Rainbow Plant Life Red Lentil Curry</a></em></p>
<p>Flavorful quinoa based dish with latin spices and an easy clean-up &#8211; <a href="https://gatheringdreams.com/mexican-quinoa/"><em>Gathering Dreams One-Pan Mexican Quinoa</em></a></p>
<p><strong>Pro Tip: Every day you keep an animal off your plate saves 1 life, 1,100 gallons of water, 40 pounds of grain, 30 sq ft of forest, and 20 lbs CO2.</strong></p>
<p><em><strong>What are your favorite plant-based dishes to cook in bulk? Drop a comment here to help out newer vegans with meal ideas!</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: right;"><em>Written by Membership Coordinator Stevie Walsh</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/easyvegan/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Rescue &#038; Adoptions Center Manager (Petaluma)</title>
		<link>https://animalplace.org/rescue-adoptions-center-manager-petaluma/?utm_source=rss&#038;utm_medium=rss&#038;utm_campaign=rescue-adoptions-center-manager-petaluma</link>
					<comments>https://animalplace.org/rescue-adoptions-center-manager-petaluma/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Chelsea Pinkham]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 21:09:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://animalplace.org/?p=10633</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Position: Manager of Rescue &#38; Adoption Center Location: Animal Place’s Rescue &#38; Adoption Center, Petaluma, CA About Animal Place: We are an animal rights organization promoting the protection of farmed animals and a vegan lifestyle. Our main sanctuary is in Grass Valley, CA. The Rescue &#38; Adoption Center is in Petaluma, CA. At our Adoption [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><b>Position: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Manage</span>r <span style="font-weight: 400;">of Rescue &amp; Adoption Center</span></p>
<p><b>Location:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Animal Place’s Rescue &amp; Adoption Center, Petaluma, CA</span></p>
<p><b>About Animal Place</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: We are an animal rights organization promoting the protection of farmed animals and a vegan lifestyle. Our main sanctuary is in Grass Valley, CA. The Rescue &amp; Adoption Center is in Petaluma, CA. At our Adoption Center we care for adoptable farmed animals, with a special emphasis on chickens from the egg industry. We started large-scale hen rescues in 2010. Since then, we have saved more than 30,000 animals; Most are hens rescued from egg farms but we also have saved turkeys, sheep, goats, llamas, and pigs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you are unfamiliar with Animal Place, please visit our website before applying at</span><a href="http://www.animalplace.org/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> www.animalplace.org</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><b>Job Title: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Manager of Rescue &amp; Adoption Center</span></p>
<p><b>Supervisor:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Animal Care Director, Hannah Beins (Grass Valley)</span></p>
<p><b>Is this your dream job? Answer the questions below to find out!</b></p>
<ol>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you love being around animals?</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you want to make a difference in this world by helping rescued animals find their forever homes?</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you like working outside but also balanced with indoor work?</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you enjoy speaking with the public?</span></li>
<li style="font-weight: 400;" aria-level="1"><span style="font-weight: 400;">If you answered yes to all, continue on and learn more about the job!</span></li>
</ol>
<p><b>Job Description: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Oversee the care of rescued animals including up to 1,500 rescued hens at a time. There are employees, volunteers and interns to supervise and adopters and donors to engage with. Additionally, the manager is responsible for ensuring the beautiful 12-acre property is well-maintained and managed.</span></p>
<p><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">Note: A one-month paid training period at the Grass Valley sanctuary is required. We provide you with housing next door to the sanctuary.</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>
<p><b>What we are looking for in a candidate </b></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Someone who enjoys and is skilled in supervising staff and volunteers &#8211; it’s a must for this position! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Have you worked with farmed animals before? Previous experience is preferred! </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you consider yourself outgoing, social, and do you enjoy working with others? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you have excellent communication and conflict resolution skills?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you like working both inside and outside? </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Are you able to work outdoors in all weather conditions?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Can you lift up to 40 pounds and perform manual labor?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Managing a sanctuary is fun but can you also follow instructions and meet deadlines?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">It goes without saying, but you must be committed to Animal Place’s mission.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Do you have a driver’s license and good driving record? It’s required (subject to verification).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Are you comfortable driving large vans and towing stock trailers?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Last, but not least, practicing a vegan lifestyle on sanctuary grounds is required!</span></p>
<p><b>The Four Main Components of the job</b></p>
<ol>
<li><b><i></i></b> <b><i>Animal Care</i></b></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Oversee and help with barn cleaning duties and maintaining sanctuary</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Train and supervise staff and volunteers</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Maintain daily animal health care and treatment records</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Schedule and supervise health checks, of rescued hens or other animals</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Transport animals to and from veterinary appointments</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Assist with rescues</span></p>
<ol start="2">
<li><b><i></i></b> <b><i>Administrative</i></b></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Cultivate relationship with farmers and coordinate the rescues </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Develop and maintain animal care schedules, adoptions, rescues with your boss</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Must be organized to keep up with a calendar of work for self and staff</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Work with Adoption Coordinator to schedule adoptions and aid adopters with the process </span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">How do you feel about education? Lead tours, volunteer orientations, and chicken care classes</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Set up veterinary visits, as needed</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Communicate with Grass Valley staff about health, adoption status, population</span></p>
<ol start="3">
<li><b><i></i></b> <b><i>Property Management</i></b></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Keep the sanctuary sparkling! Be proud of the beautiful property you work at</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Schedule regular maintenance and repairs for vehicles</span></p>
<ol start="4">
<li><b><i></i></b> <b><i>Live-In Responsibilities</i></b></li>
</ol>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Must be flexible! Sometimes you have to work late-night shifts to keep animals safe</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">&#8211;</span> <span style="font-weight: 400;">Living onsite is awesome, but it does entail being on-call (onsite) a few days a week</span></p>
<p><b>Hours/Days:</b><span style="font-weight: 400;"> 40 hours/week, weekends and some holidays required. Days off are subject to change at any time.</span></p>
<p><b>Salary: </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">18-20$/hr DOE</span></p>
<p><b>Benefits</b><span style="font-weight: 400;">: We have excellent health insurance that we pay 100% after 3-month probation. Two weeks vacation and six 6 paid holidays. You can join our 403(b) retirement plan and after one year Animal Place will match up to 3% of your salary. Oh, and a huge perk is free housing, including utilities. We welcome companion animals but, of course, subject to approval from the Animal Care Director.</span></p>
<p><b>Do You Want to Apply?  </b><span style="font-weight: 400;">Email us a cover letter and resume to </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">humanresources@animalplace.org</span><span style="font-weight: 400;">. Please allow 1-2 weeks for processing. Our apologies, but we cannot accept faxes.</span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://animalplace.org/rescue-adoptions-center-manager-petaluma/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
