<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>10,000 Birds</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.10000birds.com/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.10000birds.com</link>
	<description>Birding, blogging, conservation, and commentary</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2023 06:47:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>The Biggest Urban Pygmy Cormorant Roost is Finally Protected!!</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/the-biggest-urban-pygmy-cormorant-roost-is-finally-protected.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/the-biggest-urban-pygmy-cormorant-roost-is-finally-protected.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dragan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 12:00:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Destinations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Belgrade]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[city birds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cormorants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Pygmy Cormorant]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Serbia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Urban Birding]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150686</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It all started during the icy February of 1996. The night temperatures in Belgrade, Serbia, were already below minus 10 Celsius / 14 degrees Fahrenheit for two weeks. Everything was frozen solid and pack ice was floating down the Danube. Hiding from the elements at the riverbank, I was sitting in a Yugo and staring at the murky sky. Whenever the windscreen got frozen, I could not afford to turn the engine on due to petrol shortages (during the UN embargo on the import of fuel to the former Yugoslavia), so I would turn on a mini camping gas stove to defrost the windows and warm up my cocoon, keeping one eye at the sky and the other at the flames, to make sure they do not catch the seat. What was I doing there? Back in those days, Pygmy Cormorants Microcarbo pygmeus were considered Vulnerable by the IUCN Red List and were quite uncommon, having just returned to the city after half a century of absence. Up to the mid-20th century, Pygmy Cormorant was a common breeding species of wetlands around Belgrade until most wetlands were drained and the birds were lost, at one moment – from the entire territory of Serbia. With the construction of the huge Iron Gates dam on the Danube, the birds returned to breed in newly flooded river islands. And in the late 1980s they returned to Belgrade, too, but only to overwinter within the city. In recent years, the overwintering population in Belgrade is around 4,000 Pygmy Cormorants, representing 2 percent of the global population and over 5 percent of the European population. One of the very first Pygmy Cormorant promotions: League for Ornithological Action organised this roost watch in December 2004. Photo Milan Obradovic. In the last few hours of daylight, Pygmy Cormorants commute from the river Danube back to their roost on the Sava River, to several willow groves by the Ada Ciganlija Island, using the rivers as the flight corridors. Therefore, you can observe them in their hundreds and thousands if you spend the last hour of the day observing the flight corridor and distinguishing distant black Pygmy Cormorant dots from other equally distant and black Rook and Jackdaw dots, all of them melting into tree crowns as the sunset thickens.The biggest threat to Pygmy Cormorants overwintering in Belgrade is urbanization of its riverbanks and destruction of remaining willow groves, which sparked the 2009 initiative by the Belgrade Land Development Public Agency, League for Ornithological Action (a local NGO) and the Institute for Nature Conservation of Serbia to protect the remaining roosting sites of this species.By both Serbian legislation and the Bern Convention on the Conservation of European Wildlife and Natural Habitats, Pygmy Cormorant is a strictly protected species. In the European Union, they are included on the Annex I of the Birds Directive and their habitats are therefore potential Natura2000 ecological network sites.For almost 20 years during which the League for Ornithological Action had been following the Pygmy Cormorant in Belgrade, the maximum number was recorded in the winter of 2007/2008, when the population counted 6,728 individuals. This shows the great importance of the Sava riverbanks, in the heart of a capital, for the conservation of biological diversity, which has an importance that transcends national borders.And after 13 years of campaigning by the League for Ornithological Action, in March 2022 the Ministry of Environmental Protection informed the public about the procedure for initiating the protection of a natural area of the third category, as the Protected Habitat &#8220;Winter Roosts of Pygmy Cormorants&#8221;. The decision to declare the &#8220;Winter Roosts of Pygmy Cormorants&#8221; as a protected area was adopted at the last session of the Belgrade City Assembly.I waited for a long time, at one stage losing all hope, but finally, 23 ha / 57 ac of this tiny reserve are off the hook for the future development plans.In the same 2022, Beljarica and the wider Danube Backwaters – another reserve that I initiated and proposed, also became protected, bringing my personal total to 1881 ha / 4648 acres of newly protected areas (mostly forests) in my city. I hope that covers my carbon footprint. Cover photo (c) Maciej Szymanski ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It all started during the icy February of 1996. The night temperatures in Belgrade, Serbia, were already below minus 10 Celsius / 14 degrees Fahrenheit for two weeks. Everything was frozen solid and pack ice was floating down the Danube. Hiding from the elements at the riverbank, I was sitting in a Yugo and staring at the murky sky. Whenever the windscreen got frozen, I could not afford to turn the engine on due to petrol shortages (during the UN embargo on the import of fuel to the former Yugoslavia), so I would turn on a mini camping gas stove to defrost the windows and warm up my cocoon, keeping one eye at the sky and the other at the flames, to make sure they do not catch the seat. What was I doing there? Back in those days, <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/the-biggest-urban-pygmy-cormorant-roost-in-the-world-decreased.htm"><strong>Pygmy Cormorants</strong></a> <em>Microcarbo pygmeus</em> were considered Vulnerable by the IUCN Red List and were quite uncommon, having just returned to the city after half a century of absence. <br /><br />Up to the mid-20th century, Pygmy Cormorant was a common breeding species of wetlands around Belgrade until most wetlands were drained and the birds were lost, at one moment – from the entire territory of Serbia. With the construction of the huge Iron Gates dam on the Danube, the birds returned to breed in newly flooded river islands. And in the late 1980s they returned to Belgrade, too, but only to overwinter within the city. In recent years, the overwintering population in Belgrade is around 4,000 Pygmy Cormorants, representing 2 percent of the global population and over 5 percent of the European population.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-150699 size-full" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n.jpg" alt="" width="720" height="482" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n.jpg 720w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n-630x422.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/148567_10150116350598065_7563695_n-345x230.jpg 345w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /><em>One of the very first Pygmy Cormorant promotions: League for Ornithological Action organised this roost watch in December 2004. Photo Milan Obradovic. </em><br /><br />In the last few hours of daylight, Pygmy Cormorants commute from the river Danube back to their roost on the Sava River, to several willow groves by the Ada Ciganlija Island, using the rivers as the flight corridors. Therefore, you can observe them in their hundreds and thousands if you spend the last hour of the day observing the flight corridor and distinguishing distant black Pygmy Cormorant dots from other equally distant and black <strong>Rook</strong> and <strong>Jackdaw</strong> dots, all of them melting into tree crowns as the sunset thickens.<br /><br /><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-150694" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca-193x300.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="466" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca-193x300.jpg 193w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca-630x979.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca-768x1194.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca-988x1536.jpg 988w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/ZS-Zimovaliste-malog-vranca.jpg 1127w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" />The biggest threat to Pygmy Cormorants overwintering in Belgrade is urbanization of its riverbanks and destruction of remaining willow groves, which sparked the 2009 initiative by the Belgrade Land Development Public Agency, League for Ornithological Action (a local NGO) and the Institute for Nature Conservation of Serbia to protect the remaining roosting sites of this species.<br /><br />By both Serbian legislation and the Bern Convention on the Conservation of European Wildlife and Natural Habitats, Pygmy Cormorant is a strictly protected species. In the European Union, they are included on the Annex I of the Birds Directive and their habitats are therefore potential Natura2000 ecological network sites.<br /><br />For almost 20 years during which the League for Ornithological Action had been following the Pygmy Cormorant in Belgrade, the maximum number was recorded in the winter of 2007/2008, when the population counted 6,728 individuals. This shows the great importance of the Sava riverbanks, in the heart of a capital, for the conservation of biological diversity, which has an importance that transcends national borders.<br /><br />And after 13 years of campaigning by the League for Ornithological Action, in March 2022 the Ministry of Environmental Protection informed the public about the procedure for initiating the protection of a natural area of the third category, as the Protected Habitat &#8220;Winter Roosts of Pygmy Cormorants&#8221;. The decision to declare the &#8220;Winter Roosts of Pygmy Cormorants&#8221; as a protected area was adopted at the last session of the Belgrade City Assembly.<br /><br />I waited for a long time, at one stage losing all hope, but finally, 23 ha / 57 ac of this tiny reserve are off the hook for the future development plans.<br /><br />In the same 2022, <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/beljarica-backwaters-are-finally-protected.htm">Beljarica and the wider Danube Backwaters</a> – another reserve that I initiated and proposed, also became protected, bringing my personal total to 1881 ha / 4648 acres of newly protected areas (mostly forests) in my city. I hope that covers my carbon footprint.</p>
<p style="text-align: right"><strong>Cover photo</strong> (c) Maciej Szymanski </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/the-biggest-urban-pygmy-cormorant-roost-is-finally-protected.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bird of the Year?</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/bird-of-the-year.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/bird-of-the-year.htm#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Faraaz Abdool]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birds]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150707</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Yes, I understand what you are thinking. How can one, in what is barely the second week of the first month of the year &#8211; even think of suggesting a Bird of the Year? Well, let me explain. I began recording my bird sightings with photographs in late 2009, and since then I have seen (or at least heard) a fair proportion of species recorded within my home country of Trinidad &#38; Tobago. The euphoria of chasing sightings lasted for only a few years, eventually giving way to my current ethos of simply putting myself in place and letting nature toss me whatever she feels I need. This enriching practice makes fortuitous sightings even more precious when they do occur. One of T&#38;T&#8217;s resident species has been taking me for a real run around since I began birding &#8211; the delicately beautiful Mangrove Cuckoo. I first caught sight of one while birding a mangrove swamp in 2012. The view was of its rich buff underside and long, spotted tail as it flew from treetop to treetop &#8211; if I say the view lasted a full second I&#8217;m being generous. The second time I saw one was late in 2020 (could be 2021, the pandemic years are a blur), where a small group of photographers were enjoying (apparently) a bird in full view. It took me a while to find it and as soon as I laid eyes on the bird it flew off, never to be seen again. As I&#8217;ve been on Tobago for the last year, many have expressed surprise that I had never photographed a Mangrove Cuckoo. After all, it was a straightforward procedure: drive to the mangrove swamps, play the call, photograph the bird, leave. I experienced this first hand while attending last year&#8217;s CBC, but because I&#8217;m motivated by feelings I didn&#8217;t consider this a true experience. Nature is an infinitely unpredictable organism and I&#8217;m happy to bird naturally. Which brings me to the happenings of yesterday morning. After an enjoyable sunrise session on the beach with several Whimbrels, Southern Lapwings (including a partially leucistic individual!), and Black-bellied Plovers, we were just packing up and finalizing arrangements for where to have breakfast. I had just switched my camera off and tossed the binoculars into the back seat when Joanne pointed out a bird that was perched almost directly overhead. Yeah, you guessed it &#8211; a Mangrove Cuckoo! Whimbrel Black-bellied Plovers are always fun to spend time with! This partially leucistic Southern Lapwing didn&#8217;t seem in the least bit ostracized by its peers. A lesson we are gradually learning. I forgot all about breakfast and tracked the bird for about twenty minutes as it foraged in the treetops, only occasionally sitting for longer than a few seconds. Most of those times it was obscured by branches, but I did manage some images I&#8217;m happy with. My arms were already shaking by the time the Mangrove Cuckoo hopped on this open branch but fortunately advancements in software now mean that I can salvage images I would&#8217;ve previously tossed. What a gorgeous bird! Given how many times I&#8217;ve missed out seeing a Mangrove Cuckoo over the years and the close calls I&#8217;ve had with the species, I&#8217;m moved to consider this as a real contender for my BOTY. Of course, a major factor in this decision rests in its status as a resident species. Will it be upstaged by another? Who knows what this year will bring?! Perhaps finally an opportunity with a Pearl Kite (don&#8217;t get me started on this), or the holy grail itself &#8211; Scaled Antpitta. 2023, you have 50 weeks, let&#8217;s see what happens!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Yes, I understand what you are thinking. How can one, in what is barely the second week of the first month of the year &#8211; even <em>think</em> of suggesting a Bird of the Year? Well, let me explain. </p>



<p>I began recording my bird sightings with photographs in late 2009, and since then I have seen (or at least heard) a fair proportion of species recorded within my home country of Trinidad &amp; Tobago. The euphoria of chasing sightings lasted for only a few years, eventually giving way to my current ethos of simply putting myself in place and letting nature toss me whatever she feels I need. This enriching practice makes fortuitous sightings even more precious when they do occur. </p>



<p>One of T&amp;T&#8217;s resident species has been taking me for a real run around since I began birding &#8211; the delicately beautiful <strong>Mangrove Cuckoo</strong>. I first caught sight of one while birding a mangrove swamp in 2012. The view was of its rich buff underside and long, spotted tail as it flew from treetop to treetop &#8211; if I say the view lasted a full second I&#8217;m being generous. The second time I saw one was late in 2020 (could be 2021, the pandemic years are a blur), where a small group of photographers were enjoying (apparently) a bird in full view. It took me a while to find it and as soon as I laid eyes on the bird it flew off, never to be seen again. </p>



<p>As I&#8217;ve been on Tobago for the last year, many have expressed surprise that I had never photographed a <strong>Mangrove Cuckoo</strong>. After all, it was a straightforward procedure: drive to the mangrove swamps, play the call, photograph the bird, leave. I experienced this first hand while attending <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.10000birds.com/cbc-in-paradise.htm" data-type="post" data-id="150268" target="_blank">last year&#8217;s CBC</a>, but because I&#8217;m motivated by feelings I didn&#8217;t consider this a <em>true</em> experience. Nature is an infinitely unpredictable organism and I&#8217;m happy to bird <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.10000birds.com/increasing-intervals.htm" data-type="post" data-id="148569" target="_blank">naturally</a>. </p>



<p>Which brings me to the happenings of yesterday morning. After an enjoyable sunrise session on the beach with several <strong>Whimbrels</strong>, <strong>Southern Lapwings</strong> (including a partially leucistic individual!), and <strong>Black-bellied Plovers</strong>, we were just packing up and finalizing arrangements for where to have breakfast. I had just switched my camera off and tossed the binoculars into the back seat when Joanne pointed out a bird that was perched almost directly overhead. Yeah, you guessed it &#8211; a <strong>Mangrove Cuckoo</strong>!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="740" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/whimbrel-9277-.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150710" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/whimbrel-9277-.jpg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/whimbrel-9277--300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/whimbrel-9277--630x630.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/whimbrel-9277--150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Whimbrel</strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="277" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-bellied-plover-9234-.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150713" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-bellied-plover-9234-.jpg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-bellied-plover-9234--300x112.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-bellied-plover-9234--630x236.jpg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Black-bellied Plovers</strong> are always fun to spend time with!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="1109" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/southern-lapwing-9220-.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150711" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/southern-lapwing-9220-.jpg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/southern-lapwing-9220--200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/southern-lapwing-9220--630x944.jpg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">This partially leucistic <strong>Southern Lapwing</strong> didn&#8217;t seem in the least bit ostracized by its peers. A lesson we are gradually learning. </p>



<p>I forgot all about breakfast and tracked the bird for about twenty minutes as it foraged in the treetops, only occasionally sitting for longer than a few seconds. Most of those times it was obscured by branches, but I did manage some images I&#8217;m happy with. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="592" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/mangrove-cuckoo-9389-.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150712" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/mangrove-cuckoo-9389-.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/mangrove-cuckoo-9389--300x240.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/mangrove-cuckoo-9389--630x504.jpeg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">My arms were already shaking by the time the <strong>Mangrove Cuckoo</strong> hopped on this open branch but fortunately advancements in software now mean that I can salvage images I would&#8217;ve previously tossed. What a gorgeous bird!</p>



<p>Given how many times I&#8217;ve missed out seeing a <strong>Mangrove Cuckoo</strong> over the years and the close calls I&#8217;ve had with the species, I&#8217;m moved to consider this as a real contender for my BOTY. Of course, a major factor in this decision rests in its status as a resident species. Will it be upstaged by another? Who knows what this year will bring?! Perhaps finally an opportunity with a <strong>Pearl Kite</strong> (don&#8217;t get me started on this), or the holy grail itself &#8211; <strong>Scaled Antpitta</strong>. 2023, you have 50 weeks, let&#8217;s see what happens!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/bird-of-the-year.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Puerto Rico&#8217;s Birds after Hurricane Maria (2023 Update)</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/puerto-ricos-birds-after-hurricane-maria.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/puerto-ricos-birds-after-hurricane-maria.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Jason Crotty]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 12:00:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Conservation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Caribbean]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CBC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Christmas Bird Count]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hurricane Irma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Hurricane Maria]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Puerto Rico]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=110915</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In September of 2017, Puerto Rico was hit by two powerful hurricanes: it was grazed by Irma and then clobbered by Maria, a Category 4 storm that cut a devastating swath across the island. The human and economic consequences were dramatic and persistent. These hurricanes prompted a personal interest in the impact of hurricanes on birds, so I did some research, which ultimately led to an article in the April 2018 issue of Birding magazine. Broadly speaking, most birds appear to survive the initial “direct” effects (e.g., high winds, rain, landslides, and flooding) of hurricanes, but are significantly impacted by the “indirect” effects (e.g., loss of food supplies and roosting sites). Immediately after hurricanes, surviving birds appear to wander in an effort to find any remaining food supplies and suitable habitat. Birds that rely on a closed canopy, mature trees, or nectar, fruits, or seeds may struggle to survive. For example, hummingbirds must find patches where there are still flowers. Species with small ranges (e.g., single island endemics) or tiny populations (e.g., endangered species) are especially vulnerable. But as the months pass, forests and other habitats regenerate and many birds return. Over the longer term, forests mature, closing hurricane-created gaps in the canopy, at least until the inevitable next hurricane. Studying the impact of hurricanes requires data from before and after the event. However, there are few long-term avian studies in the Caribbean. Much of what exists is from Puerto Rico, a U.S. territory where researchers have numerous ongoing investigations, including many studies in El Yunque National Forest. Christmas Bird Counts administered by the National Audubon Society are one source of data. CBCs have been conducted for years in several locations in Puerto Rico, utilizing consistent procedures that can provide comparable “before” and “after” data. The Fajardo CBC has been conducted since 1994. Fajardo is in the northeastern corner of Puerto Rico and the count area includes parts of El Yunque. There have been six counts since Maria: (1) December 17, 2017; (2) December 16, 2018; (3) December 15, 2019; (4) December 21, 2020; (5) and December 19, 2021; and (6) December 18, 2022. The 2017 Count The 2017 CBC was conducted just a few months after Maria and forests were still extensively defoliated, with countless felled trees and snapped branches. Some plants had started to re-sprout, but recovery was in the very early stages. Nevertheless, the 2017 CBC tallied 1,934 birds of 82 species, both of which were low counts for past CBCs (e.g., the 2016 CBC had 2,579 birds, 97 species). When corrected for search effort in the field, participant groups found 1.8 species per party hour, a value not much lower than the mean for counts of the previous 10 years and within the range of earlier counts (1.8-2.2). However, they found only 43 individual birds per hour, well below the 10-year mean of 59.6, as well as below the 10-year range (47.7-68.2). Some species experienced dramatic declines. For example, nectarivores (e.g., hummingbirds and Bananaquits) showed a significant drop, which was not surprising given the loss of flowers to high winds. Most shorebird species fell too. Surprisingly, however, a few actually increased, including Scaly-naped Pigeon, Red-legged Thrush, Puerto Rican Oriole, and Puerto Rican Tody. Others were essentially unchanged. The causes of these inconsistent results are unclear. Some birds may have had to forage more actively, causing them to be observed more frequently, even if there were fewer of them. And post-hurricane habitats themselves may lead to increased detection, as there are no leaves to obscure the birds. Moreover, because many areas lacked a canopy altogether, birds that typically spend time high in trees are forced to ground level, where they are more likely to be observed. And numerous birds may cluster around remaining food sources (e.g., Royal Palms for frugivores), increasing the probability of detection. Overall, post-hurricane CBC observers saw species at a rate slightly lower than previous counts, but far fewer birds overall. The 2018 Count By the 2018 CBC, although there were still obvious signs of structural damage in the forests, most foliage had returned. But there were still large gaps in tree canopies that had been closed before the hurricanes. The 2018 CBC tallied 2,492 birds of 87 species. Both numbers were higher than 2017, but still relatively low compared to pre-hurricane counts. When corrected for search effort, participant groups found 2.0 species per party hour, within the range of earlier counts (1.8-2.2). They found 57 individual birds per hour, consistent with the 10-year mean (59.6) and within the 10-year range (47.7-68.2). There were some exceptions. For example, most nectivore numbers continued to be low. Thus, the 2018 CBC suggested that bird populations within the count area were gradually returning to pre-hurricane levels. Indeed, the 2018 count even added two new species: Black-throated Green Warbler and Greater Flamingo. The 2019 Count In 2019, there was still structural damage in the forests, but most foliage had returned. Many canopy gaps continued, and saplings, vines, and ferns flourished in those openings. The 2019 CBC tallied 2,308 birds of 90 species, similar to 2018. When corrected for search effort, 2.3 species per party hour were detected, which was at the high end of the 10-year range (1.8-2.3). Participants found 58 individual birds per hour, consistent with the historical mean (59.6) and within the historical range (47.7-68.2). Nectivores continued their slow recovery, except for the Bananaquit, which had now fully rebounded, likely due to its high reproductive rates. Hummingbird numbers were still low compared to historical numbers. Although there were variations among species, seed-eating finch counts were still low, but dove numbers were similar to baseline levels. Insectivores were on the low end of the historical ranges, omnivores were within the range, and raptors were below after returning the baseline in 2018. Waterbirds and shorebirds were generally within the historical range. Thus, overall the 2019 data showed continuing avian population recovery, with many species returning to pre-hurricane baseline levels, albeit with some exceptions (e.g., Antillean Crested Hummingbird,...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In September of 2017, Puerto Rico was hit by two powerful hurricanes: it was grazed by Irma and then clobbered by Maria, a Category 4 storm that cut a devastating swath<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2017/09/18/world/americas/hurricane-maria-tracking-map.html"> across the island</a>. The human and economic consequences were dramatic and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/09/22/us/photos-hurricane-maria-puerto-rico.html">persistent</a>.</p>
<p>These hurricanes prompted a personal interest in the impact of hurricanes on birds, so I did some research, which ultimately led to an article in the <a href="https://www.aba.org/birding-online-april-2018/">April 2018</a> issue of <a href="https://www.aba.org/magazine/"><em>Birding</em> magazine</a>.</p>
<p>Broadly speaking, most birds appear to survive the initial “direct” effects (<em>e.g.</em>, high winds, rain, landslides, and flooding) of hurricanes, but are significantly impacted by the “indirect” effects (<em>e.g.</em>, loss of food supplies and roosting sites).</p>
<p>Immediately after hurricanes, surviving birds appear to wander in an effort to find any remaining food supplies and suitable habitat. Birds that rely on a closed canopy, mature trees, or nectar, fruits, or seeds may struggle to survive. For example, hummingbirds must find patches where there are still flowers. Species with small ranges (<em>e.g.</em>, single island endemics) or tiny populations (<em>e.g.</em>, endangered species) are especially vulnerable.</p>
<p>But as the months pass, forests and other habitats regenerate and many birds return. Over the longer term, forests mature, closing hurricane-created gaps in the canopy, at least until the inevitable next hurricane.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Caribbean-Hurricanes-Birds-Birding-April-2018-640-630x418.png" alt="Caribbean Hurriances: What Happens to the Birds (Birding, April 2018)" width="630" height="418" /></p>
<p>Studying the impact of hurricanes requires data from <em>before and after</em> the event. However, there are few long-term avian studies in the Caribbean. Much of what exists is from Puerto Rico, a U.S. territory where researchers have numerous ongoing investigations, including many studies in <a href="https://www.fs.usda.gov/elyunque">El Yunque National Forest</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.audubon.org/conservation/science/christmas-bird-count">Christmas Bird Counts</a> administered by the <a href="https://www.audubon.org/conservation/history-christmas-bird-count">National Audubon Society</a> are one source of data. <a href="https://www.audubon.org/news/the-117th-cbc-west-indies-and-bermuda">CBCs</a> have been conducted for years in <a href="https://www.audubon.org/magazine/spring-2018/puerto-ricans-band-together-survey-birds">several locations in Puerto Rico</a>, utilizing consistent procedures that can provide comparable “before” and “after” data.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.fs.fed.us/working-with-us/citizen-science/christmas-bird-count-fajardo-area">Fajardo CBC</a> has been conducted since 1994. Fajardo is in the northeastern corner of Puerto Rico and the count area includes parts of <a href="https://www.birdwatchingdaily.com/hotspots/247-el-yunque-national-forest-rio-grande-puerto-rico/">El Yunque</a>. There have been six counts since Maria: (1) December 17, 2017; (2) December 16, 2018; (3) December 15, 2019; (4) December 21, 2020; (5) and December 19, 2021; and (6) December 18, 2022.</p>
<p><strong>The 2017 Count</strong></p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Joseph_Wunderle_Jr/publication/325746074_Effects_of_Hurricanes_Irma_and_Maria_on_birds_in_the_Fajardo_Christmas_Bird_Count_in_northeastern_Puerto_Rico_A_preliminary_assessment/links/5b216ec4458515270fc6d85e/Effects-of-Hurricanes-Irma-and-Maria-on-birds-in-the-Fajardo-Christmas-Bird-Count-in-northeastern-Puerto-Rico-A-preliminary-assessment.pdf?origin=publication_detail">2017 CBC</a> was conducted just a few months after Maria and forests were still extensively defoliated, with countless felled trees and snapped branches. Some plants had started to re-sprout, but recovery was in the very early stages. Nevertheless, the 2017 CBC tallied 1,934 birds of 82 species, both of which were low counts for past CBCs (<em>e.g.</em>, the 2016 CBC had 2,579 birds, 97 species).</p>
<p>When corrected for search effort in the field, participant groups found 1.8 species per party hour, a value not much lower than the mean for counts of the previous 10 years and within the range of earlier counts (1.8-2.2). However, they found only 43 individual birds per hour, well below the 10-year mean of 59.6, as well as below the 10-year range (47.7-68.2).</p>
<p>Some species experienced dramatic declines. For example, nectarivores (<em>e.g.</em>, hummingbirds and Bananaquits) showed a significant drop, which was not surprising given the loss of flowers to high winds. Most shorebird species fell too. Surprisingly, however, a few actually increased, including Scaly-naped Pigeon, Red-legged Thrush, Puerto Rican Oriole, and Puerto Rican Tody. Others were essentially unchanged.</p>
<p>The causes of these inconsistent results are unclear. Some birds may have had to forage more actively, causing them to be observed more frequently, even if there were fewer of them. And post-hurricane habitats themselves may lead to increased detection, as there are no leaves to obscure the birds. Moreover, because many areas lacked a canopy altogether, birds that typically spend time high in trees are forced to ground level, where they are more likely to be observed. And numerous birds may cluster around remaining food sources (<em>e.g.</em>, Royal Palms for frugivores), increasing the probability of detection.</p>
<p>Overall, post-hurricane CBC observers saw species at a rate slightly lower than previous counts, but far fewer birds overall.</p>
<p><strong>The 2018 Count</strong></p>
<p>By the 2018 CBC, although there were still obvious signs of structural damage in the forests, most foliage had returned. But there were still large gaps in tree canopies that had been closed before the hurricanes.</p>
<p>The 2018 CBC tallied 2,492 birds of 87 species. Both numbers were higher than 2017, but still relatively low compared to pre-hurricane counts. When corrected for search effort, participant groups found 2.0 species per party hour, within the range of earlier counts (1.8-2.2). They found 57 individual birds per hour, consistent with the 10-year mean (59.6) and within the 10-year range (47.7-68.2). There were some exceptions. For example, most nectivore numbers continued to be low.</p>
<p>Thus, the 2018 CBC suggested that bird populations within the count area were gradually returning to pre-hurricane levels. Indeed, the 2018 count even added two new species: Black-throated Green Warbler and Greater Flamingo.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-150598 size-large" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Puerto-Rico-Hurricane-Update-2022-Pearly-Eyed-Thrasher-630x360.jpg" alt="" width="630" height="360" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Puerto-Rico-Hurricane-Update-2022-Pearly-Eyed-Thrasher-630x360.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Puerto-Rico-Hurricane-Update-2022-Pearly-Eyed-Thrasher-300x171.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Puerto-Rico-Hurricane-Update-2022-Pearly-Eyed-Thrasher-768x438.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Puerto-Rico-Hurricane-Update-2022-Pearly-Eyed-Thrasher.jpg 799w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></p>
<p><strong>The 2019 Count</strong></p>
<p>In 2019, there was still structural damage in the forests, but most foliage had returned. Many canopy gaps continued, and saplings, vines, and ferns flourished in those openings.</p>
<p>The 2019 CBC tallied 2,308 birds of 90 species, similar to 2018. When corrected for search effort, 2.3 species per party hour were detected, which was at the high end of the 10-year range (1.8-2.3). Participants found 58 individual birds per hour, consistent with the historical mean (59.6) and within the historical range (47.7-68.2).</p>
<p>Nectivores continued their slow recovery, except for the Bananaquit, which had now fully rebounded, likely due to its high reproductive rates. Hummingbird numbers were still low compared to historical numbers. Although there were variations among species, seed-eating finch counts were still low, but dove numbers were similar to baseline levels. Insectivores were on the low end of the historical ranges, omnivores were within the range, and raptors were below after returning the baseline in 2018. Waterbirds and shorebirds were generally within the historical range.</p>
<p>Thus, overall the 2019 data showed continuing avian population recovery, with many species returning to pre-hurricane baseline levels, albeit with some exceptions (<em>e.g.</em>, Antillean Crested Hummingbird, Green-throated Carib, and Ruddy Quail-Dove).</p>
<p><strong>The 2020 Count</strong></p>
<p>Despite the COVID-19 pandemic, the 2020 CBC was conducted (consistent with CDC safety guidelines) on December 21, 2020. A reduced number of participants tallied 2,335 birds of 93 species. Both numbers were higher than 2019, but lower than the pre-hurricane average.</p>
<p>When corrected for search effort, 2.3 species per party hour were detected, which was the same as 2019 and at the high end of the 10-year range. Participants found 58.7 individual birds per hour, similar to 2019, and consistent with the historical mean and within the historical range.</p>
<p>Overall, it appears that most species have recovered to pre-hurricane levels, with a few lingering exceptions, including hummingbirds. Most hummingbird species were still detected at reduced rates (<em>e.g.</em>, Antillean Crested Hummingbird, Green-throated Carib, Green Mango, and Antillean Mango), though one species (Puerto Rican Emerald) has bounced back to pre-hurricane levels. This is consistent with past studies that have consistently documented post-hurricane declines in nectivores.</p>
<p>The remaining species at reduced levels are generally fruit and seed eaters, including Antillean Euphonia. Some insectivores remain at elevated levels, including Puerto Rican Woodpecker and Puerto Rican Tody, though a few (<em>e.g.</em>, Gray Kingbird) have still not recovered. Ruddy Quail-Dove were observed for the first time since 2017. And the many species that had already returned to pre-hurricane levels generally continued at those levels.</p>
<p>Thus, the 2020 data indicate that most species have returned to pre-hurricane levels, with a few remaining exceptions. There appears to be considerable resiliency in the populations of Puerto Rican birds. The next count is scheduled for December 19, 2021.</p>
<p><strong>The 2021 Count</strong></p>
<p>For the second consecutive year, COVID-19 impacted the count, with fewer participants and fewer areas covered. Moreover, rain and wind on count day hindered proceedings. Nevertheless, a reduced number of participants tallied 2,013 birds of 80 species. Both numbers were lower than 2020, and lower than the pre-hurricane averages. Participants saw 1.98 species per party hour, which was within, but at the low end of, the pre-Maria range. They observed 54.3 individual birds per party hour, which was also within the ten-year range.</p>
<p>Most species have returned to pre-hurricane levels, though there are a few exceptions, some of which are likely explained by the reduced number of observers and coverage. That said, several hummingbird species and egrets and herons continue to be seen at lower levels. Although the pandemic and weather complications make comparisons difficult, it appears that the bird community within the count area has proven highly resilient to the 2017 hurricanes. Indeed, a new species (Limpkin) was added in 2021.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-117343 aligncenter" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-Throated-Carib-PR-2019-CBC-630x352.jpg" alt="" width="630" height="352" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-Throated-Carib-PR-2019-CBC-630x352.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-Throated-Carib-PR-2019-CBC-300x168.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-Throated-Carib-PR-2019-CBC-600x336.jpg 600w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-Throated-Carib-PR-2019-CBC.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></p>
<p><strong>The 2022 Count</strong></p>
<p>For the first time since the pandemic, COVID-19 did not impact the count, which had numerous participants and good weather. Participants tallied 2,499 birds of 98 species. Both numbers were comparable to the pre-hurricane averages. Participants saw 2.2 species per party hour, which was at the high end of the pre-Maria range. They observed 58 individual birds per party hour, which was in the middle of the pre-hurricane range. A new species (Wood Duck) was observed.</p>
<p>Most species have returned to pre-hurricane levels, with a few notable exceptions, including several hummingbird species. No pre-hurricane native species has been lost from the count area and and some have seen substantial increases relative to their pre-hurricane levels. The common Bananaquit, a nectivore, is substantially above its pre-Maria levels, likely due to its high reproductive rates, particularly compared to the hummingbird species that have not reached pre-Maria levels. The 2017 hurricanes opened forest canopies, likely increasing flower and fruit production, and many of their associated birds have increased. The frugivorous Scaly-naped Pigeon had a record count in 2022, for example.</p>
<p>As with the 2020 and 2021 counts, the 2022 count reinforces the conclusion that the bird community in the count area is highly resilient.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">* * * * *</p>
<p>Although six years of data from a single CBC provides only a sliver of the overall picture, the population trends continue to be positive. Moreover, the recovery appears to be consistent with those of earlier well-documented hurricanes, such as Hugo in 1989. The post-hurricane data tell a story of avian resilience.</p>
<p>Scientists <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0214432">continue</a> <a href="https://digitalcommons.conncoll.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1037&amp;context=biofacpub">to study</a> the impact of Irma and Maria, which will improve our understanding of the impact of hurricanes on Caribbean birds. Among other things, biologists have determined that the impact of Maria on trees was <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-09319-2">much more significant</a> than prior storms, likely due to climate change.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">* * * * *</p>
<p>Once again, heartfelt thanks to <a href="https://www.fs.fed.us/research/people/profile.php?alias=jwunderlejr">Dr. Joseph M. Wunderle Jr.</a>, who wrote a number of the <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/1369528?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents">key</a> <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Joseph_Wunderle_Jr/publication/231795524_The_Effects_of_Hurricanes_on_Birds_with_Special_Reference_to_Caribbean_Islands/links/541f263a0cf2218008d3e42f/The-Effects-of-Hurricanes-on-Birds-with-Special-Reference-to-Caribbean-Islands.pdf">scientific</a> <a href="https://sora.unm.edu/sites/default/files/journals/wilson/v104n04/p0656-p0673.pdf">papers</a> that formed the basis of my <em>Birding</em> article. Now retired, Dr. Wunderle was a scientist at the <a href="https://www.fs.usda.gov/iitf/">International Institute of Tropical Forestry</a> (IITF), a part of the U.S. Forest Service. He is also a <a href="https://www.birdscaribbean.org/our-work/leadership/">founding member</a> of <a href="https://www.birdscaribbean.org/">BirdsCaribbean</a> and the editor-in-chief of the <a href="https://jco.birdscaribbean.org/index.php/jco"><em>Journal of Caribbean Ornithology</em></a>. Dr. Wunderle is the compiler for the Fajardo CBC and graciously provided the data described above.</p>
<p><em>This post was originally published on January 8, 2019, and was updated on January 14, 2020, January 15, 2021, and January 6, 2022.</em></p>
<p>Photo: <a href="https://flic.kr/p/czYomb">Bananaquit</a>, <a href="https://flic.kr/p/hRzY12">Pearly-eyed Thrasher</a>, and <a href="https://flic.kr/p/cBUK9w">Green-throated Carib</a> by <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/46789814@N05/">Jason Crotty</a>; <em><a href="https://www.aba.org/magazine/">Birding</a></em> by <a href="https://www.aba.org/">American Birding Association</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/puerto-ricos-birds-after-hurricane-maria.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Birding Napo, Guangxi, China &#8211; part 1</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/birding-napo-guangxi-china-part-1.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/birding-napo-guangxi-china-part-1.htm#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kai Pflug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 19:00:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150291</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Napo is a county in the West of Guangxi, bordering both Yunnan and Vietnam. It is about 3 hours by car from Nanning airport, which in turn can be reached from Shanghai in a 2.5-hour flight. While Napos relative remoteness made it seem less vulnerable to covid, on the second day of our hotel stay we were informed that they could no longer service the hotel rooms as all the hotel service staff had contracted the virus. Which made the rest of the trip a bit of a waiting period for contracting covid &#8230; Apparently, the Large Niltava is Asia’s largest flycatcher. That comes at a price – the HBW describes the species as “stocky and fairly sluggish” and – with a critical undertone – continues to state that the species is “generally less agile in flight than are most flycatchers”. I would like to see the speed at which some of the HBW editors catch flies &#8230; The male is quite &#8220;in your face&#8221; while the female is a bit more subdued. Quite elegant, in fact. If you aim to achieve some kind of immortality, you might do worse than follow the example of Oana Mirela Chachula, a biologist at the National Museum of Romanian History, Romania. Apparently, she supported the research of a Romanian team on ectoparasites of birds from Meghalaya (India) – and for her troubles, the team thanked her by naming a species of feather mite newly discovered on Large Niltava after her. &#160; (Side note: Should anyone involved in discovering new species enjoy reading this blog, please refrain from naming any newly discovered species after me – particularly if these species are of the itchy or vaguely disgusting kind. End of side note). I only saw the female taking a bath &#8211; coincidence? &#160; Even in China’s slightly more remote provinces, one is never far away from species with treacherously pornographic names such as Japanese Tit. Why are people always thinking about sex? &#160; The Grey-bellied Tesia is described by eBird by the seemingly Tolkien-inspired description “Long-legged and short-tailed, this tiny bird moves rapidly and unseen through dark, dense undergrowth like a pint-sized shadow”. The text just about manages not to use the word “elf”. Fortunately, it is actually not quite as difficult to photograph as the appallingly bad photo of the eBird report suggests, though it indeed moves quickly. Why the Latin species name is cyaniventer (meaning having a dark blue belly) remains a mystery to me though. The Bar-backed Partridge is a species of partridge found in southwestern China and Southeast Asia. It should not be confused with &#8220;Bareback Partridge&#8221;, a desultory term used to describe certain sexual practices among pheasants in general. &#160; The Bar-backed Partridge was also one of four focal species in an investigation into illegal bird hunting in Southwestern China. Sadly, that study found that perceived entertainment and recreational value are main motivators for illegal hunting rather than economic considerations: &#8220;Contrary to previous findings highlighting subsistence and finance as major factors driving hunting, the most important predictors of hunting activity in this landscape were related to attitudes regarding the enjoyment of hunting&#8221;. &#8220;Shoot us, it is fun!&#8221; Unfortunately, this makes it much less likely this hunting will stop once people get richer. Then again, I guess this conclusion could easily have been drawn from the popularity of hunting in the US &#8230; Hopefully, in a few hundred years, the sculptures of famous people who in their lives enjoyed hunting will be destroyed like the sculptures of slave traders today. The Sooty-headed Bulbul was the subject of a similar study &#8211; the authors checked whether the flight initiation distance of the bird is related to hunting pressure in a given area. Unsurprisingly, it is. If I can give you some advice: Better not be a bird in China. The usually fairly friendly eBird reviewers give a rather harsh assessment of the Scarlet-faced Liocichla as a &#8220;Garish medium-sized laughingthrush-like bird&#8221;. It is hard to blame them given the color combination sported by the species, though it makes me wonder why the Silver-eared Mesia with a similarly broad array of colors is described as a &#8220;beautiful small babbler&#8221;. &#8220;Me, garish?&#8221; The mystery deepens when reading the species description in the HBW: &#8220;Fairly small babbler, mostly plain brown but with ­scarlet face and scarlet in wings and tail&#8221;. That does not really sound garish, right? On the other hand, to me, a length of 21-23 cm does not sound like a &#8220;fairly small babbler&#8221; given that babblers are &#8220;small to medium birds&#8221; (Wikipedia). Confusing. Strangely, eBird gives the Red-tailed Laughingthrush a much better review as an &#8220;exquisitely- and distinctively-colored laughingthrush&#8221;. The species gets its Latin name milnei from Alphonse Milne-Edwards (1835-1900), a French mammalogist, ornithologist, and carcinologist (it seems multitasking was easier then). From the fact that I do not have anything exciting to write about him, you can deduce that I did not make him up (my imaginary ornithologists tend to be a bit more interesting, having at least committed some atrocities or fathered a number of illegitimate children). The only vaguely specific thing I can say about him from his photo in his Wikipedia entry is that he had already lost a substantial part of his hair at age 48. Maybe doing ornithological research was just his way of compensation. If you ever consider opening a haunted house, you might want to get some of these birds &#8211; according to the HBW, their sound includes phrases such as “uuu-weeoo”, “eeoo-wee” or shorter “uuuwi” or “uuuu-hiu-hiu” and “uuuu-hiu-hiu-hiu”. eBird is also back to its usual positive self in describing the Black-headed Greenfinch as a &#8220;handsome yellowish finch&#8221;. The poor Common Tailorbird is a host to the Plaintive Cuckoo. Researchers examined the interaction between the host and the cuckoo chicks and found that it is more or less the same as the one known from Common Cuckoos. That does not keep them from making the rather pompous claim that the &#8220;developmental data on Plaintive Cuckoo nestlings...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Napo is a county in the West of Guangxi, bordering both Yunnan and Vietnam. It is about 3 hours by car from Nanning airport, which in turn can be reached from Shanghai in a 2.5-hour flight.</p>



<p>While Napos relative remoteness made it seem less vulnerable to covid, on the second day of our hotel stay we were informed that they could no longer service the hotel rooms as all the hotel service staff had contracted the virus. Which made the rest of the trip a bit of a waiting period for contracting covid &#8230;</p>



<p>Apparently, the <strong>Large Niltava</strong> is Asia’s largest flycatcher. That comes at a price – the HBW describes the species as “stocky and fairly sluggish” and – with a critical undertone – continues to state that the species is “generally less agile in flight than are most flycatchers”. I would like to see the speed at which some of the HBW editors catch flies &#8230;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="450" class="wp-image-150470" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0555_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x450.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0555_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x450.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0555_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x215.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0555_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x549.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0555_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The male is quite &#8220;in your face&#8221; while the female is a bit more subdued. Quite elegant, in fact.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150471" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0510_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>If you aim to achieve some kind of immortality, you might do worse than follow the example of Oana Mirela Chachula, a biologist at the National Museum of Romanian History, Romania. Apparently, she supported the research of a Romanian team on ectoparasites of birds from Meghalaya (India) – and for her troubles, the team thanked her by <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5539365/">naming a species of feather mite</a> newly discovered on<strong> Large Niltava </strong>after her.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="684" class="wp-image-150472" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0588_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x684.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0588_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x684.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0588_Napo-Dec-24-2022-276x300.jpg 276w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0588_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x834.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0588_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1105w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="583" class="wp-image-150473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0600_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x583.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0600_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x583.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0600_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x278.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0600_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x710.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0600_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>(Side note: Should anyone involved in discovering new species enjoy reading this blog, please refrain from naming any newly discovered species after me – particularly if these species are of the itchy or vaguely disgusting kind. End of side note).</p>



<p>I only saw the female taking a bath &#8211; coincidence?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="445" class="wp-image-150474" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0602_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x445.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0602_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x445.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0602_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x212.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0602_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x543.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Large-Niltava_DSC0602_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Even in China’s slightly more remote provinces, one is never far away from species with treacherously pornographic names such as <strong>Japanese Tit</strong>. Why are people always thinking about sex?</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="513" class="wp-image-150478" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1565_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x513.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1565_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x513.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1565_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-300x245.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1565_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-768x626.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1565_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="448" class="wp-image-150477" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1572_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x448.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1572_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x448.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1572_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-300x214.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1572_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-768x547.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Japanese-Tit_DSC1572_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Grey-bellied Tesia</strong> is described by eBird by the seemingly Tolkien-inspired description “Long-legged and short-tailed, this tiny bird moves rapidly and unseen through dark, dense undergrowth like a pint-sized shadow”. The text just about manages not to use the word “elf”.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="444" class="wp-image-150481" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0399_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x444.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0399_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x444.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0399_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x212.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0399_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x541.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0399_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Fortunately, it is actually not quite as difficult to photograph as the appallingly bad photo of the eBird report suggests, though it indeed moves quickly.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="471" class="wp-image-150482" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0251_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x471.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0251_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x471.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0251_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x224.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0251_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x574.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0251_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Why the Latin species name is<em> cyaniventer</em> (meaning having a dark blue belly) remains a mystery to me though.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="456" class="wp-image-150483" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0443_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x456.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0443_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x456.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0443_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x217.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0443_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x556.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-bellied-Tesia_DSC0443_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Bar-backed Partridge</strong> is a species of partridge found in southwestern China and Southeast Asia. It should not be confused with &#8220;Bareback Partridge&#8221;, a desultory term used to describe certain sexual practices among pheasants in general.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150489" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0659_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="945" class="wp-image-150484" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0384_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x945.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0384_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x945.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0384_Napo-Dec-24-2022-200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0384_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0384_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Bar-backed Partridge </strong>was also one of four focal species in <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S000632071831454X">an investigation</a> into illegal bird hunting in Southwestern China. Sadly, that study found that perceived entertainment and recreational value are main motivators for illegal hunting rather than economic considerations: &#8220;Contrary to previous findings highlighting subsistence and finance as major factors driving hunting, the most important predictors of hunting activity in this landscape were related to attitudes regarding the enjoyment of hunting&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150491" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC0654_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;Shoot us, it is fun!&#8221;</p>



<p>Unfortunately, this makes it much less likely this hunting will stop once people get richer. Then again, I guess this conclusion could easily have been drawn from the popularity of hunting in the US &#8230;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="428" class="wp-image-150490" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC9504_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x428.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC9504_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x428.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC9504_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-300x204.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC9504_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-768x522.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Bar-backed-Partridge_DSC9504_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Hopefully, in a few hundred years, the sculptures of famous people who in their lives enjoyed hunting will be destroyed like the sculptures of slave traders today.</p>



<p>The <strong>Sooty-headed Bulbul</strong> was the subject of a <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/194008291500800214">similar study</a> &#8211; the authors checked whether the flight initiation distance of the bird is related to hunting pressure in a given area. Unsurprisingly, it is. If I can give you some advice: Better not be a bird in China.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="574" class="wp-image-150492" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Sooty-headed-Bulbul_DSC1391_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x574.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Sooty-headed-Bulbul_DSC1391_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x574.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Sooty-headed-Bulbul_DSC1391_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x273.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Sooty-headed-Bulbul_DSC1391_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x700.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Sooty-headed-Bulbul_DSC1391_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The usually fairly friendly eBird reviewers give a rather harsh assessment of the <strong>Scarlet-faced Liocichla</strong> as a &#8220;Garish medium-sized laughingthrush-like bird&#8221;. It is hard to blame them given the color combination sported by the species, though it makes me wonder why the Silver-eared Mesia with a similarly broad array of colors is described as a &#8220;beautiful small babbler&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150495" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0521_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;Me, garish?&#8221;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="447" class="wp-image-150493" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0496_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x447.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0496_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x447.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0496_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x213.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0496_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x545.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0496_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The mystery deepens when reading the species description in the HBW: &#8220;Fairly small babbler, mostly plain brown but with ­scarlet face and scarlet in wings and tail&#8221;. That does not really sound garish, right? On the other hand, to me, a length of 21-23 cm does not sound like a &#8220;fairly small babbler&#8221; given that babblers are &#8220;small to medium birds&#8221; (Wikipedia). Confusing.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="531" class="wp-image-150494" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0338_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x531.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0338_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x531.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0338_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x253.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0338_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x647.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Scarlet-faced-Liocichla_DSC0338_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Strangely, eBird gives the <strong>Red-tailed Laughingthrush</strong> a much better review as an &#8220;exquisitely- and distinctively-colored laughingthrush&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="425" class="wp-image-150496" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x425.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x425.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x203.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x518.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9242_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The species gets its Latin name <em>milnei</em> from Alphonse Milne-Edwards (1835-1900), a French mammalogist, ornithologist, and carcinologist (it seems multitasking was easier then). From the fact that I do not have anything exciting to write about him, you can deduce that I did not make him up (my imaginary ornithologists tend to be a bit more interesting, having at least committed some atrocities or fathered a number of illegitimate children). The only vaguely specific thing I can say about him from his photo in his Wikipedia entry is that he had already lost a substantial part of his hair at age 48. Maybe doing ornithological research was just his way of compensation.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="581" class="wp-image-150497" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9691_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x581.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9691_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x581.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9691_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x277.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9691_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x708.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9691_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>If you ever consider opening a haunted house, you might want to get some of these birds &#8211; according to the HBW, their sound includes phrases such as “uuu-weeoo”, “eeoo-wee” or shorter “uuuwi” or “uuuu-hiu-hiu” and “uuuu-hiu-hiu-hiu”.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="458" class="wp-image-150498" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9143_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x458.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9143_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x458.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9143_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x218.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9143_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x558.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Red-tailed-Laughingthrush_DSC9143_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>eBird is also back to its usual positive self in describing the <strong>Black-headed Greenfinch</strong> as a &#8220;handsome yellowish finch&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="582" class="wp-image-150499" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-headed-Greenfinch_DSC1664_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x582.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-headed-Greenfinch_DSC1664_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x582.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-headed-Greenfinch_DSC1664_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x277.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-headed-Greenfinch_DSC1664_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x709.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-headed-Greenfinch_DSC1664_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The poor <strong>Common Tailorbird</strong> is a host to the Plaintive Cuckoo. Researchers <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s40657-019-0143-z">examined</a> the interaction between the host and the cuckoo chicks and found that it is more or less the same as the one known from Common Cuckoos. That does not keep them from making the rather pompous claim that the &#8220;developmental data on Plaintive Cuckoo nestlings and their tailorbird host builds an important foundation for future work on the co-evolutionary interactions in this parasite–host system.&#8221; Almost 30 years ago, I may have made similarly grandiose claims in the introduction to my Ph.D. thesis. I was young then.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="479" class="wp-image-150500" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1318_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x479.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1318_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x479.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1318_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x228.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1318_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x584.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1318_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" class="wp-image-150501" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1321_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x473.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1321_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x473.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1321_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1321_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1321_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Another, somewhat more interesting <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6755120/">study</a> suggests that nest sanitation (ornithologists speak for cleaning up your room) helps Common Tailorbirds to recognize and eject parasitic eggs. While I do not find the rationale fully convincing, I would have to agree that it is easier to overlook something in a room full of trash. This also allows me to give you, my dear reader, some practical advice for your life from ornithological search results &#8211; keep your room clean! You may call me Marie Kondo if you want.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="474" class="wp-image-150502" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1372_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x474.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1372_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x474.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1372_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x226.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1372_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x578.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Common-Tailorbird_DSC1372_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Strangely, there is not much research on the <strong>Blue Whistling Thrush</strong>. It tends to live near hilly streams, not surprising given that it seems to feed mainly on snails (though <a href="https://knepublishing.com/index.php/KnE-Life/article/view/214/202">one paper</a> describes it as eating a snake). The ones in China have a black bill &#8211; further west (where apparently historically there was no ban on the use of the color yellow, which in China is traditionally reserved for the emperor), the bill is yellow.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150507" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0561_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="420" class="wp-image-150508" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-630x420.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Blue-Whistling-Thrush_DSC0099_Napo-Dec-24-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Black-throated Bushtits</strong> can also be seen in Shanghai, but they are cute and attractive birds, a fact that is even indicated at by their Latin species name of concinnus, &#8220;elegant, neat, pleasing&#8221; (HBW).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="467" class="wp-image-150575" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x467.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x467.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x222.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x569.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022-590x437.jpg 590w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0218_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="368" class="wp-image-150576" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0235_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x368.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0235_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x368.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0235_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x175.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0235_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x449.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Black-throated-Bushtit_DSC0235_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Rufescent Prinia</strong> &#8211; if that is indeed what it is &#8211; does not seem to mind very much being confused with the Grey-breasted Prinia. At least not to the extent of wearing name tags.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="608" class="wp-image-150582" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7746_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-630x608.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7746_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-630x608.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7746_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-300x290.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7746_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-768x741.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7746_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="608" class="wp-image-150583" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7792_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-630x608.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7792_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-630x608.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7792_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-300x290.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7792_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2-768x741.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-breasted-Prinia_DSC7792_Napo-Dec-23-2022-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Grey Bushchat</strong> has a species name that is derived from chemistry: &#8220;ferreus&#8221;, or iron-colored (I always guessed my chemistry studies would come in handy sooner or later). As usual, this refers to the silvery-grey color of the male rather than the brown color of the female.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="484" class="wp-image-150570" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1405_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x484.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1405_Napo-Dec-25-2022-630x484.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1405_Napo-Dec-25-2022-300x230.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1405_Napo-Dec-25-2022-768x589.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1405_Napo-Dec-25-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="517" class="wp-image-150573" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1408_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x517.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1408_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-630x517.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1408_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-300x246.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1408_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1-768x630.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-Bushchat_DSC1408_Napo-Dec-25-2022-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The last bird shown in this post is a <strong>Pallas&#8217;s Leaf Warbler </strong>&#8211; but is it really? eBird warns that it &#8220;overlaps considerably with other similar leaf warblers throughout the non-breeding range, so identification warrants caution&#8221; &#8211; which sounds like an ID challenge way above my pay grade as a birder. At least the basic description of the species in eBird seems to fit: &#8220;Tiny, chunky, sprightly warbler with a short tail and a big head&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="438" class="wp-image-150574" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pallas-Leaf-Warbler_DSC8911_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x438.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pallas-Leaf-Warbler_DSC8911_Napo-Dec-24-2022-630x438.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pallas-Leaf-Warbler_DSC8911_Napo-Dec-24-2022-300x209.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pallas-Leaf-Warbler_DSC8911_Napo-Dec-24-2022-768x534.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pallas-Leaf-Warbler_DSC8911_Napo-Dec-24-2022.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>But then again, chunky? Really?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/birding-napo-guangxi-china-part-1.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>2</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Broome&#8217;s birds get a battering</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/broomes-birds-get-a-battering.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/broomes-birds-get-a-battering.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Clare M]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Broome]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Western Australia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150615</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the best indications that we are going to get rain is that our pink Storm Lilies start to flower. The flowers above are Zephyranthes grandiflora and they are a small bulb that flowers when the air pressure drops. It doesn&#8217;t matter how much water you give them to encourage flowers, because a storm is required before they flower. We also have white Rain Lilies Pancratium zeylanicum that also depend on the air pressure changing to flower. White Rain Lily As you can see, both species of bulbs are flowering and there is a good reason for that. The first few days of 2023 have been extremely wet in Broome and surrounding areas and we have come off it lightly in town really. I know I suggested you could come and explore Australia, but it really does depend on where you want to go and when. A very reliable source of information for the highways in Western Australia is the Main Roads Travel Map. The north of Western Australia is no longer accessible by road due to unprecedented flooding. Fitzroy Crossing in particular has suffered the most in the last few days with the town flooded and the bridge severely damaged. The river height reached 15.81m and the river height gauge then failed, but the water level is slowly dropping as it moves further downstream towards Langi Crossing and then the sea. If you can imagine the Low Level Crossing with an extra 15.81 metres of water height then you can understand it is a lot of extra water. The rain does not need to fall in a town that a river runs through for it to flood. The river catchment area is massive and it will continue to flow for many months now offering some serious challenges to the bridge structural engineers. Broome has received a lot of rain these last few days, but we are now starting to dry out. Broome weather statistics are a mean average rainfall of 194.1mm for the whole of January, which is our wettest month normally. Our mean average is 627.6mm for the whole year. These records are from 1939 until 2022, but they will be adjusted after what we have just received. We have just had 565.4mm of rain in the first 6 days of January. Broome rainfall Tropical Cyclone Ellie had dropped to be an ex-cyclone, but she sat over Broome for a few days showing us that Mother Nature is in charge. Although it is a bit miserable having to stay inside watching your grass grow underwater it is even more miserable for the birds. For two days we didn&#8217;t see or hear birds other than Oriental Pratincoles that somehow managed to fight the wind and feed. On Friday, when the wind dropped, there were many of them just sat on the roads clearly exhausted. There are very good storm drains around Broome and all of the rainwater goes into massive ditches and then is controlled to go out into Roebuck Bay. However, it is a lot of water to clear and it is still slowly moving through the drainage systems. Our blue sea has become a muddy colour for obvious reasons. Storm water drains Australian White Ibis in a storm water drain The Plumed Whistling-Ducks have dispersed and we are hearing them overhead now and they have plenty of places to stand around in muddy water now. Plumed Whistling-Ducks The Masked Lapwings have been breeding and their young are having to deal with more puddles than they would normally have to. Masked Lapwing chick The Willie Wagtail is hardly standing still as it chases the flying ants and flits about constantly. Willie Wagtail As soon as we heard birds coming into our garden on Friday morning around 5.30am I went out to give them some food. They had really had a tough couple of days and anything we could do to help we would. There were soon a couple of dozen very hungry Double-barred Finch in the garden along with Bar-shouldered Doves. Double-barred Finch We have been looking for one of our Tawny Frogmouth families that still had young at Christmas and are yet to find them. No doubt they have been watching us and we hope to establish where they are now roosting. The Tawny Frogmouth that is blind in one eye remains in the middle of the dense tree in the middle of a roundabout and was clearly a bit tired after all of the rain. Tawny Frogmouth having a yawn! So, although we had a good day birding around Broome observing 113 bird species on January 1st we are now restricted on where we travel until the water level subsides. We can expect the highway south to offer excellent birding opportunities once we are allowed to travel on it again. We can expect more rain in the coming weeks and months, because this is our &#8220;Wet Season&#8221;, but nobody was really expecting quite this much rain!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>One of the best indications that we are going to get rain is that our pink Storm Lilies start to flower. The flowers above are <em>Zephyranthes grandiflora</em> and they are a small bulb that flowers when the air pressure drops. It doesn&#8217;t matter how much water you give them to encourage flowers, because a storm is required before they flower. We also have white Rain Lilies <em>Pancratium zeylanicum</em> that also depend on the air pressure changing to flower. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rain-Lily.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150619" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rain-Lily.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rain-Lily-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">White Rain Lily</p>



<p>As you can see, both species of bulbs are flowering and there is a good reason for that. The first few days of 2023 have been extremely wet in Broome and surrounding areas and we have come off it lightly in town really. I know I suggested you <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/where-could-you-go-birding-in-australia-in-2023.htm">could come and explore Australia</a>, but it really does depend on where you want to go and when. A very reliable source of information for the highways in Western Australia is the <a href="https://travelmap.mainroads.wa.gov.au/Home/Map">Main Roads Travel Map</a>. The north of Western Australia is no longer accessible by road due to unprecedented flooding.</p>



<p>Fitzroy Crossing in particular has suffered the most in the last few days with <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-01-04/defence-force-evacuate-stranded-wa-kimberley-residents-flooding/101826130">the town flooded</a> and the bridge severely damaged. The river height reached 15.81m and the river height gauge then failed, but the water level is slowly dropping as it moves further downstream towards<a href="https://www.10000birds.com/bird-watching-at-langi-crossing.htm"> Langi Crossing</a> and then the sea. If you can imagine the <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/low-level-crossing-at-fitzroy-crossing.htm">Low Level Crossing</a> with an extra 15.81 metres of water height then you can understand it is a lot of extra water. The rain does not need to fall in a town that a river runs through for it to flood. The river catchment area is massive and it will continue to flow for many months now offering some serious challenges to the bridge structural engineers. </p>



<p>Broome has received a lot of rain these last few days, but we are now starting to dry out. Broome weather statistics are a mean average rainfall of 194.1mm for the whole of January, which is our wettest month normally. Our mean average is 627.6mm for the whole year. These <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/bird-watching-at-langi-crossing.htm">records are from 1939 until 2022</a>, but they will be adjusted after what we have just received. We have just had <strong>565.4mm</strong> of rain in the first 6 days of January. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="363" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Broome-rainfall-1-630x363.png" alt="" class="wp-image-150620" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Broome-rainfall-1-630x363.png 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Broome-rainfall-1-300x173.png 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Broome-rainfall-1-768x442.png 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Broome-rainfall-1.png 1498w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">Broome rainfall</p>



<p>Tropical Cyclone Ellie had dropped to be an ex-cyclone, but she sat over Broome for a few days showing us that Mother Nature is in charge. Although it is a bit miserable having to stay inside watching your grass grow underwater it is even more miserable for the birds. For two days we didn&#8217;t see or hear birds other than <strong><a href="https://www.10000birds.com/locusts-and-oriental-pratincoles-around-broome.htm">Oriental Pratincoles</a></strong> that somehow managed to fight the wind and feed. On Friday, when the wind dropped, there were many of them just sat on the roads clearly exhausted. </p>



<p>There are very good storm drains around Broome and all of the rainwater goes into massive ditches and then is controlled to go out into Roebuck Bay. However, it is a lot of water to clear and it is still slowly moving through the drainage systems. Our blue sea has become a muddy colour for obvious reasons. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-3.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150622" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-3.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-3-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150623" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-1.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-1-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150624" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-2.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-2-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150625" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Storm-water-drain-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">Storm water drains</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Australian-White-Ibis-2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150626" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Australian-White-Ibis-2.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Australian-White-Ibis-2-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Australian White Ibis</strong> in a storm water drain</p>



<p>The <strong>Plumed Whistling-Ducks</strong> have dispersed and we are hearing them overhead now and they have plenty of places to stand around in muddy water now. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumed-Whistling-Ducks-11.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150627" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumed-Whistling-Ducks-11.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumed-Whistling-Ducks-11-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Plumed Whistling-Ducks</strong></p>



<p>The <strong>Masked Lapwings</strong> have been breeding and their young are having to deal with more puddles than they would normally have to.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Masked-Lapwing-chick.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150628" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Masked-Lapwing-chick.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Masked-Lapwing-chick-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Masked Lapwing</strong> chick</p>



<p>The <strong>Willie Wagtail</strong> is hardly standing still as it chases the flying ants and flits about constantly.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Willie-Wagtail-10.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150629" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Willie-Wagtail-10.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Willie-Wagtail-10-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Willie Wagtail</strong></p>



<p>As soon as we heard birds coming into our garden on Friday morning around 5.30am I went out to give them some food. They had really had a tough couple of days and anything we could do to help we would.  There were soon a couple of dozen very hungry <strong>Double-barred Finch</strong> in the garden along with <strong>Bar-shouldered Doves. </strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Double-barred-Finch-11.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150632" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Double-barred-Finch-11.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Double-barred-Finch-11-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Double-barred Finch</strong></p>



<p>We have been looking for one of our <strong>Tawny Frogmouth</strong> families that still had <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/a-christmas-surprise-in-broome.htm">young at Christmas</a> and are yet to find them. No doubt they have been watching us and we hope to establish where they are now roosting. The <strong>Tawny Frogmouth</strong> that is blind in one eye remains in the middle of the dense tree in the middle of a roundabout and was clearly a bit tired after all of the rain.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth-.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150634" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth-.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth--300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="473" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth-yawn-.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150635" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth-yawn-.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tawny-Frogmouth-yawn--300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Tawny Frogmouth</strong> having a yawn!</p>



<p>So, although we had a good day birding around Broome observing 113 bird species on January 1st we are now restricted on where we travel until the water level subsides. We can expect the highway south to offer <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/a-nature-lovers-highway.htm">excellent birding opportunities</a> once we are allowed to travel on it again. </p>



<p>We can expect more rain in the coming weeks and months, because this is our &#8220;Wet Season&#8221;, but nobody was really expecting quite this much rain!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/broomes-birds-get-a-battering.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Afforestation 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/afforestation-2022.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/afforestation-2022.htm#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Paul Lewis]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2023 05:05:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[afforestation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Native plants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[native trees]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150432</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Eighteen months ago, I wrote about a particular passion project of mine, which is to create a mini-forest on part of our church&#8217;s one acre of land. This project qualifies as &#8220;afforestation&#8221;, which is the creation of a forest in a site that was not originally forested &#8212; as opposed to reforestation, which creates a new forest on a site that was previously forested but has been logged. Creating a new forest is my way of turning intense frustration into positive action. Birding in the developing world means being a witness to constant habitat destruction. So I am attempting to respond, by creating new habitat. I try not to talk too much with my long-suffering congregation about birds. But I do have to mention &#8220;mis arbolitos&#8221; (my little trees), since they are growing on the church lot itself. So I am happy that this year many of mis arbolitos have finally reached a size where they can be noticed from a distance. Now they know I&#8217;m not just making this all up. Look, real trees you can actually see! This is what was there before my &#8220;forest&#8221;. The classic highland forest in Michoacán is known as pine-oak forest, and many of my 22 pine trees are now at least knee high, while three are already chest high, and one (my only surviving pine purchased from a commercial nursery) is taller than I am. Most of these pine trees were bought from reforestation nurseries, for fifty U.S. cents each. (Because of their availability and low price, I have not learned to grow these from seed.) The same price also bought me five cedros blancos, which, in spite of their name of &#8220;white cedars&#8221;, are actually native cypresses. These are also chest high, after only one year in the ground. On the left is a Michoacán pine; on the right is an Ocote pine (named for a resinous pine wood used as fire starter kindling). This Ocote pine is almost my height, but took five summers to reach that height. The pine to its left (I&#8217;m not sure which variety) has only been in the ground for 18 months. These Cedros may look skinny, but they have grown from a few inches to four feet in a year and a half. That&#8217;s an adult Cedro on another property, in the background. The ahuehuete, or Mexican Bald Cypress, is a tree with a rich relationship to Mexican history. It is also beautiful, and is one of the few trees I have been willing to spend real money on (two-to-four dollars each). I now have three chest-high ahuehuetes growing on the lot, as they are well adapted to our wet/dry climate. Bald Cypresses have soft needles that can drop in the winter, and will grow happily in swamps. But the Mexican Bald Cypress can handle our dry winters as well. I plant them on the wettest parts (in summer) of the church property. Unfortunately, while conifers may be our easiest native trees to purchase, they do not offer all that much to birds in the way of food. In contrast, oak trees are our native avian supermarkets; but I have yet to find a reforestation or commercial nursery that offers them. So I have had to climb a steep learning curve to learn to grow them from seed, or rather, from acorn. Two oak seedlings I was given in 2018, by a botanical garden, are still growing today. Since then, I have managed to grow eight more from acorns. Half of these were started just last year, so I have real hope for the future. My goal is to someday achieve a typical Michoacan mix of 40% pines, 40% oaks, and 20% other tree species. (I picked up some 30 apparently viable acorns just this morning, for the next crop. Viable acorns don&#8217;t float in water.) This is one of my two oldest oaks. It looks a bit shaggy now, during our dry winter. But It doubled in size last spring, so I would say we are off to the races. This lovely little oak was an acorn in June. As for the other species, they include two tejocotes (Mexican Hawthorn, a tree that produces crabapple-like fruits), four colorines, a native coral tree that produces tubular red flowers for the hummingbirds, an equal number of guamúchiles, which produce seeds surrounded by an edible white pulp, one native chokecherry, one ash tree, a parotilla, and two ceibas (kapok tree). I have also planted many prickly pear seedlings and cuttings, as this cactus produces both flowers and fruit for birds. And I have protected and cared for other native plants that have turned up on their own, particularly granjenos, which have now begun to produce their first tasty red fruits. After acting like a bush for several years, this Tejocote suddenly decided to be a tree this fall, and sent out this one leading shoot. I think it&#8217;s looking forward to a big 2023. This Guamúchil seedling is only 7 months old. You can barely see the first Granjeno fruits in the middle of this photo. They will eventually turn a deep red. Birds love them, and so do I. Of course, a forest does not consist only of trees. I managed to successfully start some wild grape vines this summer. I also planted a purchased blackberry plant. And my botanist friend gifted me some cucamelon seeds; this wild cucumber (native to Mexico) looks exactly like a tiny watermelon. I hope to show a photo someday soon&#8230; but they have to sprout first. I have also planted a good number of non-native ornamentals and fruit-producing trees in the more visible part of the property: citrus, jacarandas, mulberries, a peach and a guava, etc. This is a bit of a concession to what most people consider &#8220;a garden&#8221;. Pomegranate trees have also sprouted everywhere, because our home tree contributes excess fruit to my compost piles. One of my 2022 projects was this traditional, non-native bit of...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Eighteen months ago, I <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/afforestation.htm">wrote </a>about a particular passion project of mine, which is to create a mini-forest on part of our church&#8217;s one acre of land. This project qualifies as &#8220;afforestation&#8221;, which is the creation of a forest in a site that was not originally forested &#8212; as opposed to reforestation, which creates a new forest on a site that was previously forested but has been logged.</p>



<p>Creating a new forest is my way of turning intense frustration into positive action. Birding in the developing world means being a witness to constant habitat destruction. So I am attempting to respond, by creating new habitat.</p>



<p>I try not to talk too much with my long-suffering congregation about birds. But I do have to mention &#8220;<em>mis arbolitos</em>&#8221; (my little trees), since they are growing on the church lot itself. So I am happy that this year many of <em>mis arbolitos</em> have finally reached a size where they can be noticed from a distance. Now they know I&#8217;m not just making this all up.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Native-tree-zone-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150659" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Native-tree-zone-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Native-tree-zone-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Native-tree-zone.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>Look, real trees you can actually see!</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Untrimmed-lot-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150660" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Untrimmed-lot-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Untrimmed-lot-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Untrimmed-lot.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>This is what was there before my &#8220;forest&#8221;.</em></p>



<p>The classic highland forest in Michoacán is known as pine-oak forest, and many of my 22 pine trees are now at least knee high, while three are already chest high, and one (my only surviving pine purchased from a commercial nursery) is taller than I am. Most of these pine trees were bought from reforestation nurseries, for fifty U.S. cents each. (Because of their availability and low price, I have not learned to grow these from seed.) The same price also bought me five <em>cedros blancos</em>, which, in spite of their name of &#8220;white cedars&#8221;, are actually native cypresses. These are also chest high, after only one year in the ground.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Two-Pines-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150661" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Two-Pines-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Two-Pines-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Two-Pines.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>On the left is a Michoacán pine; on the right is an </em>Ocote <em>pine (named for a resinous pine wood used as fire starter kindling).</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ocote-Pine-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150662" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ocote-Pine-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ocote-Pine-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ocote-Pine.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>This </em>Ocote<em> pine is almost my height, but took five summers to reach that height. The pine to its left (I&#8217;m not sure which variety) has only been in the ground for 18 months.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="457" height="740" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cedros-blancos.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150667" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cedros-blancos.jpg 457w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cedros-blancos-185x300.jpg 185w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>These </em>Cedros <em>may look skinny, but they have grown from a few inches to four feet in a year and a half. That&#8217;s an adult </em>Cedro<em> on another property, in the background.</em></p>



<p>The <em>ahuehuete</em>, or Mexican Bald Cypress, is a tree with a rich relationship to Mexican history. It is also beautiful, and is one of the few trees I have been willing to spend real money on (two-to-four dollars each). I now have three chest-high <em>ahuehuetes </em>growing on the lot, as they are well adapted to our wet/dry climate.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ahuehuete-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150644" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ahuehuete-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ahuehuete-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Ahuehuete.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>Bald Cypresses have soft needles that can drop in the winter, and will grow happily in swamps. But the Mexican Bald Cypress can handle our dry winters as well. I plant them on the wettest parts (in summer) of the church property.</em></p>



<p>Unfortunately, while conifers may be our easiest native trees to purchase, they do not offer all that much to birds in the way of food. In contrast, oak trees are our native avian supermarkets; but I have yet to find a reforestation or commercial nursery that offers them. So I have had to climb a steep learning curve to learn to grow them from seed, or rather, from acorn. Two oak seedlings I was given in 2018, by a botanical garden, are still growing today. Since then, I have managed to grow eight more from acorns. Half of these were started just last year, so I have real hope for the future. My goal is to someday achieve a typical Michoacan mix of 40% pines, 40% oaks, and 20% other tree species. (I picked up some 30 apparently viable acorns just this morning, for the next crop. Viable acorns don&#8217;t float in water.)</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Oldest-Oak-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150664" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Oldest-Oak-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Oldest-Oak-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Oldest-Oak.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>This is one of my two oldest oaks. It looks a bit shaggy now, during our dry winter. But It doubled in size last spring, so I would say we are off to the races.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/First-year-Oak-1-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150663" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/First-year-Oak-1-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/First-year-Oak-1-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/First-year-Oak-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>This lovely little oak was an acorn in June.</em></p>



<p>As for the other species, they include two <em>tejocotes </em>(Mexican Hawthorn, a tree that produces crabapple-like fruits), four <em>colorines</em>, a native coral tree that produces tubular red flowers for the hummingbirds, an equal number of <em>guamúchiles</em>, which produce seeds surrounded by an edible white pulp, one native chokecherry, one ash tree, a <em>parotilla</em>, and two <em>ceibas </em>(kapok tree). I have also planted many prickly pear seedlings and cuttings, as this cactus produces both flowers and fruit for birds. And I have protected and cared for other native plants that have turned up on their own, particularly <em>granjenos</em>, which have now begun to produce their first tasty red fruits.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="457" height="740" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tejocote.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150665" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tejocote.jpg 457w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Tejocote-185x300.jpg 185w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>After acting like a bush for several years, this </em>Tejocote <em>suddenly decided to be a tree this fall, and sent out this one leading shoot. I think it&#8217;s looking forward to a big 2023.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Guamuchil-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150646" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Guamuchil-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Guamuchil-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Guamuchil.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>This </em>Guamúchil <em>seedling is only 7 months old.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Granjeno-fruits-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150647" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Granjeno-fruits-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Granjeno-fruits-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Granjeno-fruits.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>You can barely see the first </em>Granjeno<em> fruits in the middle of this photo. They will eventually turn a deep red. Birds love them, and so do I.</em></p>



<p>Of course, a forest does not consist only of trees. I managed to successfully start some wild grape vines this summer. I also planted a purchased blackberry plant. And my botanist friend gifted me some <em>cucamelon </em>seeds; this wild cucumber (native to Mexico) looks exactly like a tiny watermelon. I hope to show a photo someday soon&#8230; but they have to sprout first.</p>



<p>I have also planted a good number of non-native ornamentals and fruit-producing trees in the more visible part of the property: citrus, jacarandas, mulberries, a peach and a guava, etc. This is a bit of a concession to what most people consider &#8220;a garden&#8221;. Pomegranate trees have also sprouted everywhere, because our home tree contributes excess  fruit to my compost piles. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="389" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Decorative-garden-zone-630x389.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150645" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Decorative-garden-zone-630x389.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Decorative-garden-zone-300x185.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Decorative-garden-zone.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>One of my 2022 projects was this traditional, non-native bit of a garden.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="457" height="740" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pomegranate.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-150658" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pomegranate.jpg 457w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Pomegranate-185x300.jpg 185w" sizes="(max-width: 457px) 100vw, 457px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><em>Pomegranate trees with fruit do an excellent imitation of Christmas trees. This one also decided to act like a tree a few months ago, and grew a couple of feet.</em></p>



<p>But my #1 goal continues to be the establishment of a self-sustained, diverse native forest. Unfortunately, that involves a temporary process of grass trimming, fire supression, and watering. But I am already watering the better-established trees much less, and once these grow deeper roots, get taller, and start shading out most grass and forbs, they should be fine left to their own resources. One pine tree, which attrition left too far from the other remaining trees for me to bother watering, has surprised me by doing just fine without it. The goal is in sight!</p>



<p>For the birds.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/afforestation-2022.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>3</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Year of Birding in Costa Rica- Highlights and a Few Birds Missed</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/a-year-of-birding-in-costa-rica-highlights-and-a-few-birds-missed.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/a-year-of-birding-in-costa-rica-highlights-and-a-few-birds-missed.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Patrick O'Donnell]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Destinations]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Costa Rica]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Costa Rica 2023]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150384</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Another year of birding in Costa Rica has come to an end, another one begins. What will the new year bring? I bet some tanager flocks will be in the cards; birding in Costa Rica tends to deliver. There should be a good number of hummingbirds and quetzals are waiting in the mountains. It&#8217;s 2023 already and I have already started this year of birding. No quetzal trips yet but a good start nonetheless. First birds came in the form of migrants and resident species that live in an oasis of precious green space near home. An Ovenbird chipping from coffee bushes, a Mourning Warbler in the dense grass. A male American Redstart flashed its Halloween finery and other birds flitted into view. A flash of blue and red, male Painted Bunting! Slow movement in the foliage of a lime tree, there&#8217;s a Yellow-throated Vireo doing its deliberate thing. A squadron of Brown Jays flaps overhead and a White-tailed Kite hovers into view. I&#8217;ll take those first birds of the year, I celebrate them and look forward to more. With those birds, I already have some highlights for 2023. 2022 gave me a fair share of wonderful birds and birding experiences. Despite a fair degree of effort, I also had some unexpected misses. Those kept me below the 700 species threshhold but I won&#8217;t complain about 691 species. I talk about my &#8220;best&#8221; year birds at my blog. These were some of the other many highlights of this past birding year. 48 Hummingbird Species In Costa Rica, seeing 48 hummingbird species means seeing nearly all of the regular ones. The one resident I missed was the Garden Emerald. Based on unwritten, invisible birding laws, this means I&#8217;ll probably run into one tomorrow. But seriously, my hummingbird total is a reminder that if you go birding enough in Costa Rica, you have a fair chance of seeing all expected hummingbirds. The White-bellied Mountain-Gem is one of my favorites. Most Raptors I also saw a high percentage of the raptor species possible in Costa Rica. No, there weren&#8217;t any sightings of ultra mega Crested Eagle or missing Solitary Eagle, or king Harpy Eagle on my part but I did connect with most of the rest. Hawk-eagles flapping butterfly wings high above rainforest, a Tiny Hawk at a popular feeding spot, cool Crane Hawks and Bicolored Hawk, and Hook-billed Kites and more. Missing was Great Black-Hawk, missing on account of not spending enough time looking in the right places and the species having undergone serious decline in Costa Rica over the past 20 years. I also failed to see a Pearl Kite, maybe one of my biggest misses of the year. The small shrike-kestrel size and demeanor of this beautiful little raptor make it seriously unobtrusive. I looked in some of the right places but failed to connect. Which also means I&#8217;ll see one soon. All Cotingas The cotingas are special, weird, and wonderful birds. In Costa Rica, some of them are also rare and hard to find. I don&#8217;t usually see all of them in a year but in 2022, luck and being in the right places worked to give me the following cotinga sweep: Rufous Piha&#8211; Go birding in the right lowland rainforest hotspots and you&#8217;ll hear the loud wolf whistles of this bird, probably see it too. I usually hear and see it in Carara, I may have also heard it at another one or two spots. Three-wattled Bellbird&#8211; Another vociferous bird much easier to hear than see. The challenge to seeing it in the high season before March is that most birds are not at Monteverde, most are in other, less accessible areas. Luckily, in one of the most unforgettable birding experiences of my life, at Curi-Cancha, I shared wonderful scoped looks of a male bellbird with old and new friends and birding mentors from Buffalo, NY. Turquoise Cotinga&#8211; Males at a patch of rainforest in the city of Perez Zeledon also seen with folks from Buffalo were the only ones I saw in 2022. Lovely Cotinga&#8211; Once again, the continuing male at Rancho Naturalista was shared with the same group from Buffalo. We had a number of excellent birds on that trip! Snowy Cotinga&#8211; Not seen that often but go birding in the right places and you will probably connect. I saw this cool bird near Limon, Sarapiqui, and at Cano Negro. Yellow-billed Cotinga&#8211; I had excellent looks of this surreal, endangered species at Cerro Lodge, and Rincon de Osa. Bare-necked Umbrellabird&#8211; Any view of this endangered species is a major event. Admiring a female at Centro Manu with my partner was a perfect way to end of a year of birding in Costa Rica. Purple-throated Fruitcrow&#8211; Like the Snowy Cotinga, if you go birding in the right places and know how to look for them, you should see fruitcrows. They seem to be doing especially well in forests near and south of Limon. Updating “How to See, Find, and Identify Birds in Costa Rica” An edited version of my bird finding ebook for Costa Rica was long overdue. It took a while to update it but I&#8217;m glad I did; since 2015, some places have closed and lot more places have opened. This second version includes most of the new places for birding in Costa Rica along with updates for all of the older, classic locales. Updating the Costa Rica Birds Field Guide app I&#8217;m also glad to have helped update the Costa Rica Birds Field Guide app with more images, new birds (a couple of birds are still added to the Costa Rica bird list every year!), and more information. To make the app as thorough as possible, more than 60 additional species that could occur are also included in this birding app for Costa Rica. Sharing Birds As always, the biggest highlight is having the chance to share so many birds in Costa Rica with my partner and many other people. I hope you...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Another year of birding in Costa Rica has come to an end, another one begins. What will the new year bring? I bet some tanager flocks will be in the cards; birding in Costa Rica tends to deliver. There should be a good number of hummingbirds and quetzals are waiting in the mountains. It&#8217;s 2023 already and I have already started this year of birding. No quetzal trips yet but a good start nonetheless. First birds came in the form of migrants and resident species that live in an <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/urban-birding-in-costa-rica-benefits-of-brushy-fields-and-coffee-farms.htm" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.10000birds.com/urban-birding-in-costa-rica-benefits-of-brushy-fields-and-coffee-farms.htm">oasis of precious green space</a> near home.</p>



<p>An <strong>Ovenbird </strong>chipping from coffee bushes, a <strong>Mourning Warbler</strong> in the dense grass. A male <strong>American Redstart</strong> flashed its Halloween finery and other birds flitted into view. A flash of blue and red, male <strong>Painted Bunting</strong>! Slow movement in the foliage of a lime tree, there&#8217;s a <strong>Yellow-throated Vireo </strong>doing its deliberate thing. A squadron of <strong>Brown Jays</strong> flaps overhead and a <strong>White-tailed Kite </strong>hovers into view. I&#8217;ll take those first birds of the year, I celebrate them and look forward to more. With those birds, I already have some highlights for 2023. 2022 gave me a fair share of wonderful birds and birding experiences. Despite a fair degree of effort, I also had some unexpected misses. Those kept me below the 700 species threshhold but I won&#8217;t complain about 691 species. I talk about <a href="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/2022/12/30/my-best-costa-rica-birds-of-2022/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/2022/12/30/my-best-costa-rica-birds-of-2022/">my &#8220;best&#8221; year birds at my blog</a>.</p>



<p>These were some of the other many highlights of this past birding year. </p>



<h4>48 Hummingbird Species</h4>



<p>In Costa Rica, seeing 48 hummingbird species means seeing nearly all of the regular ones. The one resident I missed was the <strong>Garden Emerald</strong>. Based on unwritten, invisible birding laws, this means I&#8217;ll probably run into one tomorrow. But seriously, my hummingbird total is a reminder that if you go birding enough in Costa Rica, you have a fair chance of seeing all expected hummingbirds.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="390" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-bellied-Mountain-gem-male-2-630x390.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-116516" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-bellied-Mountain-gem-male-2.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-bellied-Mountain-gem-male-2-300x186.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-bellied-Mountain-gem-male-2-600x371.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The <strong>White-bellied Mountain-Gem</strong> is one of my favorites.</figcaption></figure>



<h4>Most Raptors</h4>



<p>I also saw a high percentage of the raptor species possible in Costa Rica. No, there weren&#8217;t any sightings of ultra mega <strong>Crested Eagle </strong>or missing <strong>Solitary Eagle</strong>, or <a href="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/2022/07/31/harpy-eagle-seen-in-costa-rica-july-21-2022/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/2022/07/31/harpy-eagle-seen-in-costa-rica-july-21-2022/">king <strong>Harpy Eagle</strong></a><strong> </strong>on my part but I did connect with most of the rest. Hawk-eagles flapping butterfly wings high above rainforest, a <strong>Tiny Hawk</strong> at a popular feeding spot, cool <strong>Crane Hawks </strong>and <strong>Bicolored Hawk</strong>, and <strong>Hook-billed Kites</strong> and more. Missing was <strong>Great Black-Hawk</strong>, missing on account of not spending enough time looking in the right places and the species having undergone serious decline in Costa Rica over the past 20 years.</p>



<p>I also failed to see a <strong>Pearl Kite</strong>, maybe one of my biggest misses of the year. The small shrike-kestrel size and demeanor of this beautiful little raptor make it seriously unobtrusive. I looked in some of the right places but failed to connect. Which also means I&#8217;ll see one soon.</p>



<h4>All Cotingas</h4>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="390" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male-630x390.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-114328" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male-300x186.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male-150x93.jpg 150w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male-80x50.jpg 80w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Yellow-billed-Cotinga-male-137x85.jpg 137w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The cotingas are special, weird, and wonderful birds. In Costa Rica, some of them are also rare and hard to find. I don&#8217;t usually see all of them in a year but in 2022, luck and being in the right places worked to give me the following cotinga sweep:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Rufous Piha</strong>&#8211; Go birding in the right lowland rainforest hotspots and you&#8217;ll hear the loud wolf whistles of this bird, probably see it too. I usually hear and see it in Carara, I may have also heard it at another one or two spots.</li>



<li><strong>Three-wattled Bellbird</strong>&#8211; Another vociferous bird much easier to hear than see. The challenge to seeing it in the high season before March is that most birds are not at Monteverde, most are in other, less accessible areas. Luckily, in one of the most unforgettable birding experiences of my life, at Curi-Cancha, I shared wonderful scoped looks of a male bellbird with old and new friends and birding mentors from Buffalo, NY.</li>



<li><strong>Turquoise Cotinga</strong>&#8211; Males at a patch of rainforest in the city of Perez Zeledon also seen with folks from Buffalo were the only ones I saw in 2022.</li>



<li><strong>Lovely Cotinga</strong>&#8211; Once again, the continuing male at Rancho Naturalista was shared with the same group from Buffalo. We had a number of excellent birds on that trip!</li>



<li><strong>Snowy Cotinga</strong>&#8211; Not seen that often but go birding in the right places and you will probably connect. I saw this cool bird near Limon, Sarapiqui, and at Cano Negro.</li>



<li><strong>Yellow-billed Cotinga</strong>&#8211; I had excellent looks of this surreal, endangered species at Cerro Lodge, and Rincon de Osa.</li>



<li><strong>Bare-necked Umbrellabird</strong>&#8211; Any view of this endangered species is a major event. Admiring a female at Centro Manu with my partner was a perfect way to end of a year of birding in Costa Rica.</li>



<li><strong>Purple-throated Fruitcrow</strong>&#8211; Like the Snowy Cotinga, if you go birding in the right places and know how to look for them, you should see fruitcrows. They seem to be doing especially well in forests near and south of Limon.</li>
</ul>



<h4>Updating “How to See, Find, and Identify Birds in Costa Rica”</h4>



<p>An edited version of my <a href="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/wherehowfind-birds-in-costa-rica/" data-type="URL" data-id="https://birdingcraft.com/wordpress/wherehowfind-birds-in-costa-rica/">bird finding ebook for Costa Rica </a>was long overdue. It took a while to update it but I&#8217;m glad I did; since 2015, some places have closed and lot more places have opened. This second version includes most of the new places for birding in Costa Rica along with updates for all of the older, classic locales.</p>



<h4>Updating the Costa Rica Birds Field Guide app</h4>



<p>I&#8217;m also glad to have helped update the Costa Rica Birds Field Guide app with more images, new birds (a couple of birds are still added to the Costa Rica bird list every year!), and more information. To make the app as thorough as possible, more than 60 additional species that could occur are also included in this <a href="https://www.birdingfieldguides.com/costarica.html" data-type="URL" data-id="https://www.birdingfieldguides.com/costarica.html">birding app for Costa Rica</a>.</p>



<h4>Sharing Birds</h4>



<p>As always, the biggest highlight is having the chance to share so many birds in Costa Rica with my partner and many other people. I hope you make it here to experience the incredible avian life of this birdy nation. There&#8217;s a lot of fantastic birding going on around here!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/a-year-of-birding-in-costa-rica-highlights-and-a-few-birds-missed.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Some common birds of Shennongjia, China</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/some-common-birds-of-shennongjia-china.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/some-common-birds-of-shennongjia-china.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Kai Pflug]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 12:00:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=144587</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The photos in this post were taken in 2015 and 2016 &#8211; I was not only an amazingly attractive, almost young person then, but also a surprisingly bad photographer. I also only managed to see rather common bird species at Shennongjia, a nature reserve in Hubei province, China. If this does not put you off from reading this post, you are hopeless anyway, so just proceed &#8230; The Brown-breasted Bulbul might well be the most common bird at Shennongjia, so it seems appropriate to start with it. &#160; This photo of a Buff-throated Warbler (I hope it is, anyway &#8211; Bella from Alpinebirding will probably correct me in a comment if I am wrong) is remarkable for both the number of insects in the bird&#8217;s bill and my amazing incapability to utilize noise reduction to smoothen the background. Fortunately, some birds like this rather wonderful Chinese Babax family with chicks let me get close enough &#8211; and in decent enough light &#8211; that smoothening the background was not much of an issue. &#160; &#160; &#160; If you see a Collared Finchbill before it has washed its face and brushed its teeth in the morning, it looks like this. &#8220;You could have waited to take the photo until I have taken my bath, couldn&#8217;t you?&#8221; &#160; &#160; &#160; (yes, I know, too many photos of this one, but I love its colors) &#160; &#8220;Please take me with some red objects &#8211; it highlights my nice green color&#8221;. &#8220;Natural reddish tones would be even nicer&#8221;. My lawyer told me just to call this a Cuckoo species so there will be no lawsuits from irate birders with better bird id skills than mine. If you think this Daurian Redstart looks bad, remember how unattractive you looked at certain times when you were a teenager. Whenever the wagtails have a family gathering in somebody&#8217;s home, you can usually find the Forrest Wagtail in the kitchen as this is closest to their natural forest habitat &#8211; not out in the open in the living room. In the past, Great Spotted Woodpeckers mostly lived off renting out their old apartments to other species. In many Western markets, this is no longer a reliable income stream as the market has been flooded with birdhouses put up by well-meaning humans not realizing that this completely destroys the property market. Fortunately for the Great Spotted Woodpecker living in Shennongjia, this has not happened here yet. &#160; The photo below shows the zygodactyl toe arrangement (two toes to the front, two to the back) useful for climbing trees &#8230; &#160; &#8230; while this one shows how the stiff tail feathers are used as a prop against the trunk. Feeding on moths, as this Green-backed Tit does, is not particularly environmentally friendly as a large share of the moth &#8211; particularly the wings &#8211; is inedible and thus is just being discarded on the spot. Grey-capped Greenfinches apparently are a bit like the American population (see, e.g., &#8220;The rise in positive assortative mating&#8220;) and Hollywood stars in particular, in that high-quality individuals prefer to mate with each other, rather than with nobodies. This is described by two Chinese scientists who could do with somebody to help them correct their English-language papers. The finding itself is not very surprising though &#8211; it would be kind of weird if socially monogamous birds of both sexes were not to try to find the highest-quality partner. Yes, it looks kind of plain. But does it deserve to be named Plain Flowerpecker? A bit of kindness in naming birds could go a long way. A male Plumbeous Water Redstart is in this weird transition phase where there are already the first stubbles of facial hair appearing but buying a razor is still a waste of money. A Red-billed Blue Magpie pretending to be a wet dog. If you ever wondered why anyone would go to the movies and watch a Jean-Claude Van Damme movie, the lyrics of &#8220;Inferno&#8221; by the Felice Brothers provide an answer (&#8220;Fight Club was sold out. We went to see Inferno instead.&#8221;) I started this paragraph without having any idea how to link this song to the Chestnut-bellied Rock Thrush. I still have no idea. Ideas welcome. I frantically searched the internet for a (presumably British) naturalist/ornithologist with the surname Russet (Lord Elgar Russet?) before discovering that russet means &#8220;reddish-brown in color&#8221;. Takes some of the mystery out of the Russet Sparrow, I am afraid. &#160; &#160; &#160; &#160; The Verditer Flycatcher has found an interesting way to avoid being parasitized by cuckoos.  It feeds newly hatched chicks entirely with beetles and grasshoppers. These are poor quality and hard-to-digest diet items that are rarely fed to chicks by regular cuckoo hosts (source). Kind of like kicking the bum roommate or partner out by only preparing really bad food. As a consequence, even though the Verditer Flycatcher does not discriminate against foreign eggs, no cuckoo species has found a viable way to turn it into a useful stepparent. &#160; &#160; &#8220;Hey, it&#8217;s such a beautiful sunny day! Why don&#8217;t we all go to our local pool and have a bath!&#8221; (Vinous-throated Parrotbills) (there probably is one bird about one meter away from the little pool, just trying to stay away from the crowd a bit. I identify with that individual) Coming back to brood parasitism: The White-browed Laughingthrush is most likely an original host of the Large Hawk-Cuckoo. However, with time it has gotten better at rejecting eggs that do not mimic its own eggs well. The authors of this paper think that this may have led to the Large Hawk-Cuckoo partially switching to another host species, the Chinese Babax (see photos above), as this species is not as good at rejecting non-matching eggs yet (source). &#160; &#160; Finally, some more reading material as a reward to those who have gotten this far: “The Bear Who Let It Alone” by James Thurber.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The photos in this post were taken in 2015 and 2016 &#8211; I was not only an amazingly attractive, almost young person then, but also a surprisingly bad photographer. I also only managed to see rather common bird species at Shennongjia, a nature reserve in Hubei province, China.</p>



<p>If this does not put you off from reading this post, you are hopeless anyway, so just proceed &#8230;</p>



<p>The <strong>Brown-breasted Bulbul</strong> might well be the most common bird at Shennongjia, so it seems appropriate to start with it.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="696" class="wp-image-144607" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC8350-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x696.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC8350-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x696.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC8350-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-272x300.jpg 272w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC8350-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x849.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC8350-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1086w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="520" class="wp-image-144604" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC0057-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x520.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC0057-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x520.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC0057-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-300x248.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC0057-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-768x634.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Brown-breasted-Bulbul_DSC0057-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>This photo of a <strong>Buff-throated Warbler</strong> (I hope it is, anyway &#8211; Bella from Alpinebirding will probably correct me in a comment if I am wrong) is remarkable for both the number of insects in the bird&#8217;s bill and my amazing incapability to utilize noise reduction to smoothen the background.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="558" class="wp-image-144608" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Buff-throated-warbler-DSC_4194-Shennongjia-0615-630x558.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Buff-throated-warbler-DSC_4194-Shennongjia-0615-630x558.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Buff-throated-warbler-DSC_4194-Shennongjia-0615-300x266.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Buff-throated-warbler-DSC_4194-Shennongjia-0615-768x680.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Buff-throated-warbler-DSC_4194-Shennongjia-0615.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Fortunately, some birds like this rather wonderful <strong>Chinese Babax</strong> family with chicks let me get close enough &#8211; and in decent enough light &#8211; that smoothening the background was not much of an issue.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="471" class="wp-image-144611" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6943-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x471.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6943-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x471.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6943-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6943-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-768x575.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6943-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="630" class="wp-image-144610" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x630.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x630.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC5947-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="337" class="wp-image-144612" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6216-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x337.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6216-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x337.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6216-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-300x160.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6216-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x410.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6216-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="525" class="wp-image-144609" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6769-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x525.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6769-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x525.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6769-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-300x250.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6769-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-768x640.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Chinese-Babax_DSC6769-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>If you see a <strong>Collared Finchbill</strong> before it has washed its face and brushed its teeth in the morning, it looks like this.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="514" class="wp-image-144626" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_4538-Shennongjia-0815-2-630x514.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_4538-Shennongjia-0815-2-630x514.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_4538-Shennongjia-0815-2-300x245.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_4538-Shennongjia-0815-2-768x627.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_4538-Shennongjia-0815-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;You could have waited to take the photo until I have taken my bath, couldn&#8217;t you?&#8221;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="472" class="wp-image-144638" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7399-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x472.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7399-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x472.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7399-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7399-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-768x575.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7399-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="478" class="wp-image-144639" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC3882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x478.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC3882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x478.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC3882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-300x228.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC3882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-768x583.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC3882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="485" class="wp-image-144632" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7397-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x485.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7397-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x485.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7397-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-300x231.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7397-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-768x591.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC7397-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="708" class="wp-image-144633" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC2816-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x708.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC2816-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x708.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC2816-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-267x300.jpg 267w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC2816-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x863.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill_DSC2816-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1068w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>(yes, I know, too many photos of this one, but I love its colors)</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="496" class="wp-image-144635" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3000a-Shennongjia-0815-2-630x496.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3000a-Shennongjia-0815-2-630x496.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3000a-Shennongjia-0815-2-300x236.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3000a-Shennongjia-0815-2-768x605.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3000a-Shennongjia-0815-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="537" class="wp-image-144631" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-finchbill-DSC_3022-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x537.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-finchbill-DSC_3022-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x537.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-finchbill-DSC_3022-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x256.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-finchbill-DSC_3022-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x655.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-finchbill-DSC_3022-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;Please take me with some red objects &#8211; it highlights my nice green color&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="512" class="wp-image-144637" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3070-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x512.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3070-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x512.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3070-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x244.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3070-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x625.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3070-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;Natural reddish tones would be even nicer&#8221;.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="489" class="wp-image-144636" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3891-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x489.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3891-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x489.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3891-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x233.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3891-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x596.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Collared-Finchbill-DSC_3891-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>My lawyer told me just to call this a <strong>Cuckoo species</strong> so there will be no lawsuits from irate birders with better bird id skills than mine.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="528" class="wp-image-144640" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cuckoo-DSC_3570-Shennongjia-0615-630x528.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cuckoo-DSC_3570-Shennongjia-0615-630x528.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cuckoo-DSC_3570-Shennongjia-0615-300x251.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cuckoo-DSC_3570-Shennongjia-0615-768x643.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Cuckoo-DSC_3570-Shennongjia-0615.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>If you think this <strong>Daurian Redstart</strong> looks bad, remember how unattractive you looked at certain times when you were a teenager.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="602" class="wp-image-144641" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Daurian-Redstart_DSC5811-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x602.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Daurian-Redstart_DSC5811-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x602.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Daurian-Redstart_DSC5811-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x287.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Daurian-Redstart_DSC5811-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x734.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Daurian-Redstart_DSC5811-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Whenever the wagtails have a family gathering in somebody&#8217;s home, you can usually find the <strong>Forrest Wagtail</strong> in the kitchen as this is closest to their natural forest habitat &#8211; not out in the open in the living room.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="439" class="wp-image-144642" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Forrest-Wagtail_DSC7882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x439.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Forrest-Wagtail_DSC7882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x439.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Forrest-Wagtail_DSC7882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x209.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Forrest-Wagtail_DSC7882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x535.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Forrest-Wagtail_DSC7882-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>In the past, <strong>Great Spotted Woodpeckers</strong> mostly lived off renting out their old apartments to other species. In many Western markets, this is no longer a reliable income stream as the market has been flooded with birdhouses put up by well-meaning humans not realizing that this completely destroys the property market. Fortunately for the <strong>Great Spotted Woodpecke</strong>r living in Shennongjia, this has not happened here yet.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="679" class="wp-image-144660" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC8087-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x679.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC8087-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-630x679.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC8087-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-279x300.jpg 279w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC8087-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3-768x827.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC8087-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-3.jpg 1114w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="679" class="wp-image-144664" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC5530-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x679.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC5530-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x679.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC5530-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-278x300.jpg 278w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC5530-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x828.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC5530-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1082w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The photo below shows the zygodactyl toe arrangement (two toes to the front, two to the back) useful for climbing trees &#8230;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="493" class="wp-image-144659" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7501_2-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x493.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7501_2-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x493.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7501_2-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-300x235.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7501_2-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x601.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7501_2-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="670" class="wp-image-144643" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7935-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x670.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7935-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x670.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7935-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-282x300.jpg 282w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7935-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x816.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7935-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1129w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8230; while this one shows how the stiff tail feathers are used as a prop against the trunk.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="618" class="wp-image-144661" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7965-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x618.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7965-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x618.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7965-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-300x294.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7965-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x753.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Great-spotted-Woodpecker_DSC7965-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Feeding on moths, as this <strong>Green-backed Tit</strong> does, is not particularly environmentally friendly as a large share of the moth &#8211; particularly the wings &#8211; is inedible and thus is just being discarded on the spot.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="464" class="wp-image-144666" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-backed-Tit-DSC_3625-Shennongjia-0815-630x464.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-backed-Tit-DSC_3625-Shennongjia-0815-630x464.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-backed-Tit-DSC_3625-Shennongjia-0815-300x221.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-backed-Tit-DSC_3625-Shennongjia-0815-768x566.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Green-backed-Tit-DSC_3625-Shennongjia-0815.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Grey-capped Greenfinch</strong>es apparently are a bit like the American population (see, e.g., &#8220;<a href="https://voxeu.org/article/us-income-inequality-and-assortative-marriages">The rise in positive assortative mating</a>&#8220;) and Hollywood stars in particular, in that high-quality individuals prefer to mate with each other, rather than with nobodies. This is <a href="https://researcherslinks.com/uploads/articles/1621413799PJZ_MH20201123101105-R1_Shang%20and%20Liu.pdf">described</a> by two Chinese scientists who could do with somebody to help them correct their English-language papers.</p>



<p>The finding itself is not very surprising though &#8211; it would be kind of weird if socially monogamous birds of both sexes were not to try to find the highest-quality partner.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="510" class="wp-image-144667" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-capped-Greenfinch_DSC6619-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x510.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-capped-Greenfinch_DSC6619-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x510.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-capped-Greenfinch_DSC6619-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x243.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-capped-Greenfinch_DSC6619-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x621.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Grey-capped-Greenfinch_DSC6619-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Yes, it looks kind of plain. But does it deserve to be named <strong>Plain Flowerpecker</strong>? A bit of kindness in naming birds could go a long way.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="461" class="wp-image-144668" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plain-Flowerpecker-DSC_3196-Shennongjia-0815-630x461.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plain-Flowerpecker-DSC_3196-Shennongjia-0815-630x461.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plain-Flowerpecker-DSC_3196-Shennongjia-0815-300x220.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plain-Flowerpecker-DSC_3196-Shennongjia-0815-768x562.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plain-Flowerpecker-DSC_3196-Shennongjia-0815.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>A male <strong>Plumbeous Water Redstart</strong> is in this weird transition phase where there are already the first stubbles of facial hair appearing but buying a razor is still a waste of money.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="478" class="wp-image-144669" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumbeous-water-redstart-DSC_5522-Shennongjia-0815-630x478.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumbeous-water-redstart-DSC_5522-Shennongjia-0815-630x478.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumbeous-water-redstart-DSC_5522-Shennongjia-0815-300x228.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumbeous-water-redstart-DSC_5522-Shennongjia-0815-768x583.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Plumbeous-water-redstart-DSC_5522-Shennongjia-0815.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>A <strong>Red-billed Blue Magpie</strong> pretending to be a wet dog.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="422" class="wp-image-144670" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x422.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x422.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x514.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-120x80.jpg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-255x170.jpg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-345x230.jpg 345w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Redbilled-Blue-Magpie_DSC6361-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>If you ever wondered why anyone would go to the movies and watch a Jean-Claude Van Damme movie, the lyrics of &#8220;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tO48acFJZOs">Inferno</a>&#8221; by the Felice Brothers provide an answer (&#8220;Fight Club was sold out. We went to see Inferno instead.&#8221;) I started this paragraph without having any idea how to link this song to the <strong>Chestnut-bellied Rock Thrush</strong>. I still have no idea. Ideas welcome.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="544" class="wp-image-144671" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rufous-bellied-Niltava-DSC_3072-Shennongjia-0615-630x544.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rufous-bellied-Niltava-DSC_3072-Shennongjia-0615-630x544.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rufous-bellied-Niltava-DSC_3072-Shennongjia-0615-300x259.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rufous-bellied-Niltava-DSC_3072-Shennongjia-0615-768x663.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Rufous-bellied-Niltava-DSC_3072-Shennongjia-0615.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>I frantically searched the internet for a (presumably British) naturalist/ornithologist with the surname Russet (Lord Elgar Russet?) before discovering that russet means &#8220;reddish-brown in color&#8221;. Takes some of the mystery out of the <strong>Russet Sparrow</strong>, I am afraid.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="526" class="wp-image-144677" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow-DSC_5257-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x526.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow-DSC_5257-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x526.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow-DSC_5257-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x251.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow-DSC_5257-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x641.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow-DSC_5257-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="543" class="wp-image-144678" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1538-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x543.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1538-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x543.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1538-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-300x259.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1538-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-768x662.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1538-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="716" class="wp-image-144679" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1551-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x716.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1551-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-630x716.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1551-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-264x300.jpg 264w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1551-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1-768x873.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russett-Sparrow_DSC1551-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-1.jpg 1056w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="470" class="wp-image-144680" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_2685-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x470.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_2685-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x470.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_2685-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x224.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_2685-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x573.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_2685-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="459" class="wp-image-144681" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_3737-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x459.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_3737-Shennongjia-0815-1-630x459.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_3737-Shennongjia-0815-1-300x219.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_3737-Shennongjia-0815-1-768x560.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Russet-Sparrow-DSC_3737-Shennongjia-0815-1.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>The <strong>Verditer Flycatcher</strong> has found an interesting way to avoid being parasitized by cuckoos.  It feeds newly hatched chicks entirely with beetles and grasshoppers. These are poor quality and hard-to-digest diet items that are rarely fed to chicks by regular cuckoo hosts (<a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1600-048X.2013.00123.x">source</a>). Kind of like kicking the bum roommate or partner out by only preparing really bad food.</p>



<p>As a consequence, even though the <strong>Verditer Flycatcher</strong> does not discriminate against foreign eggs, no cuckoo species has found a viable way to turn it into a useful stepparent.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="626" class="wp-image-144682" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x626.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x626.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x298.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x763.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC0164-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="442" class="wp-image-144691" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC3297-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x442.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC3297-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x442.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC3297-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-300x210.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC3297-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x538.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC3297-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="454" class="wp-image-144690" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC6588-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x454.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC6588-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-630x454.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC6588-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-300x216.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC6588-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2-768x554.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Verditer-Flycatcher_DSC6588-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-2.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&#8220;Hey, it&#8217;s such a beautiful sunny day! Why don&#8217;t we all go to our local pool and have a bath!&#8221; (<strong>Vinous-throated Parrotbills</strong>)</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="437" class="wp-image-144692" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Vinous-throated-Parrotbill_DSC7794-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x437.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Vinous-throated-Parrotbill_DSC7794-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x437.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Vinous-throated-Parrotbill_DSC7794-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x208.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Vinous-throated-Parrotbill_DSC7794-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x532.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/Vinous-throated-Parrotbill_DSC7794-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>(there probably is one bird about one meter away from the little pool, just trying to stay away from the crowd a bit. I identify with that individual)</p>



<p>Coming back to brood parasitism: The <strong>White-browed Laughingthrush</strong> is most likely an original host of the Large Hawk-Cuckoo. However, with time it has gotten better at rejecting eggs that do not mimic its own eggs well. The authors of this paper think that this may have led to the Large Hawk-Cuckoo partially switching to another host species, the Chinese Babax (see photos above), as this species is not as good at rejecting non-matching eggs yet (<a href="https://academic.oup.com/biolinnean/article/115/4/919/2440172?login=true">source</a>).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="435" class="wp-image-144693" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC2669-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x435.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC2669-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x435.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC2669-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x207.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC2669-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x531.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC2669-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="467" class="wp-image-144694" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x467.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x467.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x223.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x570.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-590x437.jpg 590w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3499-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="630" height="513" class="wp-image-144695" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3573-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x513.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3573-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-630x513.jpg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3573-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-300x245.jpg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3573-Shennongjia-Aug-2016-768x626.jpg 768w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/White-browed-Laughingthrush_DSC3573-Shennongjia-Aug-2016.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 630px) 100vw, 630px" /></figure>



<p>Finally, some more reading material as a reward to those who have gotten this far:</p>



<p><a href="https://bassocontinuosch.blogspot.com/2009/10/fables-for-our-time-bear-who-let-it.html">“The Bear Who Let It Alone”</a> by James Thurber.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/some-common-birds-of-shennongjia-china.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Reptilian Interloper</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/the-reptilian-interloper.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/the-reptilian-interloper.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Faraaz Abdool]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birding]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Birds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[caiman]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interspecies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Trinidad and Tobago]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[waterfowl]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150437</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I would say it was just another mundane morning at the treatment ponds in SW Tobago &#8211; but this wouldn&#8217;t be true no matter how convenient the framing would be to set the stage for this post. Several migratory species were around &#8211; I&#8217;ll touch on these in a subsequent post &#8211; but all was quiet and calm nevertheless. Ducks and grebes paddled around, Anhingas swam beneath the surface, occasionally appearing with a skewered fish. A Black Skimmer drifted from one end of the pond to the other, oftentimes coming into such proximity that the swishing of its feathers was audible. I had been visiting the ponds for the ducks, but stayed for the general ambience. An Anhinga tosses her freshly caught breakfast. Black Skimmer Two immature Least Grebes approach an adult, asking kindly for a snack. After about an hour, I noticed an unfamiliar presence: a Spectacled Caiman! These small crocodilians pose no threat to humans, but I had never before seen one in these ponds. Sure enough, I wondered about their presence as there was ample food available &#8211; fish and aquatic invertebrates &#8211; but hadn&#8217;t seen one up until this particular morning. As the caiman blinked its eyes and lay motionless in the water, it became apparent that I wasn&#8217;t the only one surprised by its presence. A Least Grebe began a tentative approach, its bright yellow eyes affixed on the caiman. Slowly, it got closer. And closer. Was it going to waltz into becoming breakfast? Maybe the grebe had never seen a Spectacled Caiman before? Perhaps the bird was trying to get a closer view, so as to reference the images of possible threats it learned as a young bird? Oh, how the things you learn in school very rapidly vaporize once adulthood sets in&#8230; My assessment of the situation was that the grebe made a very ideal-sized meal for the caiman. It seemed as if it was almost the perfect size. As I was pondering this, making the calculations of caiman jaw size versus grebe roundness &#8211; the bird suddenly panicked, as humans do when they bump into something unfamiliar in the dark. As comical as it was, the caiman didn&#8217;t seem too amused by the whole thing, and began to lazily swim off toward the other end of the pond. Which attracted more attention from the twenty-or-so Least Grebes in the pond. Adults and juveniles all surrounded the beast, while keeping a respectable distance. Eventually the caiman disappeared and equilibrium was restored. I spoke with some other birders who also remarked on seeing the caiman for the first time. Did I witness the initiation of the caiman into life in this treatment pond? I&#8217;ve seen the species mentioned here happily coexisting in other places, so I didn&#8217;t expect curiosity from either party. But nature continues to emphasize the point that species are not individuals.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I would say it was just another mundane morning at the treatment ponds in SW Tobago &#8211; but this wouldn&#8217;t be true no matter how convenient the framing would be to set the stage for this post. Several migratory species were around &#8211; I&#8217;ll touch on these in a subsequent post &#8211; but all was quiet and calm nevertheless. </p>



<p>Ducks and grebes paddled around, Anhingas swam beneath the surface, occasionally appearing with a skewered fish. A <strong>Black Skimmer</strong> drifted from one end of the pond to the other, oftentimes coming into such proximity that the swishing of its feathers was audible. I had been visiting the ponds for the ducks, but stayed for the general ambience. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="494" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663-.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150440" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663-.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663--300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663--630x421.jpeg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663--120x80.jpeg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663--255x170.jpeg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/anhinga-6663--345x230.jpeg 345w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">An <strong>Anhinga</strong> tosses her freshly caught breakfast.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="494" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150441" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811-630x421.jpeg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811-120x80.jpeg 120w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811-255x170.jpeg 255w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/black-skimmer-6811-345x230.jpeg 345w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center"><strong>Black Skimmer</strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="740" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-6779-.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150442" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-6779-.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-6779--300x300.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-6779--630x630.jpeg 630w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-6779--150x150.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p class="has-text-align-center">Two immature <strong>Least Grebes</strong> approach an adult, asking kindly for a snack.</p>



<p>After about an hour, I noticed an unfamiliar presence: a Spectacled Caiman! These small crocodilians pose no threat to humans, but I had never before seen one in these ponds. Sure enough, I wondered about their presence as there was ample food available &#8211; fish and aquatic invertebrates &#8211; but hadn&#8217;t seen one up until this particular morning. </p>



<p>As the caiman blinked its eyes and lay motionless in the water, it became apparent that I wasn&#8217;t the only one surprised by its presence. A <strong>Least Grebe</strong> began a tentative approach, its bright yellow eyes affixed on the caiman. Slowly, it got closer. And closer. Was it going to waltz into becoming breakfast?</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="416" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6822.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150443" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6822.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6822-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6822-630x354.jpeg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p>Maybe the grebe had never seen a Spectacled Caiman before? Perhaps the bird was trying to get a closer view, so as to reference the images of possible threats it learned as a young bird? Oh, how the things you learn in school very rapidly vaporize once adulthood sets in&#8230;</p>



<p>My assessment of the situation was that the grebe made a very ideal-sized meal for the caiman. It seemed as if it was almost the perfect size. As I was pondering this, making the calculations of caiman jaw size versus grebe roundness &#8211; the bird suddenly panicked, as humans do when they bump into something unfamiliar in the dark. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="416" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6828.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150444" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6828.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6828-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6828-630x354.jpeg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p>As comical as it was, the caiman didn&#8217;t seem too amused by the whole thing, and began to lazily swim off toward the other end of the pond. Which attracted <em>more</em> attention from the twenty-or-so <strong>Least Grebes</strong> in the pond. Adults and juveniles all surrounded the beast, while keeping a respectable distance. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="740" height="416" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6829.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-150445" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6829.jpeg 740w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6829-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/least-grebe-and-spectacled-caiman-6829-630x354.jpeg 630w" sizes="(max-width: 740px) 100vw, 740px" /></figure></div>


<p>Eventually the caiman disappeared and equilibrium was restored. I spoke with some other birders who also remarked on seeing the caiman for the first time. Did I witness the initiation of the caiman into life in this treatment pond? I&#8217;ve seen the species mentioned here happily coexisting in other places, so I didn&#8217;t expect curiosity from either party. But nature continues to emphasize the point that species are not individuals.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/the-reptilian-interloper.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Baby Bird Identification: A North American Guide&#8211;A Book Review</title>
		<link>https://www.10000birds.com/baby-bird-identification-a-north-american-guide-a-book-review.htm</link>
					<comments>https://www.10000birds.com/baby-bird-identification-a-north-american-guide-a-book-review.htm#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Donna]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 12:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Reviews]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[baby birds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[identification]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.10000birds.com/?p=150410</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Everyone loves baby birds; 10,000 Birds even had a Baby Bird Week once upon a time! Baby birds are cuteness personified, possibly even more so than other baby animals, including human babies, and pose interesting questions of survival and development. So, I was intrigued when I saw that Comstock Publishing, an arm of Cornell University Press, was publishing Baby Bird Identification: A North American Guide by Linda Tuttle-Adams. An impressive combination of research and artwork, combined with a pragmatic organization aimed towards quick identification, and education, Baby Bird Identification extends the frontiers of bird identification guides and is an important contribution to wildlife rehabilitation literature. There is a question that took some time to occur to me, though I&#8217;m sure most readers thought of it immediately: &#8220;Why would anyone need an identification guide to baby birds? Aren&#8217;t they usually in their nest with their parents?&#8221; A wildlife rehabber like Linda Tuttle-Adams, or our own Suzy Gilbert, would probably laugh at that question since they are apparently often brought or hear reports about baby birds found on the ground, no adult bird in sight. Baby birds may be separated from the nest and their parents because of natural occurrences (violent weather, floods) or unknowing human interference or predators. Figuring out who the parent is may be difficult because baby birds do not look like adult birds at first or even second glance, especially altricial nestlings who have still not developed. Tuttle-Adams stresses that identification is essential to helping those hatchlings, nestlings, and chicks who need help (she also stresses that the baby bird may NOT need human intervention), and that &#8220;a misidentification may be more harmful than no identification&#8221; (p.7). This guide comes out of Tuttle-Adams years in wildlife rehabilitation and her recognition of the need for an easily available resource that synthesizes data for species nesting in North America, one that allows rehabbers and other ornithological practitioners to quickly identify birds without hours of Internet searching and fighting through academic gateways. It covers 403 species: 172 nonpasserine species and 231 passerine species in the Species Accounts, 198 species beautifully illustrated by the author in the Plates section. Birds were selected based on (1) information available; (2) information available elsewhere (thus an emphasis on altricial species and limited waterfowl coverage, since they can be found elsewhere); (3) species most commonly encountered. The scarcity of information on the young of some avian species is astounding. I never realized how little information we have on wood warbler nestlings or knew how secretive their nesting habits can be. I am puzzled as to why Gulls and Terns are almost passed over, with less than two pages of text devoted to a family description and only six species accounts (four gulls, two terns). Species Accounts are organized by family according to the 61st Supplement (2020) of the AOS Checklist of North and Middle American Birds (the 62nd Supplement came out while the book was in production, which is to be expected). The summary of shared family characteristics is an important element of the Accounts, meant to help the user narrow down the baby bird identification to family group. The Species Accounts themselves vary in length and detail, depending on information available and necessary for identification. Almost a whole page of measurement data, plumage and bill description, and diet for adult, nestling, and fledgling Ravens; a brief paragraph on the measurements and plumage of adult, nestling, and fledgling Cliff Swallows. Family follows family with no page break, making this section a little dense. Light-blue colored headings for family and species names and capitalization of family names helps the eye focus on information. References to plate numbers (in the Plates section) and photograph numbers (in a Photo Gallery) are also placed prominently next to species name. Not all species accounts have corresponding plates or photographs. &#160; copyright © 2022 by Cornell University, Plate 12, pages 294-295 Here is an example of one of the 36 plates, presenting Belted Kingfisher (ABA Bird of the Year!) and three of the nine woodpeckers illustrated. Woodpeckers are a family of focus for Tuttle-Adams. Woodpeckers nest in cavities and their young are altricial (born in an undeveloped state), which means there is not a lot of documented information about their young and how they look at different stages. They may look very different at various growth stages, as she shows with Acorn Woodpecker. The number of stages illustrated vary for each species, with less for precocial species (born at a mature stage) and for species, like Wood-Warblers, about which we have scarce information. As noted above, not all species in the Accounts are illustrated, and I&#8217;m disappointed at the absence of a baby Piping Plover, my favorite baby bird. Tuttle-Adams artwork is exquisitely drawn and finely colored; she succeeds in communicating the adorableness of each baby bird without sacrificing the detail necessary for accurate and useful scientific illustration. The last subsection of the Species Accounts is the Photo Gallery, 66 small images of what appears to be photos of baby birds in rehab care taken by the author and rehab colleagues. These are mainly western species, a reflection of the author&#8217;s location. Many are hatchling birds and it&#8217;s a little startling to see their naked vulnerability. I would have like a little more explanation of where the photos came from and what stories they represent. But perhaps that&#8217;s for a different book. The chapters preceding the Species Accounts are important for rehabilitation identification: texts on baby bird anatomy and development, the importance of bird identification to the rehab process, and a systematic identification process. The anatomy chapter goes deep into mouths and beaks&#8211;features often essential to baby bird identification. We don&#8217;t think about mouth color when we identify adult birds, but they are important clues to narrowing down taxonomic families. Beaks, on the other hand, help identify a nestling in the same way they help identify an adult&#8211;plumage may change with age, but the shape and structure of a beak often remains...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Everyone loves baby birds; 10,000 Birds even had a <a href="https://www.10000birds.com/baby-bird-week-roundup.htm">Baby Bird Week</a> once upon a time! Baby birds are cuteness personified, possibly even more so than other baby animals, including human babies, and pose interesting questions of survival and development. So, I was intrigued when I saw that Comstock Publishing, an arm of Cornell University Press, was publishing <em><strong>Baby Bird Identification: A North American Guide</strong></em> by Linda Tuttle-Adams. An impressive combination of research and artwork, combined with a pragmatic organization aimed towards quick identification, and education, <em>Baby Bird Identification</em> extends the frontiers of bird identification guides and is an important contribution to wildlife rehabilitation literature.</p>
<p>There is a question that took some time to occur to me, though I&#8217;m sure most readers thought of it immediately: &#8220;Why would anyone need an identification guide to baby birds? Aren&#8217;t they usually in their nest with their parents?&#8221; A wildlife rehabber like Linda Tuttle-Adams, or our own Suzy Gilbert, would probably laugh at that question since they are apparently often brought or hear reports about baby birds found on the ground, no adult bird in sight. Baby birds may be separated from the nest and their parents because of natural occurrences (violent weather, floods) or unknowing human interference or predators. Figuring out who the parent is may be difficult because baby birds do not look like adult birds at first or even second glance, especially altricial nestlings who have still not developed. Tuttle-Adams stresses that identification is essential to helping those hatchlings, nestlings, and chicks who need help (she also stresses that the baby bird may NOT need human intervention), and that &#8220;a misidentification may be more harmful than no identification&#8221; (p.7).</p>
<p>This guide comes out of Tuttle-Adams years in wildlife rehabilitation and her recognition of the need for an easily available resource that synthesizes data for species nesting in North America, one that allows rehabbers and other ornithological practitioners to quickly identify birds without hours of Internet searching and fighting through academic gateways. It covers 403 species: 172 nonpasserine species and 231 passerine species in the Species Accounts, 198 species beautifully illustrated by the author in the Plates section. Birds were selected based on (1) information available; (2) information available elsewhere (thus an emphasis on altricial species and limited waterfowl coverage, since they can be found elsewhere); (3) species most commonly encountered. The scarcity of information on the young of some avian species is astounding. I never realized how little information we have on wood warbler nestlings or knew how secretive their nesting habits can be. I am puzzled as to why Gulls and Terns are almost passed over, with less than two pages of text devoted to a family description and only six species accounts (four gulls, two terns).</p>
<p>Species Accounts are organized by family according to the 61st Supplement (2020) of the AOS <em>Checklist of North and Middle American Birds </em>(the 62nd Supplement came out while the book was in production, which is to be expected). The summary of shared family characteristics is an important element of the Accounts, meant to help the user narrow down the baby bird identification to family group. The Species Accounts themselves vary in length and detail, depending on information available and necessary for identification. Almost a whole page of measurement data, plumage and bill description, and diet for adult, nestling, and fledgling Ravens; a brief paragraph on the measurements and plumage of adult, nestling, and fledgling Cliff Swallows. Family follows family with no page break, making this section a little dense. Light-blue colored headings for family and species names and capitalization of family names helps the eye focus on information. References to plate numbers (in the Plates section) and photograph numbers (in a Photo Gallery) are also placed prominently next to species name. Not all species accounts have corresponding plates or photographs.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.10000birds.com/baby-bird-identification-a-north-american-guide-a-book-review.htm/baby-bird-plate-12-2" rel="attachment wp-att-150420"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-150420" src="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/baby-bird-plate-12.2.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="482" srcset="https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/baby-bird-plate-12.2.jpg 600w, https://www.10000birds.com/wp-content/uploads/baby-bird-plate-12.2-300x241.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></a></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>copyright © 2022 by Cornell University, Plate 12, pages 294-295</em></p>
<p>Here is an example of one of the 36 plates, presenting Belted Kingfisher (ABA Bird of the Year!) and three of the nine woodpeckers illustrated. Woodpeckers are a family of focus for Tuttle-Adams. Woodpeckers nest in cavities and their young are altricial (born in an undeveloped state), which means there is not a lot of documented information about their young and how they look at different stages. They may look very different at various growth stages, as she shows with Acorn Woodpecker. The number of stages illustrated vary for each species, with less for precocial species (born at a mature stage) and for species, like Wood-Warblers, about which we have scarce information. As noted above, not all species in the Accounts are illustrated, and I&#8217;m disappointed at the absence of a baby Piping Plover, my favorite baby bird. Tuttle-Adams artwork is exquisitely drawn and finely colored; she succeeds in communicating the adorableness of each baby bird without sacrificing the detail necessary for accurate and useful scientific illustration.</p>
<p>The last subsection of the Species Accounts is the Photo Gallery, 66 small images of what appears to be photos of baby birds in rehab care taken by the author and rehab colleagues. These are mainly western species, a reflection of the author&#8217;s location. Many are hatchling birds and it&#8217;s a little startling to see their naked vulnerability. I would have like a little more explanation of where the photos came from and what stories they represent. But perhaps that&#8217;s for a different book.</p>
<p>The chapters preceding the Species Accounts are important for rehabilitation identification: texts on baby bird anatomy and development, the importance of bird identification to the rehab process, and a systematic identification process. The anatomy chapter goes deep into mouths and beaks&#8211;features often essential to baby bird identification. We don&#8217;t think about mouth color when we identify adult birds, but they are important clues to narrowing down taxonomic families. Beaks, on the other hand, help identify a nestling in the same way they help identify an adult&#8211;plumage may change with age, but the shape and structure of a beak often remains the same. And there is such a diversity of beak shapes! The descriptors used in the tables on beak size and shape are illustrated in the &#8220;Illustrated Glossary&#8221; in the beginning of the book. The chapter on &#8220;The Process of Identification&#8221; is a fascinating read (even to someone like me who is not a rehabilitation person). It includes questions to ask the finder, color-coded flow charts for eliminating possibilities, tables of nest types, and a step-by-step guide on what to look for while examining the hatchling or nestling. This information is not geographical specific, and the author suggests can be used world-wide by rehabilitation practitioners. (I have no background in rehabilitation other than once placing a stunned Tufted Titmouse that had found its way into my workplace into a warm box till it recovered, so I am relying on Tuttle-Adams&#8217; expertise for these things. Comments from more experienced readers are welcome.)</p>
<p>There is also ample reference material in the front and back of the guide. Significantly, the Introduction begins with &#8220;A Note to Readers: Ethical Considerations Regarding Wildlife&#8221; that offers guidelines on handling birds, for photographing nests and young, and for photographing wild birds in captive settings. These prescriptions are very important to Tuttle-Adams, who takes the perhaps radical approach that a bird&#8217;s welfare supersedes a birder&#8217;s &#8216;right&#8217; to take a photograph. Next is the already noted &#8220;Illustrated Glossary&#8221; is a unique collection of photographs and drawings illustrating scientific terms for parts of the mouth and beak; bones of the leg, feet, and wings; feather tracts; feather development; as well as the standard bird topography diagrams. Appendixes include a chapter on color charts and terminology, an identification worksheet, growth and development tables, and species comparison tables. It&#8217;s as if Tuttle-White has gathered and organized so much rich educational material she didn&#8217;t know where to put it all. There is also an Internet counterpart to the guide, <a href="https://babybirdidentification.wordpress.com/">Baby Bird Identification</a>, that offers the basics of Tuttle-Adams&#8217; identification process, the book&#8217;s bird family information, and basic resources.</p>
<p><em>Baby Bird Identification: A North American Guide</em> is baby birds taken seriously, an identification guide for wildlife rehabilitators, a visual and educational treat for the rest of us. There are other books about baby birds, most notably Julie Zickefoose&#8217;s <em>Baby Birds: An Artist Looks into the Nest</em> (2016) and<br />
Laura Erickson and Marie Read&#8217;s <em>Into the Nest: Intimate Views of the Courting, Parenting, and Family Lives of Familiar Birds</em> (2015). These books are concerned with behavior. The identification guide by Paul J. Baicich and Colin J. O. Harrison, and  Nests, <em>Eggs, and Nestlings of North American Birds, 2nd ed.</em> (2005) covers some of the territory of Baby Bird Identification and more, it&#8217;s one of the reasons Tuttle-Adams has so few drawings of waterfowl, waterbirds, and shorebirds&#8211;you can find them here. A birder or rehabber looking for a comprehensive collection should consider having both books in their collection.</p>
<p><em>Baby Bird Identification</em> focuses on scientific data, synthesizing information gathered from reference books, journal articles and databases, unpublished data, and data collected by the author herself. It is not an identification guide for everybody. Which just might be the future of identification and field guides&#8211;books filling specialized niches, offering essential information to practitioners and naturalists interested in specific families, habitats, and avian developmental stages. It emphasizes the importance of the work of wildlife rehabilitators (thank you!) and of the essential role baby birds have in our lives, because without them, of course, we would not have adult birds, and we can&#8217;t take that for granted.</p>
<p>And one more thing, readers of 10,000 Birds&#8211;A Happy, Health, Birdy New Year!</p>
<hr />
<p><strong><em>Baby Bird Identification: A North American Guide</em></strong><br />
by Linda Tuttle-Adams; foreword By Rebecca S. Duerr<br />
Comstock Publishing Associates/Cornell University Press, October 2022<br />
Paperback, 432 pages<br />
Illustrations: 68 color photo, 1 b&amp;w halftone, 379 illustrations, 2 charts<br />
Dimensions: 6 x 9 x 0 in<br />
ISBN: 13: 9781501762857; ISBN: 10: 1501762850<br />
$39.95</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.10000birds.com/baby-bird-identification-a-north-american-guide-a-book-review.htm/feed</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
