<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>PLOS Biology</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/" />
  <author>
    <name>PLOS</name>
    <uri>https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/</uri>
    <email>webmaster@plos.org</email>
  </author>
  <subtitle type="text">A Peer-Reviewed Open-Access Journal</subtitle>
  <id>https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/feed/atom</id>
  <rights>All PLOS articles are Open Access.</rights>
  <icon>https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/resource/img/favicon.ico</icon>
  <logo>https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/resource/img/favicon.ico</logo>
  <updated>2023-01-15T17:44:19Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <title>A possible role for taste receptor cells in surveying the oral microbiome</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001953" title="A possible role for taste receptor cells in surveying the oral microbiome" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001953.PDF" title="(PDF) A possible role for taste receptor cells in surveying the oral microbiome" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001953.XML" title="(XML) A possible role for taste receptor cells in surveying the oral microbiome" />
    <author>
      <name>Emma M. Heisey</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lynnette Phillips McCluskey</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001953</id>
    <updated>2023-01-13T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-13T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Emma M. Heisey, Lynnette Phillips McCluskey&lt;/p&gt;

Taste receptor cells are sensory specialists that detect chemicals in food and drink. An exciting new report in PLOS Biology suggests that some taste cells could also be involved in immune surveillance like counterparts in the intestine.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Strategic priorities for reproducibility reform</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001943" title="Strategic priorities for reproducibility reform" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001943.PDF" title="(PDF) Strategic priorities for reproducibility reform" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001943.XML" title="(XML) Strategic priorities for reproducibility reform" />
    <author>
      <name>Tony Ross-Hellauer</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001943</id>
    <updated>2023-01-12T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-12T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Tony Ross-Hellauer&lt;/p&gt;

Increasing the reproducibility of research should be a top priority. Great work is being done, but more work is needed to combine efforts and maximize our actions to enable true reproducibility reform.

Increasing the reproducibility of research should be a top priority. This Perspective argues that more work is needed to combine efforts and maximize our actions to enable true reproducibility reform.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Type II taste cells participate in mucosal immune surveillance</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001647" title="Type II taste cells participate in mucosal immune surveillance" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001647.PDF" title="(PDF) Type II taste cells participate in mucosal immune surveillance" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001647.XML" title="(XML) Type II taste cells participate in mucosal immune surveillance" />
    <author>
      <name>Yumei Qin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Salin Raj Palayyan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xin Zheng</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Shiyi Tian</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Robert F. Margolskee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sunil K. Sukumaran</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001647</id>
    <updated>2023-01-12T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-12T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Yumei Qin, Salin Raj Palayyan, Xin Zheng, Shiyi Tian, Robert F. Margolskee, Sunil K. Sukumaran&lt;/p&gt;

The oral microbiome is second only to its intestinal counterpart in diversity and abundance, but its effects on taste cells remains largely unexplored. Using single-cell RNASeq, we found that mouse taste cells, in particular, sweet and umami receptor cells that express taste 1 receptor member 3 (&lt;i&gt;Tas1r3&lt;/i&gt;), have a gene expression signature reminiscent of Microfold (M) cells, a central player in immune surveillance in the mucosa-associated lymphoid tissue (MALT) such as those in the Peyer’s patch and tonsils. Administration of tumor necrosis factor ligand superfamily member 11 (TNFSF11; also known as RANKL), a growth factor required for differentiation of M cells, dramatically increased M cell proliferation and marker gene expression in the taste papillae and in cultured taste organoids from wild-type (WT) mice. Taste papillae and organoids from knockout mice lacking &lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;i&gt;)&lt;/i&gt;, a RANKL-regulated transcription factor required for M cell development and regeneration on the other hand, failed to respond to RANKL. Taste papillae from &lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; mice also showed reduced expression of NF-κB signaling pathway components and proinflammatory cytokines and attracted fewer immune cells. However, lipopolysaccharide-induced expression of cytokines was strongly up-regulated in &lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; mice compared to their WT counterparts. Like M cells, taste cells from WT but not &lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; mice readily took up fluorescently labeled microbeads, a proxy for microbial transcytosis. The proportion of taste cell subtypes are unaltered in &lt;i&gt;Spib&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup&gt;KO&lt;/sup&gt; mice; however, they displayed increased attraction to sweet and umami taste stimuli. We propose that taste cells are involved in immune surveillance and may tune their taste responses to microbial signaling and infection.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is more always better when it comes to mating?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001955" title="Is more always better when it comes to mating?" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001955.PDF" title="(PDF) Is more always better when it comes to mating?" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001955.XML" title="(XML) Is more always better when it comes to mating?" />
    <author>
      <name>Hanna Kokko</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Michael D. Jennions</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001955</id>
    <updated>2023-01-11T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-11T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Hanna Kokko, Michael D. Jennions&lt;/p&gt;

Fitness usually increases when a male mates with more females, but is the same true for females? A new meta-analysis in PLOS Biology shows that females, like males, tend to have a positive relationship between the number of mates and their reproductive output. But why?

Fitness usually increases when a male mates with more females, but is the same true for females? A new meta-analysis in PLOS Biology shows that females, like males, tend to have a positive relationship between the number of mates and their reproductive output. This Primer asks why.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sexual selection in females and the evolution of polyandry</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001916" title="Sexual selection in females and the evolution of polyandry" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001916.PDF" title="(PDF) Sexual selection in females and the evolution of polyandry" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001916.XML" title="(XML) Sexual selection in females and the evolution of polyandry" />
    <author>
      <name>Salomé Fromonteil</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lucas Marie-Orleach</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lennart Winkler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tim Janicke</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001916</id>
    <updated>2023-01-10T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-10T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Salomé Fromonteil, Lucas Marie-Orleach, Lennart Winkler, Tim Janicke&lt;/p&gt;

Over the last decades, the field of sexual selection underwent a paradigm shift from sexual-stereotype thinking of “eager” males and “coy” females towards a more nuanced perspective acknowledging that not only males but also females can benefit from multiple mating and compete for mating partners. Yet, sexual selection in females is still considered a peculiarity, and the evolution of polyandry is often viewed to result from a higher mating interest of males. Here, we present meta-analytic evidence from 77 species across a broad range of animal taxa to demonstrate that female reproductive success is overall positively correlated with mating success, suggesting that females typically benefit from multiple mating. Importantly, we found that these fitness gains likely promote the evolution of polyandry. Our findings offer support for the idea that sexual selection is widespread in females and to play a key role for the evolution of animal mating systems. Thereby, our results extend our understanding of the evolutionary consequences of sexual reproduction and contribute to a more balanced view of how sexual selection operates in males and females.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Nutritional compensation of the circadian clock is a conserved process influenced by gene expression regulation and mRNA stability</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001961" title="Nutritional compensation of the circadian clock is a conserved process influenced by gene expression regulation and mRNA stability" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001961.PDF" title="(PDF) Nutritional compensation of the circadian clock is a conserved process influenced by gene expression regulation and mRNA stability" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001961.XML" title="(XML) Nutritional compensation of the circadian clock is a conserved process influenced by gene expression regulation and mRNA stability" />
    <author>
      <name>Christina M. Kelliher</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Elizabeth-Lauren Stevenson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jennifer J. Loros</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jay C. Dunlap</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001961</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Christina M. Kelliher, Elizabeth-Lauren Stevenson, Jennifer J. Loros, Jay C. Dunlap&lt;/p&gt;

Compensation is a defining principle of a true circadian clock, where its approximately 24-hour period length is relatively unchanged across environmental conditions. Known compensation effectors directly regulate core clock factors to buffer the oscillator’s period length from variables in the environment. Temperature Compensation mechanisms have been experimentally addressed across circadian model systems, but much less is known about the related process of Nutritional Compensation, where circadian period length is maintained across physiologically relevant nutrient levels. Using the filamentous fungus &lt;i&gt;Neurospora crassa&lt;/i&gt;, we performed a genetic screen under glucose and amino acid starvation conditions to identify new regulators of Nutritional Compensation. Our screen uncovered 16 novel mutants, and together with 4 mutants characterized in prior work, a model emerges where Nutritional Compensation of the fungal clock is achieved at the levels of transcription, chromatin regulation, and mRNA stability. However, eukaryotic circadian Nutritional Compensation is completely unstudied outside of &lt;i&gt;Neurospora&lt;/i&gt;. To test for conservation in cultured human cells, we selected top hits from our fungal genetic screen, performed siRNA knockdown experiments of the mammalian orthologs, and characterized the cell lines with respect to compensation. We find that the wild-type mammalian clock is also compensated across a large range of external glucose concentrations, as observed in &lt;i&gt;Neurospora&lt;/i&gt;, and that knocking down the mammalian orthologs of the &lt;i&gt;Neurospora&lt;/i&gt; compensation-associated genes &lt;i&gt;CPSF6&lt;/i&gt; or &lt;i&gt;SETD2&lt;/i&gt; in human cells also results in nutrient-dependent period length changes. We conclude that, like Temperature Compensation, Nutritional Compensation is a conserved circadian process in fungal and mammalian clocks and that it may share common molecular determinants.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dorsal root ganglia control nociceptive input to the central nervous system</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001958" title="Dorsal root ganglia control nociceptive input to the central nervous system" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001958.PDF" title="(PDF) Dorsal root ganglia control nociceptive input to the central nervous system" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001958.XML" title="(XML) Dorsal root ganglia control nociceptive input to the central nervous system" />
    <author>
      <name>Han Hao</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rosmaliza Ramli</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Caixue Wang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Chao Liu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Shihab Shah</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pierce Mullen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Varinder Lall</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Frederick Jones</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jicheng Shao</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hailin Zhang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>David B. Jaffe</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Nikita Gamper</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xiaona Du</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001958</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Han Hao, Rosmaliza Ramli, Caixue Wang, Chao Liu, Shihab Shah, Pierce Mullen, Varinder Lall, Frederick Jones, Jicheng Shao, Hailin Zhang, David B. Jaffe, Nikita Gamper, Xiaona Du&lt;/p&gt;

Accumulating observations suggest that peripheral somatosensory ganglia may regulate nociceptive transmission, yet direct evidence is sparse. Here, in experiments on rats and mice, we show that the peripheral afferent nociceptive information in mice undergoes dynamic filtering within the dorsal root ganglion (DRG) and suggest that this filtering occurs at the axonal bifurcations (t-junctions). Using synchronous in vivo electrophysiological recordings from the peripheral and central processes of sensory neurons (in the spinal nerve and dorsal root), ganglionic transplantation of GABAergic progenitor cells, and optogenetics, we demonstrate existence of tonic and dynamic filtering of action potentials traveling through the DRG. Filtering induced by focal application of GABA or optogenetic GABA release from the DRG-transplanted GABAergic progenitor cells was specific to nociceptive fibers. Light-sheet imaging and computer modeling demonstrated that, compared to other somatosensory fiber types, nociceptors have shorter stem axons, making somatic control over t-junctional filtering more efficient. Optogenetically induced GABA release within DRG from the transplanted GABAergic cells enhanced filtering and alleviated hypersensitivity to noxious stimulation produced by chronic inflammation and neuropathic injury in vivo. These findings support “gating” of pain information by DRGs and suggest new therapeutic approaches for pain relief.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Attachment of the RNA degradosome to the bacterial inner cytoplasmic membrane prevents wasteful degradation of rRNA in ribosome assembly intermediates</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001942" title="Attachment of the RNA degradosome to the bacterial inner cytoplasmic membrane prevents wasteful degradation of rRNA in ribosome assembly intermediates" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001942.PDF" title="(PDF) Attachment of the RNA degradosome to the bacterial inner cytoplasmic membrane prevents wasteful degradation of rRNA in ribosome assembly intermediates" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001942.XML" title="(XML) Attachment of the RNA degradosome to the bacterial inner cytoplasmic membrane prevents wasteful degradation of rRNA in ribosome assembly intermediates" />
    <author>
      <name>Lydia Hadjeras</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Marie Bouvier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Isabelle Canal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Leonora Poljak</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Quentin Morin-Ogier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carine Froment</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Odile Burlet-Schlitz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lina Hamouche</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Laurence Girbal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Muriel Cocaign-Bousquet</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Agamemnon J. Carpousis</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001942</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Lydia Hadjeras, Marie Bouvier, Isabelle Canal, Leonora Poljak, Quentin Morin-Ogier, Carine Froment, Odile Burlet-Schlitz, Lina Hamouche, Laurence Girbal, Muriel Cocaign-Bousquet, Agamemnon J. Carpousis&lt;/p&gt;

RNA processing and degradation shape the transcriptome by generating stable molecules that are necessary for translation (rRNA and tRNA) and by facilitating the turnover of mRNA, which is necessary for the posttranscriptional control of gene expression. In bacteria and the plant chloroplast, RNA degradosomes are multienzyme complexes that process and degrade RNA. In many bacterial species, the endoribonuclease RNase E is the central component of the RNA degradosome. RNase E-based RNA degradosomes are inner membrane proteins in a large family of gram-negative bacteria (β- and γ-Proteobacteria). Until now, the reason for membrane localization was not understood. Here, we show that a mutant strain of &lt;i&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/i&gt;, in which the RNA degradosome is localized to the interior of the cell, has high levels of 20S and 40S particles that are defective intermediates in ribosome assembly. These particles have aberrant protein composition and contain rRNA precursors that have been cleaved by RNase E. After RNase E cleavage, rRNA fragments are degraded to nucleotides by exoribonucleases. In vitro, rRNA in intact ribosomes is resistant to RNase E cleavage, whereas protein-free rRNA is readily degraded. We conclude that RNA degradosomes in the nucleoid of the mutant strain interfere with cotranscriptional ribosome assembly. We propose that membrane-attached RNA degradosomes in wild-type cells control the quality of ribosome assembly after intermediates are released from the nucleoid. That is, the compact structure of mature ribosomes protects rRNA against cleavage by RNase E. Turnover of a proportion of intermediates in ribosome assembly explains slow growth of the mutant strain. Competition between mRNA and rRNA degradation could be the cause of slower mRNA degradation in the mutant strain. We conclude that attachment of the RNA degradosome to the bacterial inner cytoplasmic membrane prevents wasteful degradation of rRNA precursors, thus explaining the reason for conservation of membrane-attached RNA degradosomes throughout the β- and γ-Proteobacteria.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A central CRMP complex essential for invasion in &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt;</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001937" title="A central CRMP complex essential for invasion in &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt;" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001937.PDF" title="(PDF) A central CRMP complex essential for invasion in &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt;" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001937.XML" title="(XML) A central CRMP complex essential for invasion in &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt;" />
    <author>
      <name>Mirko Singer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kathrin Simon</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ignasi Forné</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Markus Meissner</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001937</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Mirko Singer, Kathrin Simon, Ignasi Forné, Markus Meissner&lt;/p&gt;

Apicomplexa are obligate intracellular parasites. While most species are restricted to specific hosts and cell types, &lt;i&gt;Toxoplasma gondii&lt;/i&gt; can invade every nucleated cell derived from warm-blooded animals. This broad host range suggests that this parasite can recognize multiple host cell ligands or structures, leading to the activation of a central protein complex, which should be conserved in all apicomplexans. During invasion, the unique secretory organelles (micronemes and rhoptries) are sequentially released and several micronemal proteins have been suggested to be required for host cell recognition and invasion. However, to date, only few micronemal proteins have been demonstrated to be essential for invasion, suggesting functional redundancy that might allow such a broad host range. Cysteine Repeat Modular Proteins (CRMPs) are a family of apicomplexan-specific proteins. In &lt;i&gt;T&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;gondii&lt;/i&gt;, two CRMPs are present in the genome, CRMPA (TGGT1_261080) and CRMPB (TGGT1_292020). Here, we demonstrate that both proteins form a complex that contains the additional proteins MIC15 and the thrombospondin type 1 domain-containing protein (TSP1). Disruption of this complex results in a block of rhoptry secretion and parasites being unable to invade the host cell. In conclusion, this complex is a central invasion complex conserved in all apicomplexans.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cortical representations of numbers and nonsymbolic quantities expand and segregate in children from 5 to 8 years of age</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001935" title="Cortical representations of numbers and nonsymbolic quantities expand and segregate in children from 5 to 8 years of age" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001935.PDF" title="(PDF) Cortical representations of numbers and nonsymbolic quantities expand and segregate in children from 5 to 8 years of age" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001935.XML" title="(XML) Cortical representations of numbers and nonsymbolic quantities expand and segregate in children from 5 to 8 years of age" />
    <author>
      <name>Tomoya Nakai</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Cléa Girard</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Léa Longo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hanna Chesnokova</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jérôme Prado</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001935</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Tomoya Nakai, Cléa Girard, Léa Longo, Hanna Chesnokova, Jérôme Prado&lt;/p&gt;

Number symbols, such as Arabic numerals, are cultural inventions that have transformed human mathematical skills. Although their acquisition is at the core of early elementary education in children, it remains unknown how the neural representations of numerals emerge during that period. It is also unclear whether these relate to an ontogenetically earlier sense of approximate quantity. Here, we used multivariate fMRI adaptation coupled with within- and between-format machine learning to probe the cortical representations of Arabic numerals and approximate nonsymbolic quantity in 89 children either at the beginning (age 5) or four years into formal education (age 8). Although the cortical representations of both numerals and nonsymbolic quantities expanded from age 5 to age 8, these representations also segregated with learning and development. Specifically, a format-independent neural representation of quantity was found in the right parietal cortex, but only for 5-year-olds. These results are consistent with the so-called symbolic estrangement hypothesis, which argues that the relation between symbolic and nonsymbolic quantity weakens with exposure to formal mathematics in children.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Identifying barriers and enablers to rigorous conduct and reporting of preclinical laboratory studies</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001932" title="Identifying barriers and enablers to rigorous conduct and reporting of preclinical laboratory studies" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001932.PDF" title="(PDF) Identifying barriers and enablers to rigorous conduct and reporting of preclinical laboratory studies" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001932.XML" title="(XML) Identifying barriers and enablers to rigorous conduct and reporting of preclinical laboratory studies" />
    <author>
      <name>Manoj M. Lalu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Justin Presseau</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Madison K. Foster</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Victoria T. Hunniford</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kelly D. Cobey</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jamie C. Brehaut</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carolina Ilkow</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Joshua Montroy</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Analyssa Cardenas</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ayni Sharif</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Matthew S. Jeffers</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Dean A. Fergusson</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001932</id>
    <updated>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-05T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Manoj M. Lalu, Justin Presseau, Madison K. Foster, Victoria T. Hunniford, Kelly D. Cobey, Jamie C. Brehaut, Carolina Ilkow, Joshua Montroy, Analyssa Cardenas, Ayni Sharif, Matthew S. Jeffers, Dean A. Fergusson&lt;/p&gt;

Use of rigorous study design methods and transparent reporting in publications are 2 key strategies proposed to improve the reproducibility of preclinical research. Despite promotion of these practices by funders and journals, assessments suggest uptake is low in preclinical research. Thirty preclinical scientists were interviewed to better understand barriers and enablers to rigorous design and reporting. The interview guide was informed by the Theoretical Domains Framework, which is a framework used to understand determinants of current and desired behavior. Four global themes were identified; 2 reflecting enablers and 2 reflecting barriers. We found that basic scientists are highly motivated to apply the methods of rigorous design and reporting and perceive a number of benefits to their adoption (e.g., improved quality and reliability). However, there was varied awareness of the guidelines and in implementation of these practices. Researchers also noted that these guidelines can result in disadvantages, such as increased sample sizes, expenses, time, and can require several personnel to operationalize. Most researchers expressed additional resources such as personnel and education/training would better enable the application of some methods. Using existing guidance (Behaviour Change Wheel (BCW); Expert Recommendations for Implementing Change (ERIC) project implementation strategies), we mapped and coded our interview findings to identify potential interventions, policies, and implementation strategies to improve routine use of the guidelines by preclinical scientists. These findings will help inform specific strategies that may guide the development of programs and resources to improve experimental design and transparent reporting in preclinical research.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Support academic access to automated cloud labs to improve reproducibility</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001919" title="Support academic access to automated cloud labs to improve reproducibility" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001919.PDF" title="(PDF) Support academic access to automated cloud labs to improve reproducibility" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001919.XML" title="(XML) Support academic access to automated cloud labs to improve reproducibility" />
    <author>
      <name>Chase Armer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Florent Letronne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Erika DeBenedictis</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001919</id>
    <updated>2023-01-03T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2023-01-03T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Chase Armer, Florent Letronne, Erika DeBenedictis&lt;/p&gt;

Cloud labs, where experiments are executed remotely in robotic facilities, can improve the reproducibility, accessibility, and scalability of experimental biology. Funding and training programs will enable academics to overcome barriers to adopting such technology.

Remotely operated robotic labs, known as cloud labs, have the potential to improve reproducibility in the life sciences. This Perspective investigates the barriers academics face when wanting to use cloud labs and suggests strategies to make this technology more accessible.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Correction: Assessment of single-vessel cerebral blood velocity by phase contrast fMRI</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001951" title="Correction: Assessment of single-vessel cerebral blood velocity by phase contrast fMRI" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001951.PDF" title="(PDF) Correction: Assessment of single-vessel cerebral blood velocity by phase contrast fMRI" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001951.XML" title="(XML) Correction: Assessment of single-vessel cerebral blood velocity by phase contrast fMRI" />
    <author>
      <name>Xuming Chen</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yuanyuan Jiang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sangcheon Choi</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rolf Pohmann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Klaus Scheffler</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>David Kleinfeld</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xin Yu</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001951</id>
    <updated>2022-12-28T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-28T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Xuming Chen, Yuanyuan Jiang, Sangcheon Choi, Rolf Pohmann, Klaus Scheffler, David Kleinfeld, Xin Yu&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Seasonal timing on a cyclical Earth: Towards a theoretical framework for the evolution of phenology</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001952" title="Seasonal timing on a cyclical Earth: Towards a theoretical framework for the evolution of phenology" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001952.PDF" title="(PDF) Seasonal timing on a cyclical Earth: Towards a theoretical framework for the evolution of phenology" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001952.XML" title="(XML) Seasonal timing on a cyclical Earth: Towards a theoretical framework for the evolution of phenology" />
    <author>
      <name>John S. Park</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Eric Post</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001952</id>
    <updated>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by John S. Park, Eric Post&lt;/p&gt;

Phenology refers to the seasonal timing patterns commonly exhibited by life on Earth, from blooming flowers to breeding birds to human agriculture. Climate change is altering abiotic seasonality (e.g., longer summers) and in turn, phenological patterns contained within. However, how phenology should evolve is still an unsolved problem. This problem lies at the crux of predicting future phenological changes that will likely have substantial ecosystem consequences, and more fundamentally, of understanding an undeniably global phenomenon. Most studies have associated proximate environmental variables with phenological responses in case-specific ways, making it difficult to contextualize observations within a general evolutionary framework. We outline the complex but universal ways in which seasonal timing maps onto evolutionary fitness. We borrow lessons from life history theory and evolutionary demography that have benefited from a first principles-based theoretical scaffold. Lastly, we identify key questions for theorists and empiricists to help advance our general understanding of phenology.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Towards a unification of the 2 meanings of “epigenetics”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001944" title="Towards a unification of the 2 meanings of “epigenetics”" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001944.PDF" title="(PDF) Towards a unification of the 2 meanings of “epigenetics”" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001944.XML" title="(XML) Towards a unification of the 2 meanings of “epigenetics”" />
    <author>
      <name>Sui Huang</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001944</id>
    <updated>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Sui Huang&lt;/p&gt;

The notion of epigenetic “marks” used by molecular biologists is conceptually disconnected from the idea of Waddington’s epigenetic “landscape” that is used by systems biologists and biophysicists. Recent advances suggest that these 2 distinct schools of thought could be united.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The RNA export and RNA decay complexes THO and TRAMP prevent transcription-replication conflicts, DNA breaks, and CAG repeat contractions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001940" title="The RNA export and RNA decay complexes THO and TRAMP prevent transcription-replication conflicts, DNA breaks, and CAG repeat contractions" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001940.PDF" title="(PDF) The RNA export and RNA decay complexes THO and TRAMP prevent transcription-replication conflicts, DNA breaks, and CAG repeat contractions" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001940.XML" title="(XML) The RNA export and RNA decay complexes THO and TRAMP prevent transcription-replication conflicts, DNA breaks, and CAG repeat contractions" />
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca E. Brown</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xiaofeng A. Su</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stacey Fair</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Katherine Wu</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lauren Verra</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Robyn Jong</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kristin Andrykovich</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Catherine H. Freudenreich</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001940</id>
    <updated>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-27T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Rebecca E. Brown, Xiaofeng A. Su, Stacey Fair, Katherine Wu, Lauren Verra, Robyn Jong, Kristin Andrykovich, Catherine H. Freudenreich&lt;/p&gt;

Expansion of structure-forming CAG/CTG repetitive sequences is the cause of several neurodegenerative disorders and deletion of repeats is a potential therapeutic strategy. Transcription-associated mechanisms are known to cause CAG repeat instability. In this study, we discovered that Thp2, an RNA export factor and member of the THO (suppressors of transcriptional defects of &lt;i&gt;h&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i&gt;pr1Δ&lt;/i&gt; by overexpression) complex, and Trf4, a key component of the TRAMP (Trf4/5-Air1/2-Mtr4 polyadenylation) complex involved in nuclear RNA polyadenylation and degradation, are necessary to prevent CAG fragility and repeat contractions in a &lt;i&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/i&gt; model system. Depletion of both Thp2 and Trf4 proteins causes a highly synergistic increase in CAG repeat fragility, indicating a complementary role of the THO and TRAMP complexes in preventing genome instability. Loss of either Thp2 or Trf4 causes an increase in RNA polymerase stalling at the CAG repeats and other genomic loci, as well as genome-wide transcription-replication conflicts (TRCs), implicating TRCs as a cause of CAG fragility and instability in their absence. Analysis of the effect of RNase H1 overexpression on CAG fragility, RNAPII stalling, and TRCs suggests that RNAPII stalling with associated R-loops are the main cause of CAG fragility in the &lt;i&gt;thp2Δ&lt;/i&gt; mutants. In contrast, CAG fragility and TRCs in the &lt;i&gt;trf4Δ&lt;/i&gt; mutant can be compensated for by RPA overexpression, suggesting that excess unprocessed RNA in TRAMP4 mutants leads to reduced RPA availability and high levels of TRCs. Our results show the importance of RNA surveillance pathways in preventing RNAPII stalling, TRCs, and DNA breaks, and show that RNA export and RNA decay factors work collaboratively to maintain genome stability.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Threat management priorities for conserving Antarctic biodiversity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001921" title="Threat management priorities for conserving Antarctic biodiversity" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001921.PDF" title="(PDF) Threat management priorities for conserving Antarctic biodiversity" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001921.XML" title="(XML) Threat management priorities for conserving Antarctic biodiversity" />
    <author>
      <name>Jasmine R. Lee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Aleks Terauds</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Josie Carwardine</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Justine D. Shaw</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Richard A. Fuller</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hugh P. Possingham</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Steven L. Chown</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Peter Convey</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Neil Gilbert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin A. Hughes</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ewan McIvor</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sharon A. Robinson</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yan Ropert-Coudert</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Dana M. Bergstrom</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Elisabeth M. Biersma</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Claire Christian</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Don A. Cowan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yves Frenot</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stéphanie Jenouvrier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lisa Kelley</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Michael J. Lee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Heather J. Lynch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Birgit Njåstad</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Antonio Quesada</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ricardo M. Roura</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>E. Ashley Shaw</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Damon Stanwell-Smith</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Megumu Tsujimoto</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Diana H. Wall</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Annick Wilmotte</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Iadine Chadès</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001921</id>
    <updated>2022-12-22T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-22T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Jasmine R. Lee, Aleks Terauds, Josie Carwardine, Justine D. Shaw, Richard A. Fuller, Hugh P. Possingham, Steven L. Chown, Peter Convey, Neil Gilbert, Kevin A. Hughes, Ewan McIvor, Sharon A. Robinson, Yan Ropert-Coudert, Dana M. Bergstrom, Elisabeth M. Biersma, Claire Christian, Don A. Cowan, Yves Frenot, Stéphanie Jenouvrier, Lisa Kelley, Michael J. Lee, Heather J. Lynch, Birgit Njåstad, Antonio Quesada, Ricardo M. Roura, E. Ashley Shaw, Damon Stanwell-Smith, Megumu Tsujimoto, Diana H. Wall, Annick Wilmotte, Iadine Chadès&lt;/p&gt;

Antarctic terrestrial biodiversity faces multiple threats, from invasive species to climate change. Yet no large-scale assessments of threat management strategies exist. Applying a structured participatory approach, we demonstrate that existing conservation efforts are insufficient in a changing world, estimating that 65% (at best 37%, at worst 97%) of native terrestrial taxa and land-associated seabirds are likely to decline by 2100 under current trajectories. Emperor penguins are identified as the most vulnerable taxon, followed by other seabirds and dry soil nematodes. We find that implementing 10 key threat management strategies in parallel, at an estimated present-day equivalent annual cost of US$23 million, could benefit up to 84% of Antarctic taxa. Climate change is identified as the most pervasive threat to Antarctic biodiversity and influencing global policy to effectively limit climate change is the most beneficial conservation strategy. However, minimising impacts of human activities and improved planning and management of new infrastructure projects are cost-effective and will help to minimise regional threats. Simultaneous global and regional efforts are critical to secure Antarctic biodiversity for future generations.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Multispecies biofilm architecture determines bacterial exposure to phages</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001913" title="Multispecies biofilm architecture determines bacterial exposure to phages" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001913.PDF" title="(PDF) Multispecies biofilm architecture determines bacterial exposure to phages" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001913.XML" title="(XML) Multispecies biofilm architecture determines bacterial exposure to phages" />
    <author>
      <name>James B. Winans</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Benjamin R. Wucher</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carey D. Nadell</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001913</id>
    <updated>2022-12-22T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-22T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by James B. Winans, Benjamin R. Wucher, Carey D. Nadell&lt;/p&gt;

Numerous ecological interactions among microbes—for example, competition for space and resources, or interaction among phages and their bacterial hosts—are likely to occur simultaneously in multispecies biofilm communities. While biofilms formed by just a single species occur, multispecies biofilms are thought to be more typical of microbial communities in the natural environment. Previous work has shown that multispecies biofilms can increase, decrease, or have no measurable impact on phage exposure of a host bacterium living alongside another species that the phages cannot target. The reasons underlying this variability are not well understood, and how phage–host encounters change within multispecies biofilms remains mostly unexplored at the cellular spatial scale. Here, we study how the cellular scale architecture of model 2-species biofilms impacts cell–cell and cell–phage interactions controlling larger scale population and community dynamics. Our system consists of dual culture biofilms of &lt;i&gt;Escherichia coli&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Vibrio cholerae&lt;/i&gt; under exposure to T7 phages, which we study using microfluidic culture, high-resolution confocal microscopy imaging, and detailed image analysis. As shown previously, sufficiently mature biofilms of &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;coli&lt;/i&gt; can protect themselves from phage exposure via their curli matrix. Before this stage of biofilm structural maturity, &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;coli&lt;/i&gt; is highly susceptible to phages; however, we show that these bacteria can gain lasting protection against phage exposure if they have become embedded in the bottom layers of highly packed groups of &lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;cholerae&lt;/i&gt; in co-culture. This protection, in turn, is dependent on the cell packing architecture controlled by &lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;cholerae&lt;/i&gt; biofilm matrix secretion. In this manner, &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;coli&lt;/i&gt; cells that are otherwise susceptible to phage-mediated killing can survive phage exposure in the absence of de novo resistance evolution. While co-culture biofilm formation with &lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;cholerae&lt;/i&gt; can confer phage protection to &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;coli&lt;/i&gt;, it comes at the cost of competing with &lt;i&gt;V&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;cholerae&lt;/i&gt; and a disruption of normal curli-mediated protection for &lt;i&gt;E&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;coli&lt;/i&gt; even in dual species biofilms grown over long time scales. This work highlights the critical importance of studying multispecies biofilm architecture and its influence on the community dynamics of bacteria and phages.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Differences in the functional brain architecture of sustained attention and working memory in youth and adults</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001938" title="Differences in the functional brain architecture of sustained attention and working memory in youth and adults" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001938.PDF" title="(PDF) Differences in the functional brain architecture of sustained attention and working memory in youth and adults" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001938.XML" title="(XML) Differences in the functional brain architecture of sustained attention and working memory in youth and adults" />
    <author>
      <name>Omid Kardan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew J. Stier</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Carlos Cardenas-Iniguez</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kathryn E. Schertz</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Julia C. Pruin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yuting Deng</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Taylor Chamberlain</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Wesley J. Meredith</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Xihan Zhang</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jillian E. Bowman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tanvi Lakhtakia</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lucy Tindel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Emily W. Avery</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Qi Lin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kwangsun Yoo</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Marvin M. Chun</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Marc G. Berman</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Monica D. Rosenberg</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001938</id>
    <updated>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Omid Kardan, Andrew J. Stier, Carlos Cardenas-Iniguez, Kathryn E. Schertz, Julia C. Pruin, Yuting Deng, Taylor Chamberlain, Wesley J. Meredith, Xihan Zhang, Jillian E. Bowman, Tanvi Lakhtakia, Lucy Tindel, Emily W. Avery, Qi Lin, Kwangsun Yoo, Marvin M. Chun, Marc G. Berman, Monica D. Rosenberg&lt;/p&gt;

Sustained attention (SA) and working memory (WM) are critical processes, but the brain networks supporting these abilities in development are unknown. We characterized the functional brain architecture of SA and WM in 9- to 11-year-old children and adults. First, we found that adult network predictors of SA generalized to predict individual differences and fluctuations in SA in youth. A WM model predicted WM performance both across and within children—and captured individual differences in later recognition memory—but underperformed in youth relative to adults. We next characterized functional connections differentially related to SA and WM in youth compared to adults. Results revealed 2 network configurations: a dominant architecture predicting performance in both age groups and a secondary architecture, more prominent for WM than SA, predicting performance in each age group differently. Thus, functional connectivity (FC) predicts SA and WM in youth, with networks predicting WM performance differing more between youths and adults than those predicting SA.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Alternative splicing liberates a cryptic cytoplasmic isoform of mitochondrial MECR that antagonizes influenza virus</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001934" title="Alternative splicing liberates a cryptic cytoplasmic isoform of mitochondrial MECR that antagonizes influenza virus" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001934.PDF" title="(PDF) Alternative splicing liberates a cryptic cytoplasmic isoform of mitochondrial MECR that antagonizes influenza virus" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001934.XML" title="(XML) Alternative splicing liberates a cryptic cytoplasmic isoform of mitochondrial MECR that antagonizes influenza virus" />
    <author>
      <name>Steven F. Baker</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Helene Meistermann</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Manuel Tzouros</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Aaron Baker</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sabrina Golling</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Juliane Siebourg Polster</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Mitchell P. Ledwith</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anthony Gitter</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Angelique Augustin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hassan Javanbakht</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Mehle</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001934</id>
    <updated>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Steven F. Baker, Helene Meistermann, Manuel Tzouros, Aaron Baker, Sabrina Golling, Juliane Siebourg Polster, Mitchell P. Ledwith, Anthony Gitter, Angelique Augustin, Hassan Javanbakht, Andrew Mehle&lt;/p&gt;

Viruses must balance their reliance on host cell machinery for replication while avoiding host defense. Influenza A viruses are zoonotic agents that frequently switch hosts, causing localized outbreaks with the potential for larger pandemics. The host range of influenza virus is limited by the need for successful interactions between the virus and cellular partners. Here we used immunocompetitive capture-mass spectrometry to identify cellular proteins that interact with human- and avian-style viral polymerases. We focused on the proviral activity of heterogenous nuclear ribonuclear protein U-like 1 (hnRNP UL1) and the antiviral activity of mitochondrial enoyl CoA-reductase (MECR). MECR is localized to mitochondria where it functions in mitochondrial fatty acid synthesis (mtFAS). While a small fraction of the polymerase subunit PB2 localizes to the mitochondria, PB2 did not interact with full-length MECR. By contrast, a minor splice variant produces cytoplasmic MECR (cMECR). Ectopic expression of cMECR shows that it binds the viral polymerase and suppresses viral replication by blocking assembly of viral ribonucleoprotein complexes (RNPs). MECR ablation through genome editing or drug treatment is detrimental for cell health, creating a generic block to virus replication. Using the yeast homolog Etr1 to supply the metabolic functions of MECR in MECR-null cells, we showed that specific antiviral activity is independent of mtFAS and is reconstituted by expressing cMECR. Thus, we propose a strategy where alternative splicing produces a cryptic antiviral protein that is embedded within a key metabolic enzyme.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ERR2 and ERR3 promote the development of gamma motor neuron functional properties required for proprioceptive movement control</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001923" title="ERR2 and ERR3 promote the development of gamma motor neuron functional properties required for proprioceptive movement control" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001923.PDF" title="(PDF) ERR2 and ERR3 promote the development of gamma motor neuron functional properties required for proprioceptive movement control" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001923.XML" title="(XML) ERR2 and ERR3 promote the development of gamma motor neuron functional properties required for proprioceptive movement control" />
    <author>
      <name>Mudassar N. Khan</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Pitchaiah Cherukuri</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Francesco Negro</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Ashish Rajput</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Piotr Fabrowski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Vikas Bansal</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Camille Lancelin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Tsung-I Lee</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Yehan Bian</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>William P. Mayer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Turgay Akay</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Daniel Müller</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stefan Bonn</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Dario Farina</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Till Marquardt</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001923</id>
    <updated>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Mudassar N. Khan, Pitchaiah Cherukuri, Francesco Negro, Ashish Rajput, Piotr Fabrowski, Vikas Bansal, Camille Lancelin, Tsung-I Lee, Yehan Bian, William P. Mayer, Turgay Akay, Daniel Müller, Stefan Bonn, Dario Farina, Till Marquardt&lt;/p&gt;

The ability of terrestrial vertebrates to effectively move on land is integrally linked to the diversification of motor neurons into types that generate muscle force (alpha motor neurons) and types that modulate muscle proprioception, a task that in mammals is chiefly mediated by gamma motor neurons. The diversification of motor neurons into alpha and gamma types and their respective contributions to movement control have been firmly established in the past 7 decades, while recent studies identified gene expression signatures linked to both motor neuron types. However, the mechanisms that promote the specification of gamma motor neurons and/or their unique properties remained unaddressed. Here, we found that upon selective loss of the orphan nuclear receptors ERR2 and ERR3 (also known as ERRβ, ERRγ or NR3B2, NR3B3, respectively) in motor neurons in mice, morphologically distinguishable gamma motor neurons are generated but do not acquire characteristic functional properties necessary for regulating muscle proprioception, thus disrupting gait and precision movements. Complementary gain-of-function experiments in chick suggest that ERR2 and ERR3 could operate via transcriptional activation of neural activity modulators to promote a gamma motor neuron biophysical signature of low firing thresholds and high firing rates. Our work identifies a mechanism specifying gamma motor neuron functional properties essential for the regulation of proprioceptive movement control.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Efficient coding theory of dynamic attentional modulation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001889" title="Efficient coding theory of dynamic attentional modulation" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001889.PDF" title="(PDF) Efficient coding theory of dynamic attentional modulation" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001889.XML" title="(XML) Efficient coding theory of dynamic attentional modulation" />
    <author>
      <name>Wiktor Młynarski</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Gašper Tkačik</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001889</id>
    <updated>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-21T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Wiktor Młynarski, Gašper Tkačik&lt;/p&gt;

Activity of sensory neurons is driven not only by external stimuli but also by feedback signals from higher brain areas. Attention is one particularly important internal signal whose presumed role is to modulate sensory representations such that they only encode information currently relevant to the organism at minimal cost. This hypothesis has, however, not yet been expressed in a normative computational framework. Here, by building on normative principles of probabilistic inference and efficient coding, we developed a model of dynamic population coding in the visual cortex. By continuously adapting the sensory code to changing demands of the perceptual observer, an attention-like modulation emerges. This modulation can dramatically reduce the amount of neural activity without deteriorating the accuracy of task-specific inferences. Our results suggest that a range of seemingly disparate cortical phenomena such as intrinsic gain modulation, attention-related tuning modulation, and response variability could be manifestations of the same underlying principles, which combine efficient sensory coding with optimal probabilistic inference in dynamic environments.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Correction: Do multiple experimenters improve the reproducibility of animal studies?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001948" title="Correction: Do multiple experimenters improve the reproducibility of animal studies?" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001948.PDF" title="(PDF) Correction: Do multiple experimenters improve the reproducibility of animal studies?" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001948.XML" title="(XML) Correction: Do multiple experimenters improve the reproducibility of animal studies?" />
    <author>
      <name>Vanessa Tabea von Kortzfleisch</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Oliver Ambrée</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Natasha A. Karp</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Neele Meyer</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Janja Novak</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Rupert Palme</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Marianna Rosso</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Chadi Touma</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Hanno Würbel</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Sylvia Kaiser</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Norbert Sachser</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>S. Helene Richter</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001948</id>
    <updated>2022-12-20T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-20T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Vanessa Tabea von Kortzfleisch, Oliver Ambrée, Natasha A. Karp, Neele Meyer, Janja Novak, Rupert Palme, Marianna Rosso, Chadi Touma, Hanno Würbel, Sylvia Kaiser, Norbert Sachser, S. Helene Richter&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Rapid and predictable genome evolution across three hybrid ant populations</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001914" title="Rapid and predictable genome evolution across three hybrid ant populations" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001914.PDF" title="(PDF) Rapid and predictable genome evolution across three hybrid ant populations" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001914.XML" title="(XML) Rapid and predictable genome evolution across three hybrid ant populations" />
    <author>
      <name>Pierre Nouhaud</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Simon H. Martin</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Beatriz Portinha</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Vitor C. Sousa</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jonna Kulmuni</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001914</id>
    <updated>2022-12-20T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-20T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Pierre Nouhaud, Simon H. Martin, Beatriz Portinha, Vitor C. Sousa, Jonna Kulmuni&lt;/p&gt;

Hybridization is frequent in the wild but it is unclear when admixture events lead to predictable outcomes and if so, at what timescale. We show that selection led to correlated sorting of genetic variation rapidly after admixture in 3 hybrid &lt;i&gt;Formica aquilonia&lt;/i&gt; × &lt;i&gt;F&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;polyctena&lt;/i&gt; ant populations. Removal of ancestry from the species with the lowest effective population size happened in all populations, consistent with purging of deleterious load. This process was modulated by recombination rate variation and the density of functional sites. Moreover, haplotypes with signatures of positive selection in either species were more likely to fix in hybrids. These mechanisms led to mosaic genomes with comparable ancestry proportions. Our work demonstrates predictable evolution over short timescales after admixture in nature.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The structure of the human LACTB filament reveals the mechanisms of assembly and membrane binding</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001899" title="The structure of the human LACTB filament reveals the mechanisms of assembly and membrane binding" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001899.PDF" title="(PDF) The structure of the human LACTB filament reveals the mechanisms of assembly and membrane binding" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001899.XML" title="(XML) The structure of the human LACTB filament reveals the mechanisms of assembly and membrane binding" />
    <author>
      <name>Jeremy A. Bennett</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Lottie R. Steward</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Johannes Rudolph</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Adam P. Voss</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Halil Aydin</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001899</id>
    <updated>2022-12-19T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-19T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Jeremy A. Bennett, Lottie R. Steward, Johannes Rudolph, Adam P. Voss, Halil Aydin&lt;/p&gt;

Mitochondria are complex organelles that play a central role in metabolism. Dynamic membrane-associated processes regulate mitochondrial morphology and bioenergetics in response to cellular demand. In tumor cells, metabolic reprogramming requires active mitochondrial metabolism for providing key metabolites and building blocks for tumor growth and rapid proliferation. To counter this, the mitochondrial serine beta-lactamase-like protein (LACTB) alters mitochondrial lipid metabolism and potently inhibits the proliferation of a variety of tumor cells. Mammalian LACTB is localized in the mitochondrial intermembrane space (IMS), where it assembles into filaments to regulate the efficiency of essential metabolic processes. However, the structural basis of LACTB polymerization and regulation remains incompletely understood. Here, we describe how human LACTB self-assembles into micron-scale filaments that increase their catalytic activity. The electron cryo-microscopy (cryoEM) structure defines the mechanism of assembly and reveals how highly ordered filament bundles stabilize the active state of the enzyme. We identify and characterize residues that are located at the filament-forming interface and further show that mutations that disrupt filamentation reduce enzyme activity. Furthermore, our results provide evidence that LACTB filaments can bind lipid membranes. These data reveal the detailed molecular organization and polymerization-based regulation of human LACTB and provide new insights into the mechanism of mitochondrial membrane organization that modulates lipid metabolism.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reflecting on 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001957" title="Reflecting on 2022" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001957.PDF" title="(PDF) Reflecting on 2022" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001957.XML" title="(XML) Reflecting on 2022" />
    <author>
      <name>Joanna Clarke</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>on behalf of the PLOS Biology Staff Editors</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001957</id>
    <updated>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Joanna Clarke, on behalf of the PLOS Biology Staff Editors &lt;/p&gt;

As 2022 draws to a close, we look back at some of the recent changes that have taken place at PLOS Biology, highlight some of our editors’ favorite moments from the past year across the life sciences, and thank our editors, authors and peer-reviewers.

As 2022 draws to a close, we look back at some of the recent changes that have taken place at PLOS Biology, highlight some of our editors’ favorite moments from the past year across the life sciences, and thank our editors, authors and peer-reviewers.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Turning decisions into actions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001927" title="Turning decisions into actions" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001927.PDF" title="(PDF) Turning decisions into actions" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001927.XML" title="(XML) Turning decisions into actions" />
    <author>
      <name>Alexander Gail</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001927</id>
    <updated>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Alexander Gail&lt;/p&gt;

Are selection and control of action serial processes of separate neural modules? A new study in PLOS Biology argues against this and in favor of an integrated process distributed across multiple brain regions, each contributing in a distinct way.

Are selection and control of action serial processes of separate neural modules? This Primer explores a study in PLOS Biology which argues against this and in favor of an integrated process distributed over multiple brain regions, each contributing in a distinct way.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Exploring the genetic architecture of protein secretion in &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/i&gt;) for biotechnology applications</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001911" title="Exploring the genetic architecture of protein secretion in &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/i&gt;) for biotechnology applications" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001911.PDF" title="(PDF) Exploring the genetic architecture of protein secretion in &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/i&gt;) for biotechnology applications" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001911.XML" title="(XML) Exploring the genetic architecture of protein secretion in &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii&lt;/i&gt; (&lt;i&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/i&gt;) for biotechnology applications" />
    <author>
      <name>Chantle Reiko Swichkow</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Joshua S. Bloom</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Leonid Kruglyak</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001911</id>
    <updated>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-16T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Chantle Reiko Swichkow, Joshua S. Bloom, Leonid Kruglyak&lt;/p&gt;

Improvements to the production of proteins in industrial yeast species have largely relied on generating variation in a single genetic background. A new study in PLOS Biology leverages natural genetic variation to identify genes and variants with the potential to improve protein yield.

Improvements to the production of proteins in industrial yeast species have largely relied on engineering in a single genetic background. This Primer explores a new approach described in PLOS Biology which leverages natural genetic variation to identify genes and variants with the potential to improve protein yield.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Identification of genetic variants of the industrial yeast &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii (Pichia pastoris)&lt;/i&gt; that contribute to increased yields of secreted heterologous proteins</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001877" title="Identification of genetic variants of the industrial yeast &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii (Pichia pastoris)&lt;/i&gt; that contribute to increased yields of secreted heterologous proteins" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001877.PDF" title="(PDF) Identification of genetic variants of the industrial yeast &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii (Pichia pastoris)&lt;/i&gt; that contribute to increased yields of secreted heterologous proteins" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001877.XML" title="(XML) Identification of genetic variants of the industrial yeast &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii (Pichia pastoris)&lt;/i&gt; that contribute to increased yields of secreted heterologous proteins" />
    <author>
      <name>Benjamin Offei</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Stephanie Braun-Galleani</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Anjan Venkatesh</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>William T. Casey</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin E. O’Connor</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kevin P. Byrne</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Kenneth H. Wolfe</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001877</id>
    <updated>2022-12-15T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-15T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Benjamin Offei, Stephanie Braun-Galleani, Anjan Venkatesh, William T. Casey, Kevin E. O’Connor, Kevin P. Byrne, Kenneth H. Wolfe&lt;/p&gt;

The yeast &lt;i&gt;Komagataella phaffii&lt;/i&gt; (formerly called &lt;i&gt;Pichia pastoris&lt;/i&gt;) is used widely as a host for secretion of heterologous proteins, but only a few isolates of this species exist and all the commonly used expression systems are derived from a single genetic background, CBS7435 (NRRL Y-11430). We hypothesized that other genetic backgrounds could harbor variants that affect yields of secreted proteins. We crossed CBS7435 with 2 other &lt;i&gt;K&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;i&gt;phaffii&lt;/i&gt; isolates and mapped quantitative trait loci (QTLs) for secretion of a heterologous protein, β-glucosidase, by sequencing individual segregant genomes. A major QTL mapped to a frameshift mutation in the mannosyltransferase gene &lt;i&gt;HOC1&lt;/i&gt;, which gives CBS7435 a weaker cell wall and higher protein secretion than the other isolates. Inactivation of &lt;i&gt;HOC1&lt;/i&gt; in the other isolates doubled β-glucosidase secretion. A second QTL mapped to an amino acid substitution in &lt;i&gt;IRA1&lt;/i&gt; that tripled β-glucosidase secretion in 1-week batch cultures but reduced cell viability, and its effects are specific to this heterologous protein. Our results demonstrate that QTL analysis is a powerful method for dissecting the basis of biotechnological traits in nonconventional yeasts, and a route to improving their industrial performance.</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Integrated neural dynamics of sensorimotor decisions and actions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001861" title="Integrated neural dynamics of sensorimotor decisions and actions" />
    <link rel="related" type="application/pdf" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001861.PDF" title="(PDF) Integrated neural dynamics of sensorimotor decisions and actions" />
    <link rel="related" type="text/xml" href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article/asset?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001861.XML" title="(XML) Integrated neural dynamics of sensorimotor decisions and actions" />
    <author>
      <name>David Thura</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Jean-François Cabana</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Albert Feghaly</name>
    </author>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Cisek</name>
    </author>
    <id>10.1371/journal.pbio.3001861</id>
    <updated>2022-12-15T14:00:00Z</updated>
    <published>2022-12-15T14:00:00Z</published>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by David Thura, Jean-François Cabana, Albert Feghaly, Paul Cisek&lt;/p&gt;

Recent theoretical models suggest that deciding about actions and executing them are not implemented by completely distinct neural mechanisms but are instead two modes of an integrated dynamical system. Here, we investigate this proposal by examining how neural activity unfolds during a dynamic decision-making task within the high-dimensional space defined by the activity of cells in monkey dorsal premotor (PMd), primary motor (M1), and dorsolateral prefrontal cortex (dlPFC) as well as the external and internal segments of the globus pallidus (GPe, GPi). Dimensionality reduction shows that the four strongest components of neural activity are functionally interpretable, reflecting a state transition between deliberation and commitment, the transformation of sensory evidence into a choice, and the baseline and slope of the rising urgency to decide. Analysis of the contribution of each population to these components shows meaningful differences between regions but no distinct clusters within each region, consistent with an integrated dynamical system. During deliberation, cortical activity unfolds on a two-dimensional “decision manifold” defined by sensory evidence and urgency and falls off this manifold at the moment of commitment into a choice-dependent trajectory leading to movement initiation. The structure of the manifold varies between regions: In PMd, it is curved; in M1, it is nearly perfectly flat; and in dlPFC, it is almost entirely confined to the sensory evidence dimension. In contrast, pallidal activity during deliberation is primarily defined by urgency. We suggest that these findings reveal the distinct functional contributions of different brain regions to an integrated dynamical system governing action selection and execution.</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
