<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>American Humane</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.americanhumane.org/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.americanhumane.org</link>
	<description>Founded in 1877, American Humane is committed to ensuring the safety, welfare and well-being of animals.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 19:56:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Remembering the Animal Advocates We Lost in 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/remembering-the-animal-advocates-we-lost-in-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 19:56:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As we look toward a new year full of promise and hope for animals and people, we must also remember those we lost in 2022 who helped further American Humane’s “First To Serve” mission. While these animal lovers may no longer be with us physically, their spirit and generosity live on through their dedicated support [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/remembering-the-animal-advocates-we-lost-in-2022/">Remembering the Animal Advocates We Lost in 2022</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As we look toward a new year full of promise and hope for animals and people, we must also remember those we lost in 2022 who helped further American Humane’s “First To Serve” mission. While these animal lovers may no longer be with us physically, their spirit and generosity live on through their dedicated support of animals all across the globe.</p>
<h3><strong>Betty White</strong></h3>
<p>Betty White served as one of the most effective and passionate animal advocates that American Humane has ever seen for almost 100 years. We are proud to say that Betty remains the longest-serving supporter in the organization’s illustrious history.</p>
<p><iframe title="American Humane Honors Betty White and Naomi Judd" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jkdtq_VXGAU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>The affable actress with a soft spot for animals volunteered as a member of American Humane’s board of directors, supported the organization’s “<a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/initiative/no-animals-were-harmed/">No Animals Were Harmed®</a>” program protecting animals in film and television, lent her services to fundraising activities, acted as a judge and presenter for the nationally televised <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/initiative/american-humane-hero-dog-awards/">American Humane Hero Dog Awards</a>, and served as the chair of its now 106-year-old nationwide “<a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/initiative/be-kind-to-animals-week/">Be Kind to Animals Week®</a>”—the most successful humane education campaign and the oldest commemorative week in U.S. history.</p>
<p>For all of her outstanding efforts, Betty received American Humane’s National Humanitarian Medal,  our highest honor. Even in her passing, Betty’s memory helped raise hundreds of thousands of dollars for animals through the #BettyWhiteChallenge. She championed the cause of millions of furred, finned and feathered friends around the world and never missed an opportunity to help animals in need.</p>
<h3><strong>Naomi Judd<br />
</strong></h3>
<p>Iconic country music legend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Jkdtq_VXGAU&amp;t=42s">Naomi Judd</a> served on the board of American Humane for nearly a decade and was enthusiastically active in the organization’s veteran efforts. Naomi volunteered to help both reunite retired military working dogs with their former handlers and to help pair veterans with highly skilled service dogs through American Humane’s <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/initiative/pts-service-dogs-for-veterans/">Pups4Patriots</a> program.</p>
<p>She also fought valiantly to include language in the 2016 Defense Authorization Act that ultimately led to ensuring our brave military working dogs are brought back home to U.S. soil after retirement. Thanks to her efforts, former MWD handlers have the first right to adopt their battle buddies to help ensure a peaceful retirement for these often-unrecognized heroes. Naomi’s loving spirit and deep appreciation for our nation’s veterans lives on in these programs and their mission.</p>
<h3><strong>Dr. Bernie Rollin</strong></h3>
<p>Dr. Rollin is credited with bringing extraordinary change to the animal welfare industry. He taught the first-ever course on veterinary medical ethics and profoundly altered the way veterinarians are taught and how they practice. Dr. Rollin co-wrote the 1982 federal laws that enforce the humane treatment of animals in research and, as a result, was described as the person “who alleviated more animal pain than anyone in history.”</p>
<p>Dr. Rollin had a special relationship with American Humane and served on many advisory committees for our organization’s programs. His brilliant work helped make a significant, meaningful difference for millions of animals over the years.</p>
<h3><strong>Dennis Grisco</strong></h3>
<p>As an animal trainer who began his work in the film industry in the 1960s, Dennis Grisco helped keep our feathered and furred best friends safe on movie sets for more than half a century. From <em>Dr. Quinn, Medicine Woman</em> to <em>Pirates of the Caribbean: Dead Man&#8217;s Chest</em>, Dennis was a magnificent trainer committed to the animal actors who enhance our favorite movie and television shows.</p>
<p>Dennis worked with American Humane representatives throughout the years and was always a kind and passionate soul to them and the animals they helped protect on set. He was also a master falconer and contributed both great knowledge and compassion to the sport of falconry. His work will live on in the many movies and TV shows he helped bring to life for so many years.</p>
<p>There are countless others we lost this year who helped us protect animals across the globe, and we thank them all for their courage and compassion. American Humane is beyond appreciative to have known these inimitable champions of animal welfare.</p>
<p>If you’d like to donate in honor of these special heroes, <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/?form=challenge-2022">click here</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/remembering-the-animal-advocates-we-lost-in-2022/">Remembering the Animal Advocates We Lost in 2022</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Visit The Zoo Day</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/national-visit-the-zoo-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 14:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Conservation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7515</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>December 27th is National Visit the Zoo Day. Ever since the first one opened in 1793, zoos have been home to a wide range of species from around the world. They have provided visitors with close encounters to wildlife and advanced invaluable scientific research. Just one trip to the zoo can increase one’s environmental awareness, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/national-visit-the-zoo-day/">National Visit The Zoo Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>December 27th is National Visit the Zoo Day. Ever since the first one opened in 1793, zoos have been home to a wide range of species from around the world. They have provided visitors with close encounters to wildlife and advanced invaluable scientific research. Just one trip to the zoo can increase one’s environmental awareness, cultivating a deep appreciation for the natural world.</p>
<p>But zoos are much more than just spaces of entertainment and learning: they are modern conservation facilities protecting the most endangered species. Critics inaccurately portray zoos as inherently inhumane facilities that do nothing other than enclose animals for our enjoyment. In doing so, they ignore the numerous vital programs administered by zoos to support wildlife conservation.</p>
<p>In particular, zoos have a successful track record managing breeding programs that repopulate extinct animals. Take the Perth Zoo in Australia. For over a century, scientists believed the western swamp tortoise went extinct. The species was then rediscovered in 1953 in a small habitat in the Swan Valley region, making the tortoise critically endangered. Now the species is slowly reemerging thanks to the zoo’s diligent conservation efforts. In fact, nearly 1,000 of these animals have been reared in the facility in the last three decades–many of which have gone back to the wild.</p>
<p>A longtime champion of zoos and aquariums, American Humane is the first humane organization with a certification program verifying that facilities meet the highest standards of animal care. When you see the American Humane Certified<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> logo, you can rest assured that the zoo meets our benchmark of good welfare and humane treatment. And unlike other certifiers, our evidence-based standards are set by world-renowned experts in animal science and ethics</p>
<p>This holiday season, we encourage you and your loved ones to plan a visit to your local zoo. Not only will you form unforgettable memories, but you will also support the valuable work of wildlife preservation. To learn more about Humane Certified, visit <a href="https://humaneconservation.org/certified-parks/">https://humaneconservation.org/certified-parks/</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/national-visit-the-zoo-day/">National Visit The Zoo Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protect Your Pets This Holiday Season</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/protect-your-pets-this-holiday-season/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 17:22:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tips]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7516</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The holiday season is upon us, which marks the official start of winter in the United States. A few notable reindeer will brave the frigid conditions on the night of December 24th, but all animals without magical powers need to be kept safe from the incoming cold weather. The Christmas season is all about giving, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/protect-your-pets-this-holiday-season/">Protect Your Pets This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The holiday season is upon us, which marks the official start of winter in the United States. A few notable reindeer will brave the frigid conditions on the night of December 24<sup>th</sup>, but all animals without magical powers need to be kept safe from the incoming cold weather. The Christmas season is all about giving, and you’ll need to remember to give your pets the best possible care during the potentially dangerous winter months ahead.</p>
<p>It’s a common misconception that dogs and cats are more resistant than people to cold weather because of their fur. Like people, animals are susceptible to frostbite and hypothermia. Exposure to winter’s dry, cold air and chilly rain, sleet and snow can cause chapped paws and itchy, flaking skin for your pets. Many animals also become lost in the winter because snow and ice can hide recognizable scents that might normally help your pet find his/her way back home.</p>
<p>Below are some simple tips to ensure a humane winter and help you prioritize your pets’ safety:</p>
<p><strong>Prepare for Cold Weather</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Plan ahead and pay attention to cold-weather warnings.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Keep your pet preparedness kit well-stocked and ready. During a winter storm, you may not be able to leave your home for several days.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Leave your pets’ coats a little longer in the winter to provide as much warmth as possible. That summer “short cut” from your groomer should be avoided during cold weather. If you have short-haired breeds, consider getting them a coat or sweater that covers them from neck to tail and around the abdomen.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Winter Pet Care</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>When you bathe your dogs in cold weather, make sure they are completely dry before taking them outside for some play time or a walk.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>When walking your dogs during bad weather, keep them on a leash. More dogs are lost during winter than any other season, as it’s easier for a dog to become lost in winter storm conditions. (And don’t forget to microchip and put current ID tags on your dogs and cats!)</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Leash your pets if you have frozen ponds, lakes or rivers nearby, as loose pets can break through ice and quickly succumb to hypothermia before trained ice-rescue personnel can arrive. Never attempt an ice rescue of a pet yourself – leave that to trained professionals.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>When you are working on housebreaking your new puppy, remember that puppies are more susceptible to cold than adult dogs. In cold conditions or bad weather, you may need to opt for paper training your new pet rather than taking your pup outside.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Keep your pets inside, both during the day and night. Just because they have fur doesn’t mean they can withstand cold temperatures.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>If dogs must be left outside for any period of time, they should have a draft-free shelter large enough to stand and turn around in, yet small enough to retain body heat. Use a layer of straw or other bedding material to help insulate them against the cold. Make sure the entrance to the shelter faces away from the direction of incoming wind and snow.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Keep your cats indoors. Cats can freeze in cold weather without shelter. Sometimes cats left outdoors in cold weather seek shelter and heat under the hoods of automobiles and are injured or killed when the ignition is turned on. Banging loudly on the hood of your car a few times before starting the engine will help avoid a tragic situation. (This is true for wild animals in cold weather as well.)</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Precautions for Outdoor Pets</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Remember that staying warm requires extra calories. Outdoor animals typically need more calories in the winter, so feed them accordingly when the temperature drops. Talk to your veterinarian for advice on a proper diet.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Watch your pet’s outside fresh-water bowl. If it is not heated, you may need to refresh it more often as it could freeze in cold weather.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Salt and de-icers: Many pets like to go outside to romp and stomp in the snow, but people use powerful salt and chemicals on their sidewalks to combat ice buildup. Thoroughly clean your pets’ paws, legs and abdomen after they have been outside, to prevent ingestion of toxic substances and to prevent their pads from becoming dry and irritated. Signs of toxic ingestion include excessive drooling, vomiting and depression.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Ice and snow: When you let your pets in from a walk or a romp outside, make sure to wipe their paws and undersides — get those ice balls off as soon as possible, as they can cause frostbite. After being outside, check your pets’ paws, ears and tail for frostbite. Frostbitten skin usually appears pale or gray and can be treated by wrapping the area in a dry towel to gradually warm the area. Check with your veterinarian if you suspect frostbite.</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>Use nontoxic antifreeze. Antifreeze tastes delicious to pets but ingesting even a very small amount can be deadly. Look for “safe” nontoxic antifreeze, consider using products that contain propylene glycol rather than ethylene glycol, and make sure all spills are cleaned up immediately and thoroughly. Contact your veterinarian immediately if you suspect your pets have ingested any antifreeze.</li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/protect-your-pets-this-holiday-season/">Protect Your Pets This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Appreciate Your Feline Friends This Holiday Season</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7499/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 15:42:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tips]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7499</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>December is a celebratory month marked by several major holidays. A lesser-known celebration in December is National Cat Lovers Month. On this special occasion, we take the time to appreciate the furry feline friends who enrich our lives. Most historians estimate that cats were domesticated around 9,000 years ago in the Fertile Crescent area (today’s [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7499/">Appreciate Your Feline Friends This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>December is a celebratory month marked by several major holidays. A lesser-known celebration in December is National Cat Lovers Month. On this special occasion, we take the time to appreciate the furry feline friends who enrich our lives.</p>
<p>Most historians estimate that cats were domesticated around 9,000 years ago in the Fertile Crescent area (today’s Middle East). A popular pet along with dogs, cats are beloved for their fierce independence, affection, loyalty, and low maintenance. With nearly fifty different breeds, cats can come in many different coat colors, temperaments, and tail lengths. According to the Centers for Disease Control, nearly 40 million households in the United States have cats, bringing joy and companionship to their owners. In the words of writer Charles Dickens, “What greater gift than the love of a cat.”</p>
<p>While domestic cats may not be an endangered species demanding conservation efforts, they still face multiple threats to their well-being and survival. For starters, animal shelters across the country are frequently overpopulated with cats and kittens–many the result of accidental litters and owners who abandoned them. Moreover, inadequate funding and the lack of foot traffic at shelters dim the hope of these incredible creatures finding a home. Worse yet, hundreds of thousands of cats are tragically euthanized every year due to overpopulation.</p>
<p>At American Humane, we recognize that cats desperately need our help more than ever. Through our <a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3rW1p1LE9DX1gOu9SD7/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Finitiative%2Ffeed-the-hungry-fund%2F">Feed the Hungry</a> campaign, we are contributing thousands of meals to shelter animals, along with generous grants to struggling shelters. Another way we support the welfare of cats is by providing resources and helpful information to potential cat owners. Check out our links below for more information on the process of adopting a cat.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3jrqwxVwb9YyAHyTttV/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fcat-adoption-checklist%2F">A</a> <a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3jrqwxVwb9YyAHyTttV/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fcat-adoption-checklist%2F">Cat Adoption Checklist</a></li>
<li><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3PDw4uUC_3yfg5_mNRn/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fintroducing-cats-to-cats%2F">Introducing</a><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3PDw4uUC_3yfg5_mNRn/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fintroducing-cats-to-cats%2F"> Cats to Cats</a></li>
<li><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3Hs7BXR3hqcFAk6CEwD/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fintroducing-dogs-to-cats%2F">Introducing</a><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3Hs7BXR3hqcFAk6CEwD/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fintroducing-dogs-to-cats%2F"> Dogs to Cats</a></li>
<li><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-2-i4qfZujVZjgdZPbY5/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fchoosing-a-cat-collar%2F">Choosing</a><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-2-i4qfZujVZjgdZPbY5/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fchoosing-a-cat-collar%2F"> a Cat Collar</a></li>
<li><a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3H_P9wGmTvAJw9aYPJ5/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fscratching%2F">Cats</a> <a href="https://streaklinks.com/BUYS-3H_P9wGmTvAJw9aYPJ5/https%3A%2F%2Fwww.americanhumane.org%2Ffact-sheet%2Fscratching%2F">and Scratching</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7499/">Appreciate Your Feline Friends This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Join Us In Celebrating International Animal Rights Day</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7488/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 14:00:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Conservation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7488</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>December 10th is International Animal Rights Day – a special occasion to reaffirm our obligation to protect and preserve the animals that enliven our planet. Started by the humane organization, Uncaged, in 1998, this date intentionally coincides with Human Rights Day, reminding us that values such as dignity and respect are also owed to animals. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7488/">Join Us In Celebrating International Animal Rights Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>December 10th is International Animal Rights Day – a special occasion to reaffirm our obligation to protect and preserve the animals that enliven our planet.</p>
<p>Started by the humane organization, Uncaged, in 1998, this date intentionally coincides with Human Rights Day, reminding us that values such as dignity and respect are also owed to animals. Animals cannot protest, advocate, or vote for their own protection – giving humans this sacred responsibility.</p>
<p>Why should we care so much about animal rights? For starters, animals are sentient beings with the capacity to feel pleasure, pain, happiness, and distress. As such, animals deserve basic protections to minimize any unnecessary harm or threats.</p>
<p>We must also recognize that animals are not just valuable for their own sake. In an interconnected world, they belong to a wider ecosystem where they provide food, nutrients, and other functions to wildlife and people. As a prime example, pets make affectionate companions to humans – enriching our lives through social and emotional support.</p>
<p>Today, far too many species face inhumane treatment, violence, and even the specter of extinction.</p>
<p>Just this past week, law enforcement <a href="https://nj1015.com/crazy-rescue-ladies-jailed-on-animal-child-abuse-charges-in-brick-nj/">rescued</a> over 180 dogs and cats from a New Jersey home, where the animals were subjected to deplorable conditions and overcrowding. Similarly, the U.S. Department of Agriculture recently <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/elon-musk-neuralink-brain-chip-animal-abuse-accusation-investigation-report-2022-12">announced</a> an animal abuse probe of Elon Musk’s brain chip company Neuralink, which has reportedly killed around 1,500 animals through testing and experiments.</p>
<p>Recently, we <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/publication/a-new-deal-for-animals-people-and-the-world-we-share/">acknowledged</a> that humans have “failed to honor the human-animal bond which has resulted in a breakdown of our social contract with the animal world.” At American Humane, our core mission is to strengthen our bond with animals by ensuring their safety, welfare, and well-being.</p>
<p>We believe an effective way to defend animal rights is supporting organizations involved in wildlife conservation – especially zoos and aquariums.</p>
<p>Through our Humane Conservation program, we provide certification to facilities meeting the highest standards of animal care. Whether it’s managing breeding programs for endangered species or spreading awareness of wildlife protection, zoos play a critical role in enlisting public support for defending vulnerable animals. Learn more about our conservation efforts <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/program/conservation/">here</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7488/">Join Us In Celebrating International Animal Rights Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Wildlife Conservation Day and International Cheetah Day</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/wildlife-conservation-day-and-international-cheetah-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 14:00:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Conservation]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7477</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>December 4th marks Wildlife Conservation Day. Established by the U.S. State Department in 2012, this day seeks to raise awareness about preserving Earth’s most vulnerable species. It reminds us of our moral obligation to protect the animals that enrich our planet and our lives. One of the most well-known endangered species is the cheetah–and as [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/wildlife-conservation-day-and-international-cheetah-day/">Wildlife Conservation Day and International Cheetah Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>December 4th marks Wildlife Conservation Day. Established by the U.S. State Department in 2012, this day seeks to raise awareness about preserving Earth’s most vulnerable species. It reminds us of our moral obligation to protect the animals that enrich our planet and our lives.</p>
<p>One of the most well-known endangered species is the cheetah–and as luck would have it, today is also International Cheetah Day.</p>
<p>Native to sub-Saharan Africa and central Iran, cheetahs are widely known as the fastest land animal, capable of sprinting up to 75 miles per hour in just three seconds. At full speed, cheetahs take around three strides per second, each of which covers around 22 feet. Sleek and slender, they are also beloved for their elegant, golden-tan coat covered with solid black spots.</p>
<p>Sadly, the cheetah population is rapidly declining. According to the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, only around 7,000 cheetahs are alive today, making them the most endangered big cat in Africa. One century ago, over 100,000 of them roamed the planet–marking a decline of over 90 percent in that timespan alone. Moreover, cheetahs are now considered extinct in 30 former range countries in Africa and the Middle East, displaced from the habitats where they once thrived.</p>
<p>Primary threats to cheetahs’ existence include hunting, wildlife trafficking, and habitat loss. Cheetahs are especially vulnerable to the illegal pet trade as their colorful fur remains an in-demand product among animal hunters. They are also frequently targeted by farmers who arbitrarily kill them, hoping they can preempt attacks against their livestock.</p>
<p>What is American Humane doing to support wildlife conservation and protect vulnerable species like the cheetah?</p>
<p>While the UN and other international bodies have coordinated activities to highlight the plight of big cats, we are committed to supporting zoos and aquariums involved in preserving the million species endangered in today’s Sixth Mass Extinction.</p>
<p>Through our Humane Conservation program, we provide certification to zoological organizations meeting high standards of animal care. Certified zoos and aquariums may be among the best-equipped facilities to save Earth’s incredible animals–including the cheetah. Learn more about how you can support our conservation efforts <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/program/conservation/">here</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/wildlife-conservation-day-and-international-cheetah-day/">Wildlife Conservation Day and International Cheetah Day</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Cleats For Cause: NFL Running Back Plays for Pups4Patriots</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/cleats-for-cause-nfl-running-back-plays-for-pups4patriots/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 14:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Pups4Patriots]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>This weekend, the National Football League celebrates “My Cause, My Cleats” – an annual game in which players showcase a social cause close to their hearts. Participants will don customized cleats representing their chosen organizations, which are then donated to the NFL Auction and sold. All proceeds from the sale are directly donated to the [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/cleats-for-cause-nfl-running-back-plays-for-pups4patriots/">Cleats For Cause: NFL Running Back Plays for Pups4Patriots</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This weekend, the National Football League celebrates “My Cause, My Cleats” – an annual game in which players showcase a social cause close to their hearts. Participants will don customized cleats representing their chosen organizations, which are then donated to the NFL Auction and sold. All proceeds from the sale are directly donated to the respective charities selected by the players.</p>
<p>This year, American Humane is proud to have Kenyan Drake, a running back for the Baltimore Ravens, playing in honor of Pups4Patriots!</p>
<p>Kenyan is a dedicated supporter of Pups4Patriots, even hosting a veteran appreciation event earlier this year with teammate Ronnie Stanley in Owing Mills, Maryland. The pair hold a special place in their hearts for those who previously or are currently serving in our military, as Stanley’s dad is a military veteran and Drake’s sister is currently serving.</p>
<blockquote><p><em>&#8220;This is literally the least I can do, just be able to use my platform to promote positivity in any realm, especially when it comes to veterans and the ultimate sacrifice they were able to make, for us to be able to do things like this. It definitely hits home for me to be able to do as much as I can because of the service they provide for our country, for us to be free.&#8221;</em></p>
<p><em> &#8211; Kenyan Drake </em></p></blockquote>
<p>Pups4Patriots is committed to matching veterans with exceptionally trained service dogs who can well understand their unique individual needs, at no cost to the veteran. Research shows that a specially trained service dog can significantly reduce stress and anxiety levels, easing social reintegration and providing comfort for affected veterans.</p>
<p>American Humane could not be more grateful to Kenyan for his continued support for Pups4Patriots and the attention he brings to our important work.</p>
<p>You can watch the Baltimore Ravens play their “My Cause, My Cleats” game against the Denver Broncos on Sunday, December 4 at 1:00 p.m. EST on CBS.</p>
<p>Learn more about American Humane’s Pups4Patriots program <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/initiative/pts-service-dogs-for-veterans/">here</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/cleats-for-cause-nfl-running-back-plays-for-pups4patriots/">Cleats For Cause: NFL Running Back Plays for Pups4Patriots</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Giving Tuesday: Gifts with Great Impact</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7472/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 21:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Giving Tuesday]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7472</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>With the shuffle of the holiday season, it can be easy to forget the true meaning of the season: spending time with the ones you love and giving back. That’s why in 2012, GivingTuesday was created with a simple mission to inspire people to give, collaborate, and celebrate generosity. Each year, billions of dollars are [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7472/">Giving Tuesday: Gifts with Great Impact</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>With the shuffle of the holiday season, it can be easy to forget the true meaning of the season: spending time with the ones you love and giving back. That’s why in 2012, GivingTuesday was created with a simple mission to inspire people to give, collaborate, and celebrate generosity.</p>
<p>Each year, billions of dollars are donated to people’s favorite charities and organizations on GivingTuesday – making a huge impact on the causes that mean the most to them.</p>
<p>For over 100 years, American Humane has been committed to helping ensure the safety, welfare, and well-being of animals, whether that’s through our rescue efforts, conservation efforts, or contributions to our country’s heroic veteran K9’s. We have always prided ourselves on being the “first to serve.”</p>
<p>But we can’t do it alone.</p>
<p>Our life saving work through our “No Animals Were Harmed<sup>®</sup>” in Hollywood program, rapid rescue and response teams across the country, and widespread grants and awards to local shelters can’t be done without you and your generosity.</p>
<p>This year, American Humane was fortunate enough to receive a $75,000 grant from an anonymous donor, allowing us the opportunity to <u>double</u> your donation to animals in need. This GivingTuesday, remember the animals and pets that have made an impact on your life. You can help save many more by visiting <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/givingtuesday">https://www.americanhumane.org/givingtuesday</a> and giving today. Your donation will be doubled, increasing your impact on animals who rely on us today and every day.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/7472/">Giving Tuesday: Gifts with Great Impact</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Setting a Humane Table This Holiday Season</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/setting-a-humane-table-this-holiday-season/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cory Gunkel]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 15:20:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Farm]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7449</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving is centered around the table, with the holiday serving as a centerpiece to enjoy food with those who give our life meaning. And today, more than ever, we are conscious of where the food we eat during these happy times comes from. We not only want good, healthy, food this Thanksgiving season – we [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/setting-a-humane-table-this-holiday-season/">Setting a Humane Table This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving is centered around the table, with the holiday serving as a centerpiece to enjoy food with those who give our life meaning. And today, more than ever, we are conscious of where the food we eat during these happy times comes from. We not only want good, healthy, food this Thanksgiving season – we want to support farmers and ranchers who do things right and who care deeply about the well-being of their animals.</p>
<p>This desire for humanely raised products isn’t just anecdotal, either. A recent American Humane survey found that an eye-opening 67 percent of people polled are concerned about the welfare of animals on farms today. In fact, 70 percent said they are likely to choose an American Humane Certified product over one that is not.</p>
<p>Fortunately, an increasing number of farmers, ranchers and food producers are improving and verifying the welfare of animals in their care by becoming American Humane Certified. These producers can help us all make mindful choices when putting our plates together during the holidays.</p>
<p>Producers like Coleman Natural Foods, whose delicious applewood smoked uncured ham makes a delectable Thanksgiving centerpiece, are key to this mission to set a humane table. Turkey is also an iconic and beloved Thanksgiving dish that has become synonymous with the holiday. Thankfully, Butterball s turkeys are American Humane Certified, which gives people who want to cook with compassion an option to do just that with Thanksgiving’s most iconic dish.</p>
<p>To highlight these American Humane Certified producers’ efforts, and help others set a humane table, American Humane <a href="https://www.americanhumane.org/publication/the-humane-table-cooking-with-compassion/">launched a new cookbook called </a><em>The Humane Table. </em>This beautiful book showcases mouth-watering recipes featuring ingredients that are compassionately produced by farmers, ranchers, and other organizations that boast the American Humane Certified seal. Proceeds from book sales will go straight back to American Humane to help to further the critical work of helping animals, including improving the lives of more than one billion farm animals across the globe.</p>
<p><em>The Humane Table </em>is a great way to help us eat ethically, not just during Thanksgiving, but all year long. So, please join us in setting a humane table  it’s yet another way for us all to help make the world a better place for both animals and people.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/setting-a-humane-table-this-holiday-season/">Setting a Humane Table This Holiday Season</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Together for the Holidays</title>
		<link>https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/together-for-the-holidays/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Savannah Young]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 14:00:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.americanhumane.org/?post_type=blog&#038;p=7398</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving has arrived, a special day in which all Americans gather to give thanks. And this holiday season, many veterans will be thankful to have a new lifesaving service dog by their side. In the past year, American Humane helped provide another dozen U.S. veterans struggling with Post-Traumatic Stress or Traumatic Brain Injury with free, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/together-for-the-holidays/">Together for the Holidays</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanksgiving has arrived, a special day in which all Americans gather to give thanks. And this holiday season, many veterans will be thankful to have a new lifesaving service dog by their side. In the past year, American Humane helped provide another dozen U.S. veterans struggling with Post-Traumatic Stress or Traumatic Brain Injury with free, highly trained service dogs through our Pups4Patriots<img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/2122.png" alt="™" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /> program. For the first time ever, these veteran and service dog pairs will be together for the holidays.</p>
<p>For many of our nation’s brave veterans, coming home is only the beginning of another daunting battle. The invisible wounds of war, including PTS and TBI, can cause debilitating symptoms in veterans, leading to depression, social isolation and, far too often, suicide.</p>
<p>Research shows that specially trained service dogs can reduce stress and anxiety levels, mitigate depression, ease social reintegration, provide comfort and restore confidence in affected veterans. However, there are many obstacles standing in the way of veterans in need of service dogs including long waiting lists and exorbitant costs.</p>
<p>To help, American Humane’s Pups4Patriots program finds dogs in search of forever homes and trains them to be lifesaving service dogs for veterans with PTS or TBI, at no cost to the veteran. We also oversee intensive hands-on training sessions to cultivate the important connection between the veteran and his or her new service dog.</p>
<p>Our most recent Pups4Patriots graduate was U.S. Marine Corps veteran Mark. Mark lives in California and was paired with Chesty, a Labrador Retriever. Upon graduating, Mark said, “I feel my life is back on track! After years of struggling to integrate into society and dealing with isolation, it seemed nothing helped. Now, because of Chesty, I have a reason to go out every day. He has improved my life dramatically and I have enthusiasm and optimism about the future. I am so grateful and appreciative.”</p>
<p>Service dogs like Chesty can make a world of difference for veterans, helping to alleviate symptoms associated with trauma and empower veterans to live healthy, happy lives. At American Humane, we are honored to support the brave men and women who serve our county, and we are committed to putting more healing leashes into the hands of veterans who need them.</p>
<p>Mark and Chesty, along with many other veteran and service dog pairs, are together for the holidays and will celebrate this season with a newfound love in their hearts. They have found their better half.</p>
<p>Our program is made possible through the generous support of donors, and this Thanksgiving, we thank YOU for making our efforts possible.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-7403" src="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="427" height="569" srcset="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-225x300.jpg 225w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-1536x2048.jpg 1536w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/61249163052-7EAF1EC9-E27C-4810-AC09-818E23A8289A-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 427px) 100vw, 427px" /><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-7404" src="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="427" height="570" srcset="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-225x300.jpg 225w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-1536x2048.jpg 1536w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-5439-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 427px) 100vw, 427px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone  wp-image-7399" src="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/Mark-Berrier-Chesty-237x300.jpg" alt="" width="423" height="535" srcset="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/Mark-Berrier-Chesty-237x300.jpg 237w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/Mark-Berrier-Chesty.jpg 506w" sizes="(max-width: 423px) 100vw, 423px" /><img decoding="async" class="alignnone  wp-image-7400" src="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-225x300.jpg" alt="" width="401" height="535" srcset="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-225x300.jpg 225w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-1536x2048.jpg 1536w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-7220-scaled.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 401px) 100vw, 401px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone wp-image-7401" src="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="664" height="498" srcset="https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-1024x769.jpg 1024w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-768x577.jpg 768w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-1536x1154.jpg 1536w, https://www.americanhumane.org/app/uploads/2022/11/IMG-6963-2048x1539.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 664px) 100vw, 664px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org/blog/together-for-the-holidays/">Together for the Holidays</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.americanhumane.org">American Humane</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
