<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Animal Welfare, Animal Welfare Related Positive News From India</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/topics/animal-welfare/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/topics/animal-welfare/</link>
	<description>Positive and Happy Stories. Unsung Heroes</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 08:04:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.0.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2019/10/cropped-tb-favicon-new-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Animal Welfare, Animal Welfare Related Positive News From India</title>
	<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/topics/animal-welfare/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Amid Concrete Jungles, 100s of Birds Flock to Feed in This Pune Woman’s Balcony Daily</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/298956/birds-feed-in-pune-home-balcony-daily-how-to-make-bird-feeder-for-parrots-sparrows/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystelle Dsouza]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2022 04:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Birds]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[DIY]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[balcony garden]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bamboo bird feeders]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[bird feeders diy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[how to make a bird feeder]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[natural bird feeder]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=298956</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pune resident Smita Pasalkar’s balcony is a rarity amid the concrete city, where hundreds of parrots, sparrows and more flock everyday. She shares how she does it.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>For many of us living in concrete jungles, waking up to the twitter of sparrows and a gust of cool breeze seems like a distant dream. </p>



<p>But this is not the case for Pune’s Chandan Nagar resident Smita Pasalkar.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Many would call her “lucky” for being able to start her day with a cup of <em>chai </em>and a <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/270107/terrace-gardening-tips-how-to-grow-vegetables-at-home/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">balcony abuzz with parrots</a>, sunbirds, sparrows and even squirrels.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1200" height="680" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598.jpg" alt="Smita Pasalkar in her balcony where she is visited by sparrows, parrots and sunbirds" class="wp-image-298959" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598-300x170.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598-500x283.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598-768x435.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-2-1663850401_11zon-1664608598-150x85.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>Smita Pasalkar in her balcony, Picture credits: Smita Pasalkar</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Neighbours who have lived in the same society for 20 years say this is the first time they’re witnessing such a sight. Parrots were almost a rarity here.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It all started six years ago when the fashion designer had just moved into this apartment. Though she was content with the location and the decor, there was something missing — birds. </p>



<h2 id="h-a-bird-lover-by-heart">A bird lover by heart&nbsp;</h2>



<p>“When I was a child, I would watch my father always keep feed and water for the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/292683/how-to-grow-fruits-on-terrace-gardening-tips-organic-mango-farming/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">birds in our garden</a>,” she tells <strong>The Better India</strong>, adding that the birds fly to the balcony, eat their fill, and even stay on for more.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Growing up watching this sight, Smita came to love birds and the happiness they brought into the space they flew into. She decided she would always continue to feed them, no matter where she went.&nbsp;</p>



<p>So when she shifted apartments, she was intent on creating a space where the birds could come and eat and fly.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But she would soon realise that birds weren’t very common in the area.</p>



<p>“There were no parrots to be seen, or for that matter, any birds at all,” she says, adding that she started <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/17686/5-secrets-to-the-most-amazing-terrace-garden-from-expert-viswanath-kadur/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">planting saplings in the balcony</a> to attract the creatures.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1024" height="580" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654.jpg" alt="Parrots in Smita Pasalkar's garden flock to the place to eat the bird feed" class="wp-image-298960" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654.jpg 1024w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654-300x170.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654-500x283.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654-768x435.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-3-1663850670-1024x580_11zon-1664608654-150x85.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Parrots in Smita Pasalkar&#8217;s garden, Picture credits: Smita Pasalkar</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Her strategy soon worked and in time, birds began to fill the balcony space, jostling each other to get their share of the water and grains that were kept in a bowl by Smita.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As the number of birds increased, Smita decided to set up feeders so birds would never go hungry. She set up seven feeders along the balcony and grew plants to create a natural environment.</p>



<p>Smita made the feeders herself using bamboo she procured from the village. In them, she fills sunflower seeds, rice, groundnuts, etc.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I purchase around 50 kg of rice a month to feed the birds,” she says, adding that once she started, many others in her society also began feeding birds. Who doesn’t want a <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/272981/how-to-grow-vegetables-in-pots-terrace-gardening-tips/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">balcony filled with birdsong</a>?&nbsp;</p>



<h2>A flock of parrots&nbsp;</h2>



<p>What amazed Smita and her neighbours was that even though parrot sightings are rare in their area, the large number visiting her balcony would claim otherwise.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“From one, it soon grew to three, four, and then many,” she says, adding that she set up feeders for parrots separately to attract more of them to the balcony.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Due to lack of space, Smita says, she hasn’t been able to plant fruits for the birds. But she has planted many <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/294289/how-to-grow-plants-on-slanting-terrace-gardening-tips-by-engineer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">flowers for the sunbird</a>.</p>



<p>People love the idea of what Smita does and frequently reach out with queries and seek information through the videos she puts up on social media.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I devote two hours every day to the cause of feeding the birds. I do this once I complete my household chores. It is an integral part of my everyday routine,” she says.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="900" height="510" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719.jpg" alt="The bamboo bird feeders that Smita Pasalkar has built attract parrots and other birds" class="wp-image-298961" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719.jpg 900w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719-300x170.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719-500x283.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719-768x435.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/10/bird-lover-6-1-1663851789-1024x580_11zon-1664608719-150x85.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px" /><figcaption>The bamboo bird feeders, Picture credits: Smita Pasalkar</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Make your own bamboo bird feeder like Smita:&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Step 1: Take a piece of bamboo with a diameter of around 8 cm.</p>



<p>Step 2: Cut the bamboo into a piece measuring around 30 cm, and then into two halves. You can either use a saw or knife to do this.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Step 3: Smoothen the frayed edges with sandpaper for a finished look.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Step 4: For the half that will serve as the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/276514/ludhiana-terrace-gardener-instagram-tips-how-to-zucchini/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">top of the bird feeder</a>, drill holes on the extremes, one hole per extreme. For the half that will serve as the bottom, drill two holes at each edge, thus drilling four holes in the bottom feeder.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Step 5: The next step is threading the halves. Loop the rope through the two bottom holes and then after around 10 cm knot it through the top hole of that side. Repeat this on the other side.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Step 6: Now on both sides, you can tie the rope to the roof. Your bamboo feeder is ready!</p>



<p>Read the entire story in Hindi, <a href="https://hindi.thebetterindia.com/urban-gardening/hundreds-of-birds-come-everyday-at-smila-pasalkar-balcony-in-pune/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>‘Snake Man’ of Bihar Fights Superstition to Rescue 3000 Snakes &#038; 152 Animals</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/298187/bihar-snake-man-fights-superstition-to-rescue-snakes-sets-up-animal-centre/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystelle Dsouza]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2022 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animal Welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Changemakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal rescues]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rescue centre bihar]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rescuing snakes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rural india superstitions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife rescue]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=298187</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[People in many parts of rural India continue to believe that death due to a snakebite is because the Gods are not pleased. Hariom Chaubey, the Snake Man of Bihar is trying to fight such superstitious beliefs.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>“Growing up in Dalsagar village of Bihar, I would notice that as monsoons approached, there would be several snakes around our mud homes. But as soon as the villagers would spot the reptiles, they would kill them,” says Hariom Chaubey, an 18-year-old.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As he would later learn, every year 300 people in Buxar, Bihar, alone die as early intervention is not done following a snake bite. Hariom spent his youth helping the people of Bihar by performing snake rescues, and eventually even went on to <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/297672/kashmir-couple-start-animal-rescue-shelters-for-wounded-animals/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">set up an animal rescue centre</a> that tended to domestic animals.&nbsp;</p>



<p>This is his story.&nbsp;</p>



<p>On observing the harsh treatment met out to the reptiles by the villagers, Hariom decided to save the reptile the next time it was at the mercy of someone.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="640" height="1259" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0001_11zon-1664003845.jpg" alt="Hariom Chaubey with the owls he rescued as part of his animal rescue centre" class="wp-image-298198" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0001_11zon-1664003845.jpg 640w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0001_11zon-1664003845-153x300.jpg 153w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0001_11zon-1664003845-500x984.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0001_11zon-1664003845-150x295.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption>Hariom Chaubey, Picture credits: Hariom Chaubey</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“The first time I rescued a snake was when I was 12,” he says, adding that he let it free in a <em>talaab</em> (lake) in the village, and would go see it every day. However, when Hariom’s family got wind of this, they were upset and discouraged the young boy from associating himself with snakes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Then one birthday, Hariom had a visit from an uncle who lived in South India. On learning about the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/296016/inspiring-grandma-feeds-street-dogs-in-ghaziabad-despite-osteoporisis-surgeries/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">young boy’s passion for snakes</a>, he gifted him a book titled ‘Snakes of India’.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“This was the best gift,” recounts Hariom, saying that he ardently read and studied the book for four years. Through the descriptions and pictures, he learnt about reptiles, first aid for a bite, which snakes are venomous and how a snake could be rescued.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Contrary to his family’s opinion about the reptiles, Hariom believed they were harmless. He was certain that one needed to know how to handle them, and once again began his rescues.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-snake-rescues-soon-turned-into-his-side-hustle">Snake rescues soon turned into his side hustle.&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="826" height="1600" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127.jpg" alt="Hariom Chaubey with a cobra in Bux Bihar where he performs snake and animal rescues" class="wp-image-298236" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127.jpg 826w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127-155x300.jpg 155w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127-500x969.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127-768x1488.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127-793x1536.jpg 793w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0029-1664007127-150x291.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 826px) 100vw, 826px" /><figcaption>Hariom Chaubey is fearless as he rescues snakes, Picture credits: Hariom Chaubey</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“People had come to know about my fascination for rescuing snakes and in 2019, when I got my first phone, I began <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/293104/chennai-real-life-hero-antony-rubin-rescues-animals-lion-chimpanzee-in-tamil-nadu/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">getting calls from the villagers</a> asking me to come to help them get rid of the snakes that would be near their homes.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Recalling a frightening incident, Hariom says it was the time he rescued 35 cobras all from a single house. “It had started as one, and then that one had given birth to the many others. It was an infestation,” he recounts.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, he adds that despite his good work, society never understood him and always looked at him as a snake charmer. They even went on to tell his parents that he was performing an ‘unholy’ act.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In 2020, the blind beliefs of the villagers were only strengthened when a man in the village succumbed to a snake bite and died.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="960" height="1280" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901.jpg" alt="The animal rescue centre built with bamboo sticks by Hariom Chaubey in Bihar" class="wp-image-298200" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901.jpg 960w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901-225x300.jpg 225w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901-500x667.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901-640x853.jpg 640w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0017_11zon-1664003901-150x200.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" /><figcaption>The animal rescue centre, Picture credits: Hariom Chaubey</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“The villagers believed that the Gods hadn’t heard their prayers and were convinced that the man must have been punished for something,” says Hariom. In an attempt to <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/291236/gangaram-crocodile-village-charotar-gujarat-shetpal-snakes-human-coexistence/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">stop the fear-mongering</a> and explain to people the logic behind death due to snake bites, Hariom began going to every home, spreading these messages among the community. He would tell people the importance of keeping the home clean, swabbing it, etc. and thus educate them well.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Then in April 2021, he got a call that changed his life.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Setting up a rescue centre</h2>



<p>“The call was from Discovery Channel,” says Hariom. “They were shooting a segment in Siliguri and it involved snakes and someone had told them about my work.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the time he spent at Siliguri, he <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/289461/delhi-university-students-open-community-kitchen-to-feed-stray-dogs-pawriwar/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">discovered a rescue centre</a> that would save animals that were hurt and injured and release them back into the wild. Hariom loved this concept and wrote a plea to the Government on his return to Bihar to give him a piece of land to do the same.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, since they declined, he leased out a space measuring 10 <em>kathas</em> (6000 sq ft) in Churamanpur and to build the rescue centre, he started charging for snake rescues. Some people were frequent callers for the rescues and he would take Rs 100 a month from them.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Hariom’s rescue centre was ready on 25 December 2021. He says he was getting around 25 calls every day for rescues of dogs, cats, monkeys, snakes and cows.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1280" height="960" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994.jpg" alt="The owls rescued by Hariom Chaubey" class="wp-image-298202" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994.jpg 1280w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994-300x225.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994-500x375.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994-768x576.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0002_11zon-1664003994-150x113.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /><figcaption>The owls rescued by Hariom Chaubey, Picture credits: Hariom Chaubey</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Recounting <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/12062/meet-snake-man-of-india-vava-suresh-thiruvananthapuram/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">some rescues that he holds close to his heart</a>, he says one was of a goat that had three legs. “When I received a call informing me of this, I had a lorry arranged and brought the animal to me. It stayed with us at the rescue centre for a month and then we sent it back.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another was of an owlet.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Someone had shot the owl and the young ones had fallen near the tree,” says Hariom adding that for three months they fed the owls and then released them. But the birds would always come back to the nest that had been set up at the rescue centre.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The medicines of the animals at the centre were being ordered from Siliguri and villagers often donated too.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, in February, someone set the rescue centre ablaze. Hariom lost everything.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Rebuilding his hopes&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Thankfully, he says, <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/5163/the-jackals-of-kala-dungar-where-a-community-has-kept-them-alive/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">no animals were hurt</a> in the process. In the last 10 days preceding the fire, they had let the animals free since they had recovered.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Disheartened by the fire, Haiom says that after this incident he stopped taking donations from people. He was determined to rebuild the rescue centre, but this time at his own expense.&nbsp;</p>



<p>He began charging Rs 1,000 for every snake he rescued, and in seven months he had collected Rs 70,000. Just as he was relieved that now he could rebuild the shelter, he suffered a snakebite from a venomous cobra two months ago.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I am under treatment for the bite but I continue to get <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/5163/the-jackals-of-kala-dungar-where-a-community-has-kept-them-alive/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">calls for animal rescues</a>. Now I request the caller to send the animal to me. I have a doctor friend who then advises treatment and another friend Rahul who helps. Once the animal is treated, we leave them back from where they came,” he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>To date, Hariom has rescued 152 animals, including dogs, cats, goats and 3,000 snakes.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="960" height="1280" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054.jpg" alt="Hariom Chaubey has been rescuing snakes since he was a child" class="wp-image-298204" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054.jpg 960w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054-225x300.jpg 225w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054-500x667.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054-640x853.jpg 640w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220924-WA0026_11zon-1664004054-150x200.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" /><figcaption>Hariom Chaubey has been rescuing snakes since he was a child, Picture credits: Hariom Chaubey</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“People in my village are very responsible,” he says, adding that everyone is concerned about the welfare of the animals. The doctor and Rahul visit the village cowsheds every Sunday to assess the cows and their health.&nbsp;</p>



<p>They do this for free.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Hariom says once he recovers from the snake bite, he wishes to get back to rescues and thus collect funds for rebuilding the centre.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I will show people that I am passionate about what I do, and will continue doing it.”</p>



<p><em>Edited by Yoshita Rao</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Kashmiri Couple Rescue 1000+ Wounded Animals, Use Savings to Build Them a Haven</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/297672/kashmir-couple-start-animal-rescue-shelters-for-wounded-animals/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystelle Dsouza]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 14:09:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animal Welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kashmir]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=297672</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Dawood Mohammad and his wife, Mariya Mushtaq, started the Animal Rescue Kashmir, a venture that shelters wounded animals.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It is another Monday in Srinagar, Kashmir, and for Dawood Mohammad and his wife Mariya Mushtaq, it means yet another day of calls from people who have spotted an injured animal.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Being one of the only few rescue centres in the valley, Dawood says that the work at Animal Rescue Kashmir is never-ending but he wouldn’t have it any other way.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It all started in 2017 when he returned to Srinagar from London, where he was working and studying and noticed the prevalence of <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/297656/ias-officer-dr-m-k-ranjitsinh-behind-cheetah-relocation-project-india-kuno-national-park/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">instances of animal cruelty</a> in the valley. This animal lover would often rescue dogs in the neighbourhood that were hurt by helping them get medical aid or even distributing food. </p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1040" height="780" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125.jpg" alt="Stray dogs at the rescue centre" class="wp-image-297673" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125.jpg 1040w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125-300x225.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125-500x375.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125-768x576.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0003-1663588125-150x113.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1040px) 100vw, 1040px" /><figcaption>Stray dogs at the rescue centre, Picture credits: Dawood Mohammad</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>With time, his area of focus expanded. Today, not just people in the vicinity but also those across the valley reach out to Dawood when they spot an animal that needs help.&nbsp;</p>



<p>And he always obliges.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Mariya and Dawood run Animal Rescue Kashmir, a venture that was started in 2018, that aims to alleviate the sorry plight of animals in the Kashmir Valley.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-a-need-to-help-wounded-animals">A need to help wounded animals</h2>



<p>Thinking back to the time he <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/296016/inspiring-grandma-feeds-street-dogs-in-ghaziabad-despite-osteoporisis-surgeries/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first began helping animals</a>, Dawood says he observed that the population of stray dogs was the highest.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1080" height="1080" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297.jpg" alt="Dawood Mohammad with a dog that he rescued" class="wp-image-297675" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297.jpg 1080w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297-300x300.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297-500x500.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297-150x150.jpg 150w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297-768x768.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/animal-rescue-1663588297-96x96.jpg 96w" sizes="(max-width: 1080px) 100vw, 1080px" /><figcaption>Dawood Mohammad with a dog that he rescued, Picture credits: Dawood Mohammad</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“I often noticed that these dogs were infected with mange. It was a common sight, albeit pitiful,” says Dawood, adding that he noticed this on almost every street. Not having much of a medical background himself, he decided to consult a veterinarian and read up about this condition on the internet.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Based on the advice of the vet, I would give these stray dogs the medicines that would help their discomfort,” he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Recounting the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/289461/delhi-university-students-open-community-kitchen-to-feed-stray-dogs-pawriwar/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">first-ever rescue he did</a>, he says it was of a paralysed pup near his home. “The pup’s hind leg wasn’t okay and on closer observation, I discovered that its body was inflicted by multiple wounds and these had maggots in them.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dawood immediately rushed the pup to the vet and following the visit, kept the animal with him for a year and a half.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1200" height="1600" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348.jpg" alt="At the rescue centre, animals are given  space to stay" class="wp-image-297676" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-225x300.jpg 225w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-500x667.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-1152x1536.jpg 1152w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-640x853.jpg 640w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0004-1663588348-150x200.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>At the rescue centre, animals are given  space to stay, Picture credits: Dawood Mohammad</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“This incident changed me,” he says. “I couldn’t stop myself from helping animals.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dawood and Mariya were fuelled by a common zeal and decided to start a venture that would help them perform rescues in a planned manner, and also <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286906/dog-home-foundation-stray-animals-shelter-jodhpur-donation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bring the animals to a centre</a> where they could be kept until they felt better.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-the-joy-of-doing-rescue-work-is-unparalleled">‘The joy of doing rescue work is unparalleled.’&nbsp;</h2>



<p>The duo went on to help many such voiceless creatures, sometimes with medical aid and other times by simply taking good care of them at the rescue centre. The space was given to them by the local municipal corporation and is about 200 sq ft.</p>



<p>Among the many cases they have seen, Dawood says there are two he holds very close to his heart. One is of a young mare.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Her leg was <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286697/bengaluru-entepreneur-rescues-abanoned-disabled-dogs-with-own-money-animal-shelter-video/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fractured and broken</a>. The owner had tied nylon strings around its hind legs to prevent the mare from running away while she grazed,” says Dawood. He adds that the nylon had cut into the bone of the leg, thus preventing the helpless creature from moving.&nbsp;</p>



<p>When he received a call from a passerby who had seen the animal, Dawood knew he had to do something to help.</p>



<p>“From our knowledge of animal rescues, we had learnt that tending to a horse’s leg when fractured was no easy task. It would be a miracle even if the animal managed to survive.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>On going to the vet, they were informed that the leg would have to be amputated. Julie, the mare, would live with three legs. As Dawood adds, she lived with them for two years <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/283869/jaipur-veterinarian-free-prosthetic-limbs-to-disabled-animals/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">at the rescue centre</a> where they looked after her well.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another rescue was that of a dog.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>“One rainy day we received a call that a dog was stuck in a pool of water on a nearby ground. When we reached the site, her state was pitiful. Half of the animal’s body was stuck in the water and the dog wasn’t able to make her way out,” says Dawood.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="958" height="1280" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445.jpg" alt="A rescue operation" class="wp-image-297677" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445.jpg 958w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445-225x300.jpg 225w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445-500x668.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445-768x1026.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0005_11zon-1663588445-150x200.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 958px) 100vw, 958px" /><figcaption>A rescue operation, Picture credits: Dawood Mohammad </figcaption></figure></div>


<p>On examination, when he went into the water, Dawood discovered that the dog was unable to move as her hind legs were tied together. She had been thrown into the water by someone.&nbsp;</p>



<p>What they also figured was that she was a lactating mother and thus <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/278819/delhi-brothers-rescue-birds-kite-flying-injuries-wildlife-hospital/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">began to look for her pups</a> around the area. But the rain made it impossible. So, Dawood took the mother to his rescue shelter.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The next day, on going back to the field, they spotted four pups that resembled the mother and picked them up in a box and took them to the shelter.</p>



<p>“As soon as we dropped them in front of their mother, they were so happy,” says Dawood. While the mother passed away after two months after this incident, two of the pups were adopted, while the other two were kept at the rescue centre.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-every-rescue-is-an-achievement">‘Every rescue is an achievement.’&nbsp;</h2>



<p><a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/272456/cat-cafe-studio-mumbai-lets-you-adopt-stray-animals/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Helping a voiceless creature</a> always comes with a sense of satisfaction, says Dawood. He adds that what he and his team are doing is vital as there are not many rescue operations in the valley.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“We are the most active and the face we have is not our own, but of the animals.”</p>



<p>In his rescue work, Dawood is joined by his wife Mariya. She says in her experience “it has been transformational to be able to help animals in need”. She adds that being able to save a soul which can do nothing for you in return has been an awakening experience.&nbsp;</p>



<p>She says, “We are often asked – why not help humans instead? This gives us an idea of how important it is to let people know about the sufferings and plight of animals.” She adds that with the rise of incidents involving<a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/251019/wildlife-rescue-kashmir-woman-teacher-leopard-bear-aaliya-mir-math-teacher-animal-human-conflict-yos191/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"> man-animal conflicts daily</a>,&nbsp; she believes if they can make changes in people’s behaviour towards animals, many problems can be solved.</p>



<p>Along with Mariya, there are three other people in Dawood’s team.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The way the rescue operations work is simple. The team’s numbers are on social media and people in the valley are aware of them.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="664" height="640" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0012-1663588492.jpg" alt="Animal Rescue Kashmir" class="wp-image-297678" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0012-1663588492.jpg 664w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0012-1663588492-300x289.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0012-1663588492-500x482.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/IMG-20220919-WA0012-1663588492-150x145.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 664px) 100vw, 664px" /><figcaption>Animal Rescue Kashmir, Picture credits: Dawood Mohammad</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“People contact us through call or WhatsApp and since we may not always be able to go on-site, we ask them for pictures and videos. This helps us get an idea of the severity of cases,” says Dawood.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Once he receives the details and can assess the state of the animal, he gets his staff together and they plan on how to go about it. He says, “We don&#8217;t have transport of our own, and so we contact load carriers and auto drivers and ask them to come to the shelter and load the equipment such as the cages, medical equipment, bandages, iodine, etc. or in the case of larger animals, ropes, grass to lure animal, etc. We then go to the site and <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/268812/chennai-birdman-joseph-sekar-own-savings-feed-birds-rescue-video/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take the animal to the vet</a> or the shelter.”</p>



<p>At the shelter, dogs are given food twice a day. The meal includes rice mixed with pulses and soybean, and sometimes even non-vegetarian food. Horses and cows are given hay and dry grass fodder.&nbsp;</p>



<p>He adds that the biggest challenge they face is a lack of ambulances and space. The space too is small and overcrowded, increasing the chances of cross infection.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Additionally, adoptions are a concern. “Though we put up posts on social media, so people can come and adopt, there are <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/267123/unsung-hero-domestic-help-mangaluru-rajani-shetty-rescue-stray-dogs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">many social stigmas</a> here as keeping dogs is not a done thing in a Muslim majority community.”</p>



<p>To date, the shelter has helped 1,200 animals, says Dawood adding that they receive 8 to 10 calls a day and can do around three to four rescues.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Currently, we are trying to raise funds to get ambulances so we can reach the destinations on time and even at odd times when transport may not be available,” says Dawood, who finances the venture through the earnings of the clothing store that he runs. “The yearly expenses amount to Rs 20 lakh and thus funds are of utmost importance.”&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you wish to be a part of Dawood’s endeavour to save and rescue animals, you can donate <a href="https://milaap.org/fundraisers/support-dawood-3?deeplink_type=paytm" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">here</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>Edited by Yoshita Rao</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Ex-IAS Officer Who Helped Bring Cheetahs to India For The First Time in 70 Years</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/297656/ias-officer-dr-m-k-ranjitsinh-behind-cheetah-relocation-project-india-kuno-national-park/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sowmya Mani]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 10:16:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Civil Servants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cheetah]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[cheetah relocation]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kuno national park]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[mk ranjitsinh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[namibia]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[project cheetah]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=297656</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Seventy years after the Asiatic Cheetah was declared extinct in India, eight cheetahs were flown in from Namibia to the Kuno National Park in Madhya Pradesh. Meet former IAS officer Dr M K Ranjitsinh, the brains behind the relocation project.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Seven decades after the Asiatic Cheetah was declared extinct in India, <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/241434/forogotten-hero-india-south-africa-es-reddy-apartheid-united-nations-andhra-pradesh-freedom-struggle-india-nor41/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">eight cheetahs were flown in from Namibia</a>, marking a much-awaited return for the big cat.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>On Saturday, Prime Minister Narendra Modi celebrated his birthday with the majestic predators, releasing eight cubs of the African species at the Kuno National Park in Madhya Pradesh.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-twitter wp-block-embed-twitter"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">An unforgettable day in Madhya Pradesh! <a href="https://t.co/ius7WxTlDN">pic.twitter.com/ius7WxTlDN</a></p>&mdash; Narendra Modi (@narendramodi) <a href="https://twitter.com/narendramodi/status/1571161121532547072?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 17, 2022</a></blockquote><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</div></figure>



<p>Another person who was perhaps even happier than the Prime Minister on Saturday was 83-year-old Dr M K Ranjitsinh.&nbsp;</p>



<p>A former IAS officer of the 1961 batch of Madhya Pradesh cadre and among the masterminds of the Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972, Ranjitsinh dreamt of bringing back cheetahs to the country even as a young boy. </p>



<p>“&#8230;I had heard that the last cheetah had been shot and this must have been in either 1948 or 1949. I was an avid reader of wildlife literature and I thought why can’t we bring the cheetah back from somewhere. It was a dream and it’s now come true. I always say the most difficult thing to kill is a good idea,” Ranjitsinh, who belongs to the royal family of Wankaner, Gujarat, told <em>The Indian Express</em>.</p>



<p>While drafting the Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972, the former director of Wildlife Preservation had included the cheetah as a protected species, even though it was extinct.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2>The history of the cheetah in India&nbsp;</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img width="1200" height="628" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783.jpg" alt="Asiatic cheetah cubs in Dharwad" class="wp-image-297660" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783-300x157.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783-500x262.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783-768x402.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T151611.173-1663580783-150x79.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>Asiatic cheetah cubs along with a dog in Dharwad in 1897. Image: Major G S Rodon at Dharwar, 17th August 1897, published in Journal of the Bombay Natural History, Vol XI.</figcaption></figure>



<p>While there was a time when the cheetah had a robust population across different corners of India, reports suggest that Maharaja Ramanuj Pratap Singh Deo of Koriya shot the last three surviving big cats in 1947. Over-hunting, loss of prey, and habitat loss led to the cheetah’s extinction, which the Government of India officially declared in 1952.&nbsp;</p>



<p>India’s first attempt to bring back the carnivore was in the early 70s. It was Ranjitsingh who spoke to Iran even then, but the negotiations stalled after the declaration of Emergency in ‘75 and the deposition of the Shah of Iran in 1979.</p>



<p>Since then, Ranjitsinh and wildlife conservationist Divyabhanusinh Chavda have worked on the guidelines and policy to reintroduce cheetahs.</p>



<p>The ‘African Cheetah Introduction Project in India’ was born in 2009, but it was only in 2020 that the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/248312/supreme-court-of-india-first-sitting-sc-chief-justice-hj-kania-fundamental-right-law-nor41/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Supreme Court gave its final approval.</a> The SC appointed Ranjitsinh to chair an expert committee set up for the relocation.</p>



<h2>Why Kuno was chosen</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1200" height="628" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006.jpg" alt="A cheetah in Kuno on Saturday" class="wp-image-297661" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006-300x157.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006-500x262.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006-768x402.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Untitled-design-2022-09-19T150314.692-min-1663581006-150x79.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>A cheetah in Kuno National park on Saturday. Image: Twitter</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Ranjitsinh told <em>Village Square</em>, “In 1981, I went to Kuno and I was struck by the similarity of the habitat. The ruler of Gwalior had selected it as a very suitable area for lions and cheetahs in the 1920s. I declared Kuno as a sanctuary in 1981.” </p>



<p>He added, “When I became the director of Wildlife Institute of India in 1985, I tried again to reintroduce the cheetah, but the numbers had fallen and there was no focus on conservation in Iran.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Addressing concerns of cheetahs being grassland animals and problems of rehabilitation, the former IAS officer told Village Square that bringing in such predators helps in habitat protection.</p>



<p>“We have learned, not only from the cheetah project, but also from the tiger and snow leopard projects, that bringing in an apex predator has a large cascading effect. It leads to better protection of the habitat — this is most important. Bringing back cheetahs has led to building and protection of the habitat not only for cheetahs but also the prey species. Kuno National Park has seen a spectacular recovery due to the reintroduction of cheetahs,” said Ranjitsinh.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>What would this relocation look like?&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="737" height="820" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Fcqzk1xaAAA9Mmr-1663581063.jpg" alt="The flight which brought the cheetahs" class="wp-image-297662" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Fcqzk1xaAAA9Mmr-1663581063.jpg 737w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Fcqzk1xaAAA9Mmr-1663581063-270x300.jpg 270w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Fcqzk1xaAAA9Mmr-1663581063-500x556.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/09/Fcqzk1xaAAA9Mmr-1663581063-150x167.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 737px) 100vw, 737px" /><figcaption>The flight that flew the cheetahs from Namibia</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>This is the first time in world history that a cheetah, or any large carnivore, is being relocated from a different continent. As per a statement issued by the Prime Minister’s Office (PMO), Project Cheetah is the “world’s first inter-continental large wild carnivore translocation project”. </p>



<p>Some experts and members of wildlife groups say this project will help increase the number of Asiatic cheetahs, which today only survive in a small population in Iran, wrote <em>The National Geographic</em>.   </p>



<p>However, several have also raised several concerns, calling this a ‘vanity project’, premature, and risky. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-twitter wp-block-embed-twitter"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">When <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Cheetah?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Cheetah</a> are coming back to <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/India?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#India</a>. A look at how the last of the lots were hunted, maimed and domesticated for hunting parties. Video made in 1939. 1/n <a href="https://t.co/obUbuZoNv5">pic.twitter.com/obUbuZoNv5</a></p>&mdash; Parveen Kaswan, IFS (@ParveenKaswan) <a href="https://twitter.com/ParveenKaswan/status/1570828855837085696?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 16, 2022</a></blockquote><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</div></figure>



<p>Since Kuno has a leopard population, there is fear that the cheetahs may be attacked by them. There is also a fear that the cheetahs may stray outside and get killed either by animals or humans.</p>



<p>“It’s putting the cart before the horse. I’m not against the project, I’m against this very tunnel vision thing of just bringing cheetahs and dumping them in the middle of India where there are 360 people per square kilometer,” said Ullas Karanth, emeritus director for the nonprofit Center for Wildlife Studies and a specialist in large carnivores to National Geographic.</p>



<p>Another independent conservation scientist Arjun Gopalaswamy argued that there is no chance for a free-ranging cheetah population now.</p>



<p>“Cheetahs in India perished for a reason, which is human pressure. This has only gotten worse in the 70 years since the species disappeared. So the first question is, why is this attempt even being made?” questioned Gopalaswamy in the <em>National Geographic </em>report. </p>



<p>Meanwhile, Ranjitsingh told <em>Times of India</em>, “I interpret the return of the cheetah as a resolve of both the Indian people and government to let no wildlife species go extinct in the country. If God forbid it does, no effort will be spared to restore it.” </p>



<p>For this former IAS officer, seeing his lifelong dream coming true on Saturday was another feather in his cap.&nbsp;</p>



<p>He earlier won the Lifetime Achievement Award in 2014 for conservation of wildlife. He has also served as former secretary for forests &amp; tourism in <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/247963/bhuri-bai-madhya-pradesh-padma-shri-2021-winner-pithora-paintings-inspiring-india-gop94/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Madhya Pradesh</a>; director of wildlife preservation; chairman of Wildlife Trust of India (WTI); director general of WWF Tiger Conservation Programme (TCP); and is presently the regional adviser in nature conservation (Asia &amp; Pacific) for UNEP.</p>



<p>He has also been responsible for saving the central Indian Barasingha from extinction. Ransitsinh also established fourteen sanctuaries and eight national parks in Madhya Pradesh.</p>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size" id="h-sources">Sources</h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://www.firstindia.co.in/news/lifeStyle/the-cheetah-in-the-forest-a-tribute-to-mk-ranjitsinh" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘The Cheetah in the Forest: A Tribute to MK Ranjitsinh’ </a>by Sanjeev Chopra for First India, Published on 19 September, 2022</em></h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/express-sunday-eye/cheetah-kuno-national-park-india-mk-ranjitsinh-8156050/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘Seeing the cheetah in Kuno National Park is a dream come true: MK Ranjitsinh’ </a>by Devyani Onial for The Indian Express, Published on 18 September, 2022</em></h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://indianexpress.com/article/explained/india-cheetah-relocation-extinction-narendra-modi-explained-8155532/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘How cheetahs went extinct in India, and how they are being brought back’ </a>by Esha Roy for The Indian Express, Published on 18 September, 2022</em></h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/city/bhopal/madhya-pradesh-a-dream-come-true-for-indias-cheetah-man/articleshow/94259360.cms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘Madhya Pradesh: A dream come true for India&#8217;s cheetah man’ </a>by P Naveen for Times of India, Published on 17 September, 2022</em></h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://www.villagesquare.in/an-interview-with-mk-ranjitsinh-on-cheetah-reintroduction-in-india/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘Ambitious plans to reintroduce cheetahs to India’ </a>Published on 22 August, 2022, Courtesy Village Square</em></h5>



<h5 class="has-small-font-size"><em><a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/animals/article/inside-the-controversial-plan-to-reintroduce-cheetahs-to-india" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">‘Inside the controversial plan to reintroduce cheetahs to India’ </a>by Rachel Nuwer for National Geographic, Published on 13 September, 2022</em></h5>



<p><em>Edited by Divya Sethu, Feature Image Courtesy EarToTheWild/Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>90-YO Grandma Doesn’t Let Osteoporosis Stop Her From Cooking For 120 Dogs Daily</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/296016/inspiring-grandma-feeds-street-dogs-in-ghaziabad-despite-osteoporisis-surgeries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sowmya Mani]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2022 14:36:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Dogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Senior Citizens]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[feeding dogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ghaziabad]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[grandma]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[inspiring]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kanak saxena]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[sana saxena]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=296016</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With her granddaughter Sana, 90-year-old Kanak Saxena cooks and feeds 120 dogs every day in Ghaziabad, despite her Osteoporosis, fractures, and major surgeries.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Kanak Saxena’s day begins at 4.30 am.&nbsp;</p>



<p>She wakes up and heads straight to the kitchen — not to cook for her family, but for <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/289461/delhi-university-students-open-community-kitchen-to-feed-stray-dogs-pawriwar/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">120 dogs</a>. The 90-year-old hasn’t let health problems like osteoporosis, fractures, or major operations come in her way.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>She says the happiness and love she receives by feeding these dogs is the secret to her health.&nbsp;</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="472" height="851" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.11.50-PM-1661781588.jpeg" alt="Kanak Saxena with a rescue dog brought home by granddaughter Sana" class="wp-image-296028" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.11.50-PM-1661781588.jpeg 472w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.11.50-PM-1661781588-166x300.jpeg 166w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.11.50-PM-1661781588-150x270.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 472px) 100vw, 472px" /><figcaption>Kanak Saxena with a rescue dog</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>She wasn’t always a dog lover, but when her granddaughter Sana brought their dog Coco home, everything changed.</p>



<p>“I wasn’t attached to dogs earlier. When Sana brought a dog home, I slowly started getting attached to him. My day started revolving around feeding him, playing with him, and just loving him. My attitude towards dogs completely changed. So when Sana started taking care of street dogs, I wanted to help with that. As I can’t physically go and feed them, I feel satisfied by cooking for them,” says Kanak.</p>



<p>Earlier, Sana and her father would go to feed street dogs biscuit and dog food every once in a while. </p>



<h2>However, the advent of the pandemic and the death of a dog changed their life.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img width="1125" height="1156" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911.jpeg" alt="Sana's mother " class="wp-image-296033" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911.jpeg 1125w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911-292x300.jpeg 292w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911-500x514.jpeg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911-768x789.jpeg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.17-AM-1-1661781911-150x154.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1125px) 100vw, 1125px" /><figcaption>Sana&#8217;s mother with a dog</figcaption></figure>



<p>Sana, a 22-year-old pursuing her final year in fashion design, says, “There was a dog called Bholu near our house. We would feed him occasionally. His death affected me a lot. I felt that had I known a bit about how to recognise a sick dog, I would have been able to help him. At the same time, the first lockdown was imposed. My dad and I wondered how these dogs would eat. Since we knew people couldn’t step out, we decided to help the animals.”&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-feeding-120-dogs-daily">Feeding 120 dogs daily</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="853" height="1024" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649.jpeg" alt="Sana with a dog" class="wp-image-296029" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649.jpeg 853w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649-250x300.jpeg 250w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649-500x600.jpeg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649-768x922.jpeg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-29-at-7.01.17-PM-1661781649-150x180.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 853px) 100vw, 853px" /><figcaption>Sana Saxena with a dog</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In March 2020, the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/280578/bengaluru-rescue-abandoned-injured-dog-shelter-contact-trust/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">family began feeding 10-20 dogs </a>on a street in Vaishali, Ghaziabad. Today, the number has grown to 120 dogs every day, alongside taking care of their vaccinations, medications, and shelter.&nbsp;</p>



<p>While the father-daughter duo started with packaged food, Kanak stepped in and said they must have fresh food.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“It’s so funny how my <em>dadi </em>completely changed from a person who wasn’t attached to dogs to one who can’t sleep without seeing their videos on my phone. She is the one who pampers Coco the most too. We were giving some packaged food to the street dogs but <em>dadi </em>and mom wanted to give them fresh food. So they started cooking at home,” adds Sana.&nbsp;</p>



<p>They use almost 10 kg of rice daily, along with chicken. Kanak loves experimenting with food daily.</p>



<p>“Dadi keeps trying new combinations. We get <em>chatan</em>, which is parts of a chicken, from a meat shop in bulk. She makes chicken biryani with it, and on some days, adds bits of soya chunks, or paneer, or vegetables to make it interesting. She also cooks dishes using milk and rice,” says Sana.</p>



<p>This costs them almost Rs 350 per dog per month, which involves a total cost of Rs 42,000 for 120 dogs. They manage by raising funds.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Sana ensures that the dogs are fed 365 days a year, come what may. If she is away, her mother takes care of the feeding. In fact, when Sana lost her father last year due to COVID, they continued to feed the dogs as that is what he would have wanted.</p>



<h2>A day in Kanak’s life</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1125" height="1090" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724.jpeg" alt="Kanak cooking for the dogs" class="wp-image-296031" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724.jpeg 1125w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724-300x291.jpeg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724-500x484.jpeg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724-768x744.jpeg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/WhatsApp-Image-2022-08-28-at-11.06.15-AM-1661781724-150x145.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1125px) 100vw, 1125px" /><figcaption>Kanak Saxena cooking for the dogs</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>While Kanak wakes up at 4.30 am and starts cooking, Sana and her mother wake up by 5 am. They start making individual packets for all the dogs. They also carry extra food in case they meet more strays on the way.</p>



<p>By 6.30 am, Sana, her mother, and two other friends head out. They distribute this food in three sectors in Vaishali and return home by 8.30 am.</p>



<p>“I feel so much love for these dogs. I feel satisfied and happy when they are able to eat a good meal. We are contributing to some good purpose. Otherwise, who will care for these poor animals? Ideally, I would love to go feed them myself, but I manage now by watching their videos,” says Kanak.</p>



<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CfjYFRQJpjj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" data-instgrm-version="14" style="background:#FFF;border:0;border-radius:3px;margin: 1px;max-width:540px;min-width:326px;padding:0;width:99.375%;width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px);width:calc(100% - 2px)"><div style="padding:16px"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CfjYFRQJpjj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style="background:#FFFFFF;line-height:0;padding:0 0;text-align:center;text-decoration:none;width:100%" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> <div style="flex-direction: row;align-items: center"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 50%;flex-grow: 0;height: 40px;margin-right: 14px;width: 40px"></div> <div style="flex-direction: column;flex-grow: 1;justify-content: center"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 4px;flex-grow: 0;height: 14px;margin-bottom: 6px;width: 100px"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 4px;flex-grow: 0;height: 14px;width: 60px"></div></div></div><div style="padding: 19% 0"></div> <div style="height:50px;margin:0 auto 12px;width:50px"></div><div style="padding-top: 8px"> <div style="color:#3897f0;font-family:Arial,sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-style:normal;font-weight:550;line-height:18px">View this post on Instagram</div></div><div style="padding: 12.5% 0"></div> <div style="flex-direction: row;margin-bottom: 14px;align-items: center"><div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 50%;height: 12.5px;width: 12.5px"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;height: 12.5px;width: 12.5px;flex-grow: 0;margin-right: 14px;margin-left: 2px"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 50%;height: 12.5px;width: 12.5px"></div></div><div style="margin-left: 8px"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 50%;flex-grow: 0;height: 20px;width: 20px"></div> <div style="width: 0;height: 0;border-top: 2px solid transparent;border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4;border-bottom: 2px solid transparent"></div></div><div style="margin-left: auto"> <div style="width: 0px;border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4;border-right: 8px solid transparent"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;flex-grow: 0;height: 12px;width: 16px"></div> <div style="width: 0;height: 0;border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4;border-left: 8px solid transparent"></div></div></div> <div style="flex-direction: column;flex-grow: 1;justify-content: center;margin-bottom: 24px"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 4px;flex-grow: 0;height: 14px;margin-bottom: 6px;width: 224px"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4;border-radius: 4px;flex-grow: 0;height: 14px;width: 144px"></div></div></a><p style="color:#c9c8cd;font-family:Arial,sans-serif;font-size:14px;line-height:17px;margin-bottom:0;margin-top:8px;overflow:hidden;padding:8px 0 7px;text-align:center"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CfjYFRQJpjj/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style="color:#c9c8cd;font-family:Arial,sans-serif;font-size:14px;font-style:normal;font-weight:normal;line-height:17px;text-decoration:none" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A post shared by Paws in Puddle🐾 (@pawsinpuddle)</a></p></div></blockquote>



<p>This love for dogs slowly has spread to vaccinations, building temporary shelters, adoptions and rescue operations.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Sana ensures that all dogs in her area are vaccinated.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“We need to vaccinate dogs twice a year. It takes 5-6 days to get every dog vaccinated. I have also learnt to vaccinate them. We built a few temporary shelters for the dogs during the monsoons. We’ve also helped 13 dogs get adopted,” says Sana.</p>



<p>Sana also runs a page called Paws in Puddle on Instagram which she uses to educate people about dogs and encourage adoptions. </p>



<p>The family has learned compassion after they started feeding dogs, Sana feels, adding that if people start feeding even one or two dogs, most of the street dogs would be taken care of.</p>



<p>“I’ve learned so much in the past two years. I learned about medications for dogs and carry a medicine kit with me all the time. If I see a dog in trouble, I always help them. We hope to spread awareness and make people compassionate and sensitive,” says Sana.</p>



<p>This empathy has spread in their house, with Kanak being the one who has changed the most. She waits up every night till Sana comes back, and sees the videos of her feeding the dogs, or hears stories of rescues.</p>



<p>“The best part of my day is sitting with <em>dadi </em>at night and sharing what happened with the dogs. She loves seeing them well-fed and cries when she <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/277550/bejubano-ki-rasoi-jaipur-feeds-dogs-strays-indies-cooked-meals/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">hears of distressed dogs</a>. She urges me to rescue them,” says Sana.&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>Edited by Divya Sethu, Images Courtesy Sana Saxena</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Threats, Bribes No Match For Hero Who Rescues Lions, Chimpanzees From Horrifying Cruelty</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/293104/chennai-real-life-hero-antony-rubin-rescues-animals-lion-chimpanzee-in-tamil-nadu/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystelle Dsouza]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 13:40:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animal Welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chennai]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=293104</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[From lions and tigers to chimpanzees and elephants, Chennai-based Antony Rubin has led many important animal rescue missions across Tamil Nadu. He shares why he began this work, and how he keeps going.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Antony Rubin, though the founder of a web development company by profession, is a passionate animal rescuer at heart.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The 37-year-old, who hails from Chennai, has <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/289461/delhi-university-students-open-community-kitchen-to-feed-stray-dogs-pawriwar/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">worked towards animal welfare</a> since 2000. He also holds a postgraduate diploma in the subject.&nbsp;</p>



<p>He says that from around the time he was 17, he would take pity on seeing overloaded bullock carts. He and his friends would offload the heavy material and remove the whips attached to the animals.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>“From a young age, I couldn’t stand to see animals in pain. Rescue work brought me satisfaction,” he says.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-the-incident-that-got-antony-interested-in-animal-rescue">The incident that got Antony interested in animal rescue:</h2>



<p>Young Antony was always on the lookout for <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286906/dog-home-foundation-stray-animals-shelter-jodhpur-donation/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">creatures in pain</a> and in need of rescue. So when he spotted a horse in a pathetic state while on a beach one day, he acted immediately.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="720" height="960" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544.jpg" alt="Antony Rubin" class="wp-image-293114" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544.jpg 720w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544-225x300.jpg 225w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544-500x667.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544-640x853.jpg 640w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0002-1659613544-150x200.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" /><figcaption>Antony Rubin</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“The horse had been used for joy rides on the beach, and the constant walking had left it in a deplorable condition, with its legs swollen. We arranged for an ambulance to take it to a veterinary hospital,” he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But unfortunately, the horse dropped dead before it could get to the hospital. This tragic incident left a mark on Antony, who decided to take up animal rescue work in his free time on a much larger scale.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Since then, he has been into <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286697/bengaluru-entepreneur-rescues-abanoned-disabled-dogs-with-own-money-animal-shelter-video/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">rescue work for dogs</a>, horses, chimpanzees and even lions, among other animals.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-the-chimpanzee-affair">The chimpanzee affair</h2>



<p>“I’ll let you in on the chimpanzee rescue operation,” says Antony, explaining that it all began when he got to know from his sources about a well-known circus in Tamil Nadu, where four chimpanzees were performing.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Among them was Lakshmi, who had been riding a bicycle on a thin rope to entertain the crowds, and was left injured during the act. “When we saw her, she was paralysed, had bed sores, and couldn’t move,” says Antony, adding that her small cage restricted her movements and made matters worse.&nbsp;</p>



<p>With his team, he filed a complaint with the police and arranged a setup to rescue the chimps and <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/275486/unique-bird-hospital-in-bengaluru-treats-pigeons-for-free-dunzo-uber/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take them to safety</a>. However, it wasn’t as simple as it sounds.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Owing to the size of the chimps, only two could be taken in the caravan at a time. Lakshmi’s mother and cousin were taken on the first trip. “We’d planned to return and take Guru (her son) on the second trip, but he was aggressive. He did not feel safe without his family present. So we had to bring the other two chimps back to the circus, and take the three back to the rescue centre together.”</p>



<p>He recounts, “The entire operation took 72 hours and was overseen by 300 police.”</p>



<p>As for Lakshmi, she was taken in an ambulance to a nearby rescue centre, where her injuries were tended to.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For Antony, it is the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/274041/nat-geo-india-series-on-benhail-antao-louise-remedios-goa/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">happiness of the animal on being rescued</a> that makes all the difference.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Months later, on Lakshmi’s birthday, I went to the rescue centre to see how she was doing. The chain on her neck was still there as it was feared she would get aggressive once it was removed and she was free.”</p>



<p>With the permission of the guards there, Antony began to remove the chain, as ‘Happy Birthday’ was being sung for the chimp. He says, “I knew either of two things could happen — Lakshmi would either get violent after so many years of being held captive, or she would be immensely happy at the freedom.”</p>



<p>What came next melted Antony’s heart — Lakshmi smiled brightly and kept a hand on Antony.&nbsp;</p>



<p>But as heartwarming as these moments may be, he also comes across many terrifying incidents.</p>



<h2 id="h-the-poacher-who-was-selling-a-panther">The poacher who was selling a panther&nbsp;</h2>



<p>“Sometimes, I get to know about an animal that needs rescuing, but when I dive deep into the case, the scene gets murkier and it leads to something I don’t expect,” he says.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One such incident was when, on his rounds in Chennai, he spotted a Malabar squirrel.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“I knew for a fact that this was not a likely habitat where one would see a giant squirrel, and started tracking down where it had come from. I landed on a house near a prominent university in Chennai.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Things got more suspicious when the homeowners — when questioned — said they purchased the giant squirrel from a man who apparently had a menu card of <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/75818/save-india-owl-poaching-blind-belief-superstition-ritual/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">animals that had been poached</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Pretending to be a buyer, Antony managed to track him down and was offered a panther for Rs 22,000.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In an attempt to put an end to his game, Antony played along and set up bait with the police involved. The story ended with the poacher being put behind bars.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The instances of animal cruelty are many, as Antony says.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="aligncenter size-full"><img width="1280" height="720" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738.jpg" alt="Antony Rubin rescues elephants, lions, chimpanzees among other animals" class="wp-image-293116" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738.jpg 1280w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738-300x169.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738-500x281.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738-768x432.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/08/IMG-20220802-WA0001_11zon-1659613738-150x84.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /><figcaption>Antony Rubin rescues elephants, lions, chimpanzees among other animals</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2 id="h-the-pride-of-lions">The pride of lions&nbsp;</h2>



<p>Antony was well aware that the Government of India has banned the use of lions in circuses. So when he got to know about a certain place that was hiding lions for a circus, and keeping them in rusted cages with little to no maintenance, he was bent on getting to the bottom of the story.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“<a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/265515/gurusamy-tamil-nadu-farmer-ancestral-land-deer-population-conservation-inspiring/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">My investigation</a> led me to a district in Tamil Nadu, where I traced the laundry shop near which there were a couple of cages,” he says, adding that it was an area with plenty of local shops nearby, all without a clue that just metres from them, there were these four ferocious wild beasts.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“When I saw the way the lions were kept, I was fearful about how long it was until they broke free,” he adds, recalling how there was no one to feed the beasts and they were given only <em>daal</em> and rice.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In an attempt to put an end to this, Antony then went to the cops, but they refused to do anything, claiming it was a court matter and they couldn’t get involved.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“But I knew my plea would be heard by the media.”&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>So, Antony took photos of the cages and returned to Chennai, where he shared them with the media and spoke about why the situation was dangerous.</p>



<p>The next day, citizens and politicians of Tamil Nadu woke up to the horrific news of the lions being in such close proximity to residential spaces, and it was ordered that the <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/237460/west-bengal-woman-activist-wildlife-protection-act-1972-hunting-antipoaching-ngo-heal-india-ana79/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">lions be immediately transferred</a> to the rescue centre.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“When I went to the centre later to see the animals, the lion wanted to nuzzle against me through the mesh,” he recounts. “It was behaving like a small cat.”&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>But doesn’t he ever feel scared?&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>“When you are doing good, there is a kind of protection around you,” says Antony. “Even in the scariest of circumstances, I feel there is a force that surrounds me.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>He recounts how people have threatened him, as he often rescues cattle from being illegally slaughtered. But at the end of the day, Antony feels he is doing his bit to <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/189666/chennai-woman-rescues-animals-shelter-abuse-euthanasia-inspiring-india/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">help voiceless animals</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>While he doesn’t keep a count of the number of animals he rescues, he says there have been 85 horses and 18 lions among these.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Along with field rescues, Antony has also started getting involved in policy frameworks for the animals. “I advocate for acts to be introduced for animal safety, laws against cruelty. I also file animal abuse cases.”</p>



<p>In May 2022, Antony was made a member of the State Wildlife Board of the Government of Tamil Nadu.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“What we have to understand is we share the same planet,” he says, explaining why he is so passionate about <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/176635/mumbaikar-rescues-protects-wild-animals-in-mumbai/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">animals and their rights</a>. “Animals never want to harm us, but with us taking over their land, they are forced to survive in whatever way they can. We need to step up for change.”&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>15 States, 12000 Km: An Epic Bike Journey From Kerala to Ladakh With My Rescue Pup</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/292238/kochi-man-travels-with-pet-dog-from-kerala-to-ladakh-bike-trip-travel/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anjali Krishnan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2022 04:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Dogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Travel]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bike ride with pet dog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kerala to Ladakh trip]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Kochi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ladakh bike trip]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Travelling with dogs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Travelling with pets]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=292238</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Sudheesh KT and his rescue dog Snowbell went on an epic bike journey from Kerala to Ladakh, covering over 12,000 km and creating unforgettable memories.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>&#8220;I&#8217;ve always been fond of travelling. So, it was nothing short of a <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/178733/driver-son-selected-into-iim-ahmedabad-dream-come-true/">dream come true</a> for me when I travelled across the country to reach one of my favourite destinations,” exclaims Kochi resident Sudheesh K T, who recently fulfilled his lifelong wish of taking a road trip to Ladakh on his 100 cc bike.</p>



<p></p>



<p>But the journey was special for a very different reason and it was because he had the best travel companion — Snowbell, his three-year-old pet dog. “Travelling with Snowbell was one of the best decisions I took,” says the 28-year-old, who rescued him from the street almost three years ago.</p>



<p>“There have been several incidents of <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/277040/peepal-farm-spiti-valley-feeding-stray-dogs-man-animal-conflict-heroes/">people mistreating dogs</a> and abandoning them, that I came to notice in recent times. Therefore this journey was also an effort to send out a message to society that these poor creatures are no lesser than human beings and must be treated equally. Besides, people consider Indie dogs as inferior to foreign breeds and I wanted to prove them wrong,” Sudheesh tells <strong>The Better India.</strong></p>



<p>Starting on May 8, he says that they both enjoyed every bit of their trip, crossing over 15 states across the country, covering over 12,000 km, and returning after two months on July 15.</p>



<blockquote class="instagram-media" data-instgrm-captioned="" data-instgrm-permalink="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CgJedNGBCXS/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" data-instgrm-version="14" style=" background:#FFF; border:0; border-radius:3px; box-shadow:0 0 1px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.5),0 1px 10px 0 rgba(0,0,0,0.15); margin: 1px; max-width:540px; min-width:326px; padding:0; width:99.375%; width:-webkit-calc(100% - 2px); width:calc(100% - 2px);"><div style="padding:16px;"> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CgJedNGBCXS/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" background:#FFFFFF; line-height:0; padding:0 0; text-align:center; text-decoration:none; width:100%;" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> <div style=" display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;"> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 40px; margin-right: 14px; width: 40px;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 100px;"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 60px;"></div></div></div><div style="padding: 19% 0;"></div> <div style="display:block; height:50px; margin:0 auto 12px; width:50px;"><svg width="50px" height="50px" viewBox="0 0 60 60" version="1.1" xmlns="https://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:xlink="https://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><g stroke="none" stroke-width="1" fill="none" fill-rule="evenodd"><g transform="translate(-511.000000, -20.000000)" fill="#000000"><g><path d="M556.869,30.41 C554.814,30.41 553.148,32.076 553.148,34.131 C553.148,36.186 554.814,37.852 556.869,37.852 C558.924,37.852 560.59,36.186 560.59,34.131 C560.59,32.076 558.924,30.41 556.869,30.41 M541,60.657 C535.114,60.657 530.342,55.887 530.342,50 C530.342,44.114 535.114,39.342 541,39.342 C546.887,39.342 551.658,44.114 551.658,50 C551.658,55.887 546.887,60.657 541,60.657 M541,33.886 C532.1,33.886 524.886,41.1 524.886,50 C524.886,58.899 532.1,66.113 541,66.113 C549.9,66.113 557.115,58.899 557.115,50 C557.115,41.1 549.9,33.886 541,33.886 M565.378,62.101 C565.244,65.022 564.756,66.606 564.346,67.663 C563.803,69.06 563.154,70.057 562.106,71.106 C561.058,72.155 560.06,72.803 558.662,73.347 C557.607,73.757 556.021,74.244 553.102,74.378 C549.944,74.521 548.997,74.552 541,74.552 C533.003,74.552 532.056,74.521 528.898,74.378 C525.979,74.244 524.393,73.757 523.338,73.347 C521.94,72.803 520.942,72.155 519.894,71.106 C518.846,70.057 518.197,69.06 517.654,67.663 C517.244,66.606 516.755,65.022 516.623,62.101 C516.479,58.943 516.448,57.996 516.448,50 C516.448,42.003 516.479,41.056 516.623,37.899 C516.755,34.978 517.244,33.391 517.654,32.338 C518.197,30.938 518.846,29.942 519.894,28.894 C520.942,27.846 521.94,27.196 523.338,26.654 C524.393,26.244 525.979,25.756 528.898,25.623 C532.057,25.479 533.004,25.448 541,25.448 C548.997,25.448 549.943,25.479 553.102,25.623 C556.021,25.756 557.607,26.244 558.662,26.654 C560.06,27.196 561.058,27.846 562.106,28.894 C563.154,29.942 563.803,30.938 564.346,32.338 C564.756,33.391 565.244,34.978 565.378,37.899 C565.522,41.056 565.552,42.003 565.552,50 C565.552,57.996 565.522,58.943 565.378,62.101 M570.82,37.631 C570.674,34.438 570.167,32.258 569.425,30.349 C568.659,28.377 567.633,26.702 565.965,25.035 C564.297,23.368 562.623,22.342 560.652,21.575 C558.743,20.834 556.562,20.326 553.369,20.18 C550.169,20.033 549.148,20 541,20 C532.853,20 531.831,20.033 528.631,20.18 C525.438,20.326 523.257,20.834 521.349,21.575 C519.376,22.342 517.703,23.368 516.035,25.035 C514.368,26.702 513.342,28.377 512.574,30.349 C511.834,32.258 511.326,34.438 511.181,37.631 C511.035,40.831 511,41.851 511,50 C511,58.147 511.035,59.17 511.181,62.369 C511.326,65.562 511.834,67.743 512.574,69.651 C513.342,71.625 514.368,73.296 516.035,74.965 C517.703,76.634 519.376,77.658 521.349,78.425 C523.257,79.167 525.438,79.673 528.631,79.82 C531.831,79.965 532.853,80.001 541,80.001 C549.148,80.001 550.169,79.965 553.369,79.82 C556.562,79.673 558.743,79.167 560.652,78.425 C562.623,77.658 564.297,76.634 565.965,74.965 C567.633,73.296 568.659,71.625 569.425,69.651 C570.167,67.743 570.674,65.562 570.82,62.369 C570.966,59.17 571,58.147 571,50 C571,41.851 570.966,40.831 570.82,37.631"></path></g></g></g></svg></div><div style="padding-top: 8px;"> <div style=" color:#3897f0; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:550; line-height:18px;">View this post on Instagram</div></div><div style="padding: 12.5% 0;"></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; margin-bottom: 14px; align-items: center;"><div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(0px) translateY(7px);"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; height: 12.5px; transform: rotate(-45deg) translateX(3px) translateY(1px); width: 12.5px; flex-grow: 0; margin-right: 14px; margin-left: 2px;"></div> <div style="background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; height: 12.5px; width: 12.5px; transform: translateX(9px) translateY(-18px);"></div></div><div style="margin-left: 8px;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 50%; flex-grow: 0; height: 20px; width: 20px;"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 2px solid transparent; border-left: 6px solid #f4f4f4; border-bottom: 2px solid transparent; transform: translateX(16px) translateY(-4px) rotate(30deg)"></div></div><div style="margin-left: auto;"> <div style=" width: 0px; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-right: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(16px);"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; flex-grow: 0; height: 12px; width: 16px; transform: translateY(-4px);"></div> <div style=" width: 0; height: 0; border-top: 8px solid #F4F4F4; border-left: 8px solid transparent; transform: translateY(-4px) translateX(8px);"></div></div></div> <div style="display: flex; flex-direction: column; flex-grow: 1; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 24px;"> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; margin-bottom: 6px; width: 224px;"></div> <div style=" background-color: #F4F4F4; border-radius: 4px; flex-grow: 0; height: 14px; width: 144px;"></div></div></a><p style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; line-height:17px; margin-bottom:0; margin-top:8px; overflow:hidden; padding:8px 0 7px; text-align:center; text-overflow:ellipsis; white-space:nowrap;"><a href="https://www.instagram.com/reel/CgJedNGBCXS/?utm_source=ig_embed&amp;utm_campaign=loading" style=" color:#c9c8cd; font-family:Arial,sans-serif; font-size:14px; font-style:normal; font-weight:normal; line-height:17px; text-decoration:none;" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A post shared by Sudhi Sudhin (@pet_traveller__)</a></p></div></blockquote> <script async="" src="//www.instagram.com/embed.js"></script>



<h2 id="h-fulfilling-a-long-cherished-dream">Fulfilling a long-cherished dream</h2>



<p>Growing up, Sudheesh recalls that<a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/290444/experience-slow-travel-curated-immersive-journeys-in-sikkim-arunachal-ladakh/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> his love for travelling</a> began during his school days, when most of his classmates went on school tours he had to stay back as his family couldn’t afford the expense. “Since then, it turned out to be one of my life goals to travel a lot and explore different places,” he adds.</p>



<p>“So, when I got a job, I started saving up and going for small trips within Kerala with my family and sometimes solo,” says Sudheesh, who works as a shop manager in a medical store.</p>



<p>While planning for his longtime <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/282723/best-homestays-in-ladakh-things-to-do-in-leh-local-experience/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dream journey to Ladakh</a>, he knew that his monthly earnings wouldn’t suffice. So, he started working as a food delivery agent for Zomato post his work, from evening till midnight. He says his wife Amrutha and his parents stood by him in all his endeavours.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image size-full wp-image-292258">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img width="1200" height="628" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115.jpg" alt="Sudheeh and Snowbell" class="wp-image-292258" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115-300x157.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115-500x262.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115-768x402.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Sudheeh-and-Snowbell-1659017115-150x79.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>Sudheeh and Snowbell</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>“By doing two jobs I was able to make a decent earning for my family as well as save up something for my trip. I even work extra at times to meet the budget whenever I plan trips,” he says, adding, “The Ladakh trip was also under a strict low budget. We just spent around Rs 50,000 for the entire trip including food and fuel.”</p>



<p>Sudheesh and Snowbell’s Ladakh trip was on a 100 cc Herohonda splendour on which they carried their camping essentials including a camping stove, tent, sleeping bags and so on. “I did think of buying a 200 cc off-roading bike for this trip but I couldn’t afford the price. So, I dropped the idea and went ahead with my humble chariot which I have been riding for the past three years. It was in good condition and had decent mileage,” explains Sudheesh.</p>



<p>When he decided <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/196674/air-travel-pet-rules-book-indian-railways-flight-train-charges/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to take Snowbell with him</a>, Sudheesh says that he wasn’t sure about how to set up a special seat for him which was both safe and comfortable. “I found several videos on the internet, from outside India where people set up a special canine carrier for their dogs. I was impressed by a model that I felt was perfect for Snowbell. So, I designed a similar model and made the carrier with the help of a welder. We also did upholstery work to make sure that the seats were comfortable for Snowbell,” he elaborates.</p>



<p>After fixing the seat, to test the waters, Sudheesh started taking Snowbell on his bike to smaller distances in the vicinity. “Right from the time I got him, I have been training him in everything. He is very clever and has always been obedient. I was impressed by the fact that he was equally excited as me,” he says, adding that eventually, through training, Snowbell got his way around travelling on the customised seat.</p>



<p>Before starting the journey Snowbell was taken to a veterinarian to check if he was fit enough to go on a trip. “The doctor said he was healthy and we got him vaccinated. He also received a fitness certificate. Besides, as per the doctor’s suggestion I also bought a few gears like helmet, goggles and raincoat for Snowbell to make his journey safer,” he says.</p>



<h2 id="h-off-to-the-mountains">Off to the mountains</h2>



<p>Starting their trip from Edappally in Kochi, the duo crossed over 15 states <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/260689/covid-19-tourist-ladakh-restrictions-rules-rt-pcr-report-travel/">to reach Ladakh</a>. On their way back they skipped the Northeastern region due to heavy rains at that time.</p>



<p>Sudheesh says one of his favourite places they visited was Jammu and Kashmir where the duo spent over a week. “I was mesmerised by the beauty of the place and I am sure Snowbell was too. We also went trekking in Gulmarg. It was an unforgettable experience for both of us as we experienced snow for the first time in life,” he gushes.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image size-full wp-image-292256">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img width="1200" height="628" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437.jpg" alt="Photos of Sudheesh and Snowbell from Ladakh (left) and Dal Lake (right)." class="wp-image-292256" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437-300x157.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437-500x262.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437-768x402.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Photos-of-Sudheesh-and-Snowbell-from-Ladakh-left-and-Dal-Lake-right.-1659016437-150x79.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>Photos of Sudheesh and Snowbell from Ladakh (left) and Dal Lake (right).</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The duo also trekked the Kalsubai peak, one of the tallest peaks in Maharashtra. “The Kalsubai trek was a bit difficult for Snowbell as there were certain places which were really steep. So, I carried him. It was Snowbells’ first trek and I felt that it made him more confident while we trekked in other locations,” says Sudheesh, adding that they also went for a 42 km trek in Kedarnath.</p>



<p>Finally, when they reached Ladakh, he says that they spent a few days in Nubra Valley. Besides, they were thrilled to witness the Himalayan ranges and the famous Pangong Lake in real life.</p>



<p>Sudheesh and Snowbell camped in their tent at night. Though it was an amazing experience to be able to travel across the country, Sudheesh says it wasn’t without its challenges.</p>



<p>“There were objections from the people in some neighbourhoods and also sometimes from the police as well. We had instances where we had to remove our tents and travel throughout the night till we found another place,” he says.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image size-full wp-image-292261">
<figure class="aligncenter"><img width="1200" height="628" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436.jpg" alt="Glimpses from their trip to Ladakh." class="wp-image-292261" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436.jpg 1200w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436-300x157.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436-500x262.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436-768x402.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/Glimpses-from-their-trip-to-Ladakh..-1659017436-150x79.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px" /><figcaption>Glimpses from their trip to Ladakh.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>But despite the hiccups, he adds that the best part of the journey was that they got to meet a lot of people from different states and cultures. “Wherever we went people were curious to see Snowbell on my bike and it became a conversation starter everywhere,” he says with a smile.</p>



<p>Sudheesh says that cooking breakfast and dinner saved them a lot of money as<a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/215292/travel-cheap-budget-travel-tips-low-cost-couple-romantic-rajasthan-india-valentines-day-gop94/"> they were on a budget</a>. “We only had lunch from outside. Otherwise, we cooked and ate something light and healthy for breakfast and dinner,” he points out.</p>



<p>After returning home and fulfilling his longtime dream, Sudheesh says that it was worth all the efforts. “I had the best travel partner and I am happy that I could give Snowbell an experience of a lifetime. In return I would say that he made the trip even more special and less lonely for me,” he says, with a hopeful glimmer of returning to the northeast with his fury friend soon.</p>



<p><em>Edited by Yoshita Rao</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Why a 130-YO Crocodile Named Gangaram Has a Memorial Dedicated to Him</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/291236/gangaram-crocodile-village-charotar-gujarat-shetpal-snakes-human-coexistence/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sanchari Pal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2022 14:32:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Chhattisgarh]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal lovers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[crocodile memorial]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[gangaram crocodile]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[human wildlife coexistence]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nature]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[wildlife india]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=291236</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[When Gangaram passed away, he was carried to its funeral on a tractor decorated with garlands, with over 500 people attending its last rites.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“<span style="font-size: 42px; color: #004697;">H</span>e was not a crocodile but a friend,” Basawan, a resident of Bawa Mohtara village in Chhattisgarh’s Bemetara district, told Hindustan Times after the death of the 130-year-old Gangaram in 2019.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/161695/crocodile-whisperers-india-news/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Crocodiles are widely feared</a>, but not in Bawa Mohtara. This is because, for the longest time, this tiny village was home to Gangaram, one of the most docile members of this dangerous predator species.</p>
<p>Loved and revered by his village, Gangaram would swim peacefully alongside young children while their mothers washed clothes on the banks of his pond. No one was ever attacked by him, and the villagers responded with respect, ensuring that the croc was never harmed.</p>
<p>In short, he broke the mould of ‘vicious crocodile’ and his fellow villagers <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/133895/dantewada-nurse-crocodile/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">broke the ‘cruel human’ one</a>.</p>
<p>Bawa Mohtara was known as the ‘Magarmachha-vala gaon’, because of Gangaram’s peaceful presence in the village pond. So when he passed away of natural causes after a long life, the entire village assembled to grieve and bid an emotional adieu to their beloved crocodile.</p>
<p>He was carried to its funeral on a tractor decorated with garlands, with over 500 people attending its last rites. Many of the grief-stricken villagers also didn’t cook food that day. In the years that followed, the residents of Bawa Mohtara set up a memorial in Gangaram’s honour on the pond’s bank.</p>
<p><figure id="attachment_291256" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-291256" style="width: 540px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-291256 size-full" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/fb_img_1658235312789-1658240014.jpg" alt="130-year-old Gangaram, a crocodile in Chhattisgarh, is thronged by a large crowd" width="540" height="930" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/fb_img_1658235312789-1658240014.jpg 540w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/fb_img_1658235312789-1658240014-174x300.jpg 174w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/fb_img_1658235312789-1658240014-500x861.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/fb_img_1658235312789-1658240014-150x258.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 540px) 100vw, 540px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-291256" class="wp-caption-text">Source: People For Animals</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Interestingly, Bawa Mohtara isn’t the only village in India to witness such <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/237460/west-bengal-woman-activist-wildlife-protection-act-1972-hunting-antipoaching-ngo-heal-india-ana79/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a peaceful coexistence</a> between predators and humans.</p>
<p>In Gujarat’s Charotar district, humans and crocodiles go about their business without attacking or even disturbing each other. According to surveys by the local NGO, Voluntary Nature Conservancy, there are at least 164 resident mugger crocodiles in Charotar’s 30 villages, an area that packs over 600 people per sq km.</p>
<p>Almost every pond in these villages is abuzz with crocodile activity but this doesn’t deter the residents from swimming in them, washing their cattle and clothes, and harvesting water chestnuts. The reptiles, meanwhile, raise their young on the same banks, basking in the sun and crawling through the grass where cattle graze and children play.</p>
<p>Yes, there are the occasional attacks but they are way lesser than the norm. So much so, that the residents of Charotar not only make excuses for these rare attacks, they also plan to dig extra ponds to give the crocs more space!</p>
<p><figure id="attachment_291257" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-291257" style="width: 1079px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-291257 size-full" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060.jpg" alt="crocodiles lounge in the water" width="1079" height="1156" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060.jpg 1079w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060-280x300.jpg 280w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060-500x536.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060-768x823.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/07/screenshot_20220719-183031_chrome-1658240060-150x161.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1079px) 100vw, 1079px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-291257" class="wp-caption-text">Source: crocodilecount.org</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>Little wonder the wetlands of Charotar have proven to be <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/167113/rajasthan-hero-animal-rescue-wildlife-inspiring-india/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the safest haven for the giant reptile</a> species in Gujarat. Talking of safe havens for reptiles, this story would be incomplete without a nod to Shetpal, the unique village in Maharashtra’s Solapur district where snakes are considered family.</p>
<p>In Shetpal, it is a normal occurrence to see snakes slither around people’s homes and even through school classrooms. In fact, each house in the village, no matter how tiny, keeps aside a hollow space known as ‘devasthanam’ (abode of the deity) where snakes can rest and cool off at any time.</p>
<p>Bawa Mohatra, Charotar and Shetpal are all just beautiful examples of humans and wild reptiles co-adapting to living in shared landscapes.</p>
<p>But <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/81447/animal-ark-wild-animals-asylum-dr-prakash-amte-hemalkhasa/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">human-wildlife coexistence</a> is more than a conservation concern, it is just as much a humanitarian and development concern. By avoiding persecuting the wildlife living around our habitats, we humans safeguard the health of our ecosystem, and therefore our own well-being and future food security.</p>
<p>In fact, one in five of all reptile species in the world are threatened by extinction, which could be a ‘devastating’ blow to the planet’s biodiversity, according to a study by Nature.</p>
<p>“If we remove reptiles, it could change ecosystems radically, with unfortunate knock-on effects, such as increases in pests and insects. Biodiversity, including reptiles, underpins the ecosystem services that provide a healthy environment for people,” Neil Cox, co-leader of the aforementioned study at the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN), told the Guardian.</p>
<p>So, at a time when human-reptile conflict is often in the news, Gangaram’s endearing story comes across as a beacon of hope. One can also hope that there are more Gangarams out there, waiting to be discovered, loved and protected by humans.</p>
<h5><em>Sources</em></h5>
<h5 class="hdg1"><em><a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/india-news/500-people-attend-last-rites-of-beloved-130-years-old-crocodile-in-chhattisgarh-village/story-a99uY31NnoAgi4mEYx5NuN.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">500 people attend last rites of beloved 130-years-old crocodile in Chhattisgarh village</a> by Ritesh Mishra, Published on 10 January 2019. </em></h5>
<h5 id="main-heading" class="ssrcss-15xko80-StyledHeading e1fj1fc10" tabindex="-1"><em><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-asia-india-46983559" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Indians sharing their villages with crocodiles</a> by Anirudh Vasava, Published on 31 January 2019. </em></h5>
<h5 class="c-article-title" data-test="article-title"><em><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-022-04664-7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">A global reptile assessment highlights shared conservation needs of tetrapods</a> by Nature, Published on 27 April 2022. </em></h5>
<h5 class="dcr-125vfar"><em><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/environment/2022/apr/27/one-in-five-reptiles-face-extinction-in-devastating-blow-to-biodiversity-aoe?utm_term=Autofeed&amp;CMP=twt_b-gdnnews&amp;utm_medium=Social&amp;utm_source=Twitter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">One in five reptiles faces extinction in what would be a ‘devastating’ blow</a> by The Guardian, Published on 19 May 2022. </em></h5>
<p><em>Edited by Yoshita Rao</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DU Students Use Savings to Start Community Kitchen for Dogs, Rescue Over 1000 Strays</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/289461/delhi-university-students-open-community-kitchen-to-feed-stray-dogs-pawriwar/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Krystelle Dsouza]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 13:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Animal Welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Delhi]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal adoptions]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Community Kitchen]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stray animals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[stray dogs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=289461</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How to help stray animals? These students have some ideas for you.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 42px; color: #004697;">E</span>very evening, as dusk settles, college students around the national capital come to the end of a long day of lectures and assignments. Their chatter suggests that they have plans to relax, and probably grab a bite to eat before they head home.</p>
<p>But for two students of Delhi University — Arts student Jasdeep Kaur (Jiya) and law student Ishan Joshi — the schedule is slightly different.</p>
<p>Every day after classes, they head to the areas around Laxmi Bai Nagar in New Delhi to feed more than 200 stray animals. This is part of their initiative Pawriwar, which was started in 2020, as a way of reaching out to these strays.</p>
<p>The latest addition to this venture is the community kitchen that they have set up for animals.</p>
<h2>A mission born of empathy</h2>
<p>It all began in 2020.</p>
<p>“The government had introduced a redevelopment policy that called for the reconstruction of government colonies. With residents being shifted elsewhere, strays were stripped of their only source of food,” says Jiya, adding that the unprecedented lockdown that followed made things worse.</p>
<p>“Local food joints shut down, and Ishan and I wanted to rise to the occasion. So we put together our savings and started feeding strays.”</p>
<p>Along with taking care of their food requirements, the duo would also <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/205001/how-to-adopt-dog-army-india-pet-adoption-dog-shelter-process-procedure/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">take care of adoptions</a>, vaccinations, and rescue services. What started as a one-time feeding drive for 20 strays was now shaping up to be an endeavour that cared for over 250 animals every day. This was when Ishan, who managed the finances of the venture, realised that the costs were exceeding their budget.</p>
<p>Prior to this, the duo had been procuring meals from different community kitchens around Delhi to feed the strays, the latest being in the Tughlakabad extension. So on realising the rising costs, Ishan came up with an idea — turning his home’s backyard into a kitchen.</p>
<p><figure id="attachment_289477" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-289477" style="width: 1024px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-289477 size-full" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236.jpg" alt="Jiya and Ishan's community kitchen" width="1024" height="768" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236.jpg 1024w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236-300x225.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236-500x375.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236-768x576.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0002-1656423236-150x113.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-289477" class="wp-caption-text">Jiya and Ishan&#8217;s community kitchen</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>“This way, we would also have the flexibility of payment,” he says.</p>
<h2>A community kitchen for strays</h2>
<p>How tough was it for two college students to build a community kitchen in the backyard?</p>
<p>“Very,” replies Ishan, but adds that they knew this would be beneficial in the time to come.</p>
<p>So they went about placing a stove and some utensils in the space, but soon realised that harsh weather would interrupt their plans. To tackle this, they decided to cover the area with a shed. The entire process took them a week to set up.</p>
<p>Work begins in the early evening hours, Jiya says. “The cook starts preparing the chicken and rice at around 4.30 pm, after which the food is left to cool down,” she explains. Then, Jiya mixes the food and divides it into small packets. The duo then hands over the packets to daily wage workers at construction sites, who have been feeding the animals for a couple of months now. Once they ensure that the animals have been fed, they then proceed to feed some more strays in Sarojini Nagar, Netaji Nagar, and Narouji Nagar, as well as some areas of Safdarjung Enclave and Laxmi Bai Nagar.</p>
<p><figure id="attachment_289478" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-289478" style="width: 1359px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-289478 size-full" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333.jpg" alt="Jiya and Ishan go around the areas of South Delhi feeding stray animals" width="1359" height="1019" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333.jpg 1359w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333-300x225.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333-500x375.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333-768x576.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0003_11zon-1656423333-150x112.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1359px) 100vw, 1359px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-289478" class="wp-caption-text">Jiya and Ishan go around the areas of South Delhi feeding stray animals</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>The 18-20 kg of chicken and 25-30 kg of rice prepared are enough to feed over 200 dogs and cats every day, the duo says. Apart from the regular feeding, Ishan and Jiya also feed monkeys and cows twice a week.</p>
<p>Having their own <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/266374/community-kitchens-help-marginalised-women-transgenders-skill-training-golden-heart-foundation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">community kitchen</a> has helped them tremendously, says Jiya. “It helps us save money in many ways. Since we are not the ones to cook and distribute the food, we can control our resources and expenses.”</p>
<p>While their work is impressive, they face the constant challenge of lack of funds.</p>
<p>“We’ve never had stability when it comes to managing expenses,” she says, adding that the crowdfunding they do through social media platforms does not help much. So they put in their own savings. As their monthly expenses go up to Rs 45,000, the duo is constantly looking for support.</p>
<p>With a goal to expand their feeding in different areas of Delhi and ensure that no stray is going to sleep with an empty stomach, they wish to expand further.</p>
<p>To date, Pawriwar has also managed to get 113 stray dogs adopted and fostered, and rescued over 1,000. They have also got stray animals sterilised through their vaccine drives.</p>
<p>Jiya says that the duo provides preliminary care for minor wounds, scratches, etc, while for more serious cases, their veterinary friend Shibangini Das helps them with the amount of dosage required, antibiotics, and oral medications. They then call her in for a consult.</p>
<p><figure id="attachment_289479" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-289479" style="width: 1510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img class="wp-image-289479 size-full" src="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393.jpg" alt="Jiya and Ishan go around the areas of South Delhi feeding stray animals" width="1510" height="1132" srcset="https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393.jpg 1510w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393-300x225.jpg 300w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393-500x375.jpg 500w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393-768x576.jpg 768w, https://en-media.thebetterindia.com/uploads/2022/06/IMG-20220628-WA0004_11zon-1656423393-150x112.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 1510px) 100vw, 1510px" /><figcaption id="caption-attachment-289479" class="wp-caption-text">Jiya and Ishan go around the areas of South Delhi feeding stray animals</figcaption></figure></p>
<p>“If required, we sometimes bring home a stray that has been hurt and foster them as well. Apart from this, we encourage people to adopt our Indie kids, and we’ve found families for over 100 kids so far,” says Jiya.</p>
<p>However, due to limited resources and hands on deck, they find it tough to respond to every plea for help. But it is their love for animals that keeps them going.</p>
<p>“If we won&#8217;t do it, no one else will,” she says adding that these animals rely on them for the only meal they get in a day.</p>
<p>For Ishan and Jiya, who have been fond of strays since their playschool days, Pawriwar is a way for them to now reach out in a substantial way to these animals.</p>
<p>But they face their own set of challenges.</p>
<p>“We sometimes receive calls from Noida and Gurugram, but cannot go to these areas as they are far,” says Jiya. In these cases, they ask the person contacting them to do the primary treatment and guide them virtually after a consultation with a vet. Once the animal gets better, they get in touch with other stray support groups in the area and ask them to take charge.</p>
<p>To aid in their operations, they soon plan to open a <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286906/dog-home-foundation-stray-animals-shelter-jodhpur-donation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shelter for injured strays</a> to be treated and fostered, as well as start an ambulance service to be able to rescue injured animals in the shortest time possible. They also plan to expand their services across Delhi.</p>
<p><em>If you wish to donate to this cause, <a href="https://milaap.org/fundraisers/support-stray-animals-333?utm_source=whatsapp&amp;utm_medium=fundraisers-title&amp;mlp_referrer_id=4677373" target="_blank" rel="noopener">click here</a> to do so.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 Pawfect Indian Brands Offering Natural &#038; Healthy Organic Treats for Your Pets</title>
		<link>https://www.thebetterindia.com/287979/healthy-pet-treats-brands-buy-natural-organic-dog-cat-food-amazon/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anjali Krishnan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2022 13:32:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Affiliate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Animal Welfare]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Amazon buy]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[animal food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BARF India]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[FurrMeals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Heads Up For Tails]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[healthy dog food]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[pet food]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.thebetterindia.com/?p=287979</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Pet parents take note — from yummy yak cheese treats to ready-to-eat wet food, there is a long list of healthy food options for your furry friends.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>This article contains affiliate links. If you purchase something using one of these links, The Better India will get a small commission.</em></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 42px; color: #004697;">M</span>ore and more Indians are opting to be ‘pet parents’ in India, with 6 in 10 Indians now owning pets. But when it comes to finding organic pet food and treats for your pets, there are a lot of things to consider like the pet’s breed, age, allergies, lifestyle and nutrient requirements. As every brand offers a huge variety of <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286670/best-indian-food-influencers-instagram-traditional-easy-to-cook-recipes/">flavours, proteins and ingredients</a>, it could be often confusing to make the right choice for organic pet food.</p>
<p>So, here are a few brands that provide natural, grain-free, preservative-free and healthy food and treats for pets.</p>
<h2>1. Heads up for tails &#8211; Organic pet food</h2>
<p>Heads Up For Tails is one of India’s first pet care brands and a store dedicated to furry friends. Started as a small business by Delhi-based Rashi Narang in 2008, the brand now has a strong customer base with over 30 stores in six different cities.</p>
<p>From accessories to food, they offer all things essentials for your pet dog or cat. They have a wide variety of premium quality products from their brand as well as curated from a variety of brands.</p>
<p>When it comes to food, they have a long list of different categories like dry food, wet food, puppy food, kitten food, organic pet food and so on that are free of artificial preservatives, colourants or flavours.</p>
<p>Buy their ‘real chicken dog biscuits’ <a href="https://amzn.to/39evyzT">here</a>.</p>
<h2>2. Licks and Crunch</h2>
<p>Started by Indore-based Surbhi Hablani in 2020, the pet food brand Licks &amp; Crunch makes gourmet dog treats, which are grain-free, gluten-free and preservative-free. This Instagram-based dog food startup makes innovative and yummy treats, which are prepared after thorough research. They use several herbs and Indian spices to make the food more delicious as well as nutritious.</p>
<p>Surbhi runs the business out of her kitchen at home along with her mother and co-founder, Ritu Hablani.</p>
<p>Check out their products <a href="https://www.instagram.com/licksandcrunch/?hl=en">here</a>.</p>
<h2>3. BARF India</h2>
<p>The BARF India claims to make natural and healthy food for dogs that are free from grains, preservatives, colourants, fillers and anything artificial. They aim to dramatically improve the health, longevity, and quality of life of pets by promoting an evolutionary diet, and a host of holistic health care solutions. They formulate a balanced blend of raw meat, fruits, vegetables and bones.</p>
<p>They have a wide range of jerkies, dehydrated grain-free dog food and cat food.</p>
<p>Buy their raw dog food chicken recipe <a href="https://amzn.to/3mqAa92">here</a>.</p>
<h2>4. FurrMeals</h2>
<p>Launched by Sujata Bhattacharya, a passionate pet mom, FurrMeals aims at providing natural, healthy, preservative-free food and treats for pets.</p>
<p>When Sujata started her venture in 2018, she was driven by a passion to provide better <a href="https://www.thebetterindia.com/286691/sattu-health-benefits-indian-food-recipes-for-summer/">nutrition </a>to her pet dog Buddy along with thousands of other furry babies like him.<br />
Designed by a group of highly skilled and qualified canine nutritionists, the brand uses only high-quality protein, vitamin-rich veggies, and immunity-boosting herbs to make its recipes healthy.<br />
They have a range of unique recipes like veg and non-vegetarian, natural, ready-to-eat, wet dog food in multiple protein options, natural treats and the ‘first-of-its-kind’ ready-to-serve chicken bone broth for dogs and cats.</p>
<p>Buy their wet dog food <a href="https://amzn.to/3Q28MM6">here</a>.</p>
<h2>5. Captain Zack</h2>
<p>Started in 2016 when owner and founder, Mohit Lalvani was unable to find a good shampoo and conditioner for his pup Zack, who had sensitive skin. He then put his three-decade-long personal care and pharma experience to use which led him to formulate a non-irritant, gentle, and pH balanced shampoo for his puppy Zack which eventually led to the formation of the brand — Captain Zack.<br />
Now the brand provides, well researched, innovative and safe range of products that contribute to pets’ overall well being.</p>
<p>They have a range of nutrition packed ready-to-eat and cooked food, treats and even cake mixes for dogs and treats for cats.</p>
<p>Buy their ready-to-eat wet food with gravy <a href="https://amzn.to/3H5PBNf">here</a>.</p>
<h2>6. Doggie Dabbas</h2>
<p>A wellness brand for dogs and cats, the Doggies Dabbas was started by Rashee Kuchroo who was inspired by the health issues faced by her Labrador, Sloppy, to make home-cooked meals in New Delhi.<br />
Every product is handcrafted with love and has been formulated after detailed nutritional research and testing. The treats are yummy and each ingredient involved in them carries several health benefits.<br />
They have a range of freeze-dried food for your dogs, fresh meals and treats that are made with fresh, preservative and gluten-free ingredients.</p>
<p>Buy their high protein dog treats <a href="https://amzn.to/3tkYBsw">here</a>.</p>
<h2>7. Dogsee chew</h2>
<p>Dogsee chew was started in 2015 by husband and wife duo Bhupendra Khanal and Sneh Sharma in Bengaluru to provide dogs with natural, gluten-free, and grain-free treats. They started the venture when they found it difficult to get healthy treats for their pet, a Golden Retriever pet named Mowgli.<br />
During their research to find a good alternative for bones or rawhides, they discovered Chhurpi, a hard yak cheese which is rich in protein and had bone-like hardness. Thus they introduced it as a healthy treat across the globe as Dogsee Chew Hard Bars.</p>
<p>Besides, all their products are organic with even 100 per cent vegetarian treats or chews for dogs that work as an alternative to bones or rawhide.</p>
<p>Buy their Himalayan cheese-based dental chews for dogs <a href="https://amzn.to/3Q9sIwD">here</a>.</p>
<h2>8. Luvin</h2>
<p>Luvin is a dog-food brand by Ipshit Bhattacharya, a B Tech graduate in Food Technology and a canine nutritionist. He decided to come up with a brand after the realisation that most pet parents are not informed about balanced, home-cooked meals and indigenous products.<br />
The brand’s first offering was a complete and balanced, mono-protein, a grain-free meal full of natural goodness where each ingredient has been purposefully curated to ensure the complete health and wellbeing of canine companions.</p>
<p>They provide a range of human-grade, grain-free, vegetarian and non-vegetarian treats for dogs and cats.</p>
<p>Buy their grain-free chicken recipe for cats <a href="https://amzn.to/3xxZqke">here</a>.</p>
<h2>9. Kennel Kitchen</h2>
<p>Kennel Kitchen was founded by Awral Beri in his family kitchen in Alwar, Rajasthan, in 2011. He started making home-cooked food for his family dogs to ensure that they were eating the most nutritious and wholesome food possible. Eventually, it turned into a flourishing business with the introduction of more recipes for dogs and cats and a larger team to work for it.</p>
<p>They use the best quality ingredients that provide high levels of protein, fats, vitamins and minerals. They only use fresh and wholesome ingredients sourced locally and directly from farmers.<br />
The brand offers a range of jerky treats, gravies, soft-baked treats, pate and more.<br />
Buy their wet dog food lamb chunks in gravy <a href="https://amzn.to/3aEAKNZ">here</a>.</p>
<h2>10. Pawfectly made</h2>
<p>Founded by Bengaluru-based Arpita Ganesh, Pawfectly aimed to bring healthy and wholesome food solutions for pets.</p>
<p>Their food is handcrafted with love, and care and is made with the best ingredients. Also, they make it convenient and affordable for pet parents to be able to switch to healthier pet food.<br />
All their meals claim to be free of any preservatives or additives and carefully handmade using fresh meats and veggies.</p>
<p>Check out their products <a href="https://www.instagram.com/pawfectlymadeforpets/?hl=en">here</a>.</p>
<p>Source:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.cnbctv18.com/videos/lifestyle/study-finds-6-in-10-indians-now-have-a-pet-heres-whats-fuelling-the-pet-care-industry-11496972.htm">&#8220;Study finds 6 in 10 Indians now have a pet; here’s what’s fuelling the pet care industry&#8221;</a>; Published by CNBC TV18 on 17 November 2021</p>
<p><em>Edited by Yoshita Rao</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
